Template talk:Nesdbbox

If you can set unif's search type to be "unif_op=LIKE+`%25%40%25`" then we can use SQL GLOBs in the template rather than having to enumerate all the variants, q.v. "http://bootgod.dyndns.org:7777/search.php?unif_op=LIKE+%60%25%40%25%60&unif=A%25ROM" —Lidnariq (talk) 04:01, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

Well, technically you could make any search string you like, the form is just "PARAM1"="PARAM2" so you could just cram "unif_op"="LIKE+%60%25%40%25%60&unif=A%25ROM" into the string, but if you can explain how that URL you just made work I could try and make an easy-to-use form of this for the template. What does unif_op do? What does "LIKE+`%@%`" mean? Is the % in A%ROM a wildcard character that the LIKE operation expands? (Is this documented somewhere?)
What would you like the template code to look like? Something like this?

{{nesdblink|unif_wildcard|A%ROM|AxROM}}

- Rainwarrior (talk) 10:56, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

In SQL-ese, "LIKE" gets you globs like filename ? and *, and "_" and "%" are equivalent to ? and *. @ here is substituted with the value of the unif parameter. (But "LIKE" is case-insensitive, while "GLOB" is case-insensitive.)
But, yes, something like your example would be lovely. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:48, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

Added. - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:40, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

Something that might make things easier for making queries sufficiently restrictive would be to change it to "LIKE `@`" and the query to "%-A%ROM", i.e. move the globs into the query and out of the "op"eration. On the other hand, searching for "LIKE `%A%ROM%`" produces 128 hits, for "LIKE `%A%ROM`" produces 112, and for mapper 7 produces 76 hits, so it's still rather inadequate. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:25, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

Text compression

Text compression refers to techniques that allow fitting more text data into a smaller space. General-purpose compression formats that work well on a platform with relatively plentiful RAM, such as a PC, Nintendo 64, or Nintendo DS, may not work on platforms whose RAM is much smaller, such as the NES.

Contents

1 Dictionary compression and DTE

1.1 Simon's Quest (NES)
1.2 Chrono Trigger (SNES)
1.3 Joel Yliluoma's ppu_read_buffer test (NES)
1.4 Damian Yerrick's robotfindskitten (NES)

2 Bitrate reduction methods

2.1 Fixed-bit encoding
2.2 Variable-bit encodings

2.2.1 Huffman coding
2.2.2 Arithmetic coding

3 LZ based methods

Dictionary compression and DTE

Dictionary compression is a technique where part of the character set is reserved to denote references to a "dictionary". If the byte falls into this range, a string is copied from the dictionary rather than the byte being copied verbatim. It could be considered the textual equivalent of metatiles in scrolling maps. As this compression technique does not require knowledge of past data, it is very easy to implement on machines having little memory like the NES.

Sometimes the compression may be applied recursively, where the dictionary string itself may contain references to other dictionary strings.

Dual-tile encoding, or DTE for short, is a special case of dictionary compression. It is also known as byte-pair encoding, or digram coding. In this case, the dictionary strings are all two bytes long.

Example implementations:

Simon's Quest (NES)

In Simon's Quest (NES) (all versions), the font is 252 symbols long, although only a small part of that is actual text symbols used in dialog text.

Value | Meaning
00–FB | Print this symbol.
FC | Denotes the end of a substring. Restores the string pointer saved by opcode FD.
FD | Save current string pointer. The next byte determines the string number; this number will be used to calculate the new string pointer. Interpreting will continue from that address.
FE | Newline.
FF | End of text. If used in a substring, will not return to the main string. A string that ends in FD can omit the trailing FF, if the substring ends in FF.

Dictionary strings are arbitrary length. There is room for only one saved string pointer, so substrings can not refer to other substrings, unless it is to terminate the entire string. The substring mechanism is used in the Japanese diskette version of the game. The cartridge versions of the game also support this mechanism, even though the actual text data does not utilize it.

Chrono Trigger (SNES)

In Chrono Trigger (SNES) (all versions), the font is 768 symbols long, but a significant number of those symbols can not be printed.

Value | Meaning
00 | End of string.
01 | Read next byte; print symbol byte+0x100.
02 | Read next byte; print symbol byte+0x200.
03–20 | Various text effects, references to item tables, and references to party member names.
21–xx | Reference to a dictionary string. xx is a compile-time constant that determines the length of the dictionary. This number is 0x9F in the USA version and 0x3F in the Japanese version.
xx+1–FF | Print this symbol.

Dictionary strings have a length limit of 255 bytes. They are not applied recursively. The dictionary strings are stored in length-data format without an end delimiter.

Joel Yliluoma's ppu_read_buffer test (NES)

In Joel Yliluoma's emulator test ROM ppu_read_buffer ([1]) the font is 128 symbols long, and in addition to the alphabet it includes some pre-rendered substrings in variable-width font. The ROM uses a combination of DTE and dictionary for text compression. For DTE, the compression is applied recursively, in both DTE bytes. Additionally the string may contain a jump label to another string, which forms a DAFSA that allows the reuse of the same string suffix in different test descriptions.

Value | Meaning
00 | End of string.
01–80 | Print this symbol. After printing, if the stack pointer is wrong, pop a byte and interpret it rather than loading the next byte from the string.
81–FE | Push DTE_TABLE1[n-0x81] in stack, and interpret DTE_TABLE0[n-0x81].
FF | A 16-bit word follows. This word is loaded as a new string pointer and loading continues from that address. The old string pointer is not saved.

Damian Yerrick's robotfindskitten (NES)

This implementation of robotfindskitten contains a compressor written in Python and a 6502 decompressor. Comments in the compressor (dte.py) refer to the method as "digram tree encoding" for two reasons: to emphasize its recursive nature and because code units aren't "tiles", especially when displayed with a proportional font. The decompressor first copies the compressed string into RAM, into the end of a fixed size buffer, where the first portion of the buffer (and also the string itself) doubles as a stack for the recursive DTE references. The string is then interpreted from the buffer as follows.

Value | Meaning
00 | End of string. This code is only interpreted when copying the compressed string.
00–7F | Print this symbol, and increase the reading position in the compressed string. If the reading position is now at the end of the buffer, the string has ended.
80–FF | Replace the current character with bpe_table[n×2+1] and decrease the reading position in the compressed string. Read bpe_table[n×2+0] and interpret it. The multiplication by 2 discards the carry. The replaced character will be interpreted next, when the decompressor again reads bytes from the compressed string.

Decompressing with a software stack, rather than the hardware stack, would permit a scheme where a subroutine is repeatedly called to decompress one character at a time. The game however does not do that; it decompresses the entire string first, so that it can then perform operations like word-wrap on the decompressed text.

Ignoring the special meaning of byte 00 when decompressing means that the string itself could include raw 00 bytes, if hidden inside the bytepair tables. They could be used e.g. as newlines. The game however does not do that. Byte 0A acts as a newline, as is traditional on Linux and UNIX systems.

Bitrate reduction methods

Fixed-bit encoding

When the character set is small, such as 64 characters at most, strings could be encoded in a bitstream that packs 6 bits per character rather than 8 bits per character. This results in 20 % reduction of data size.

Main article: Fixed Bit Length Encoding

Variable-bit encodings

In variable-bit encodings different symbols are stored in different number of bits.

Example assembler code for reading a MSB-first bit stream (adopted from Tokumaru's tile decompressor):

InitBitReader:
        ; Input:   InputStream = pointer to beginning of bitstream
        ; Output:  Y = buffer position
        ; Clobber: A,ZN
        lda #$80
        sta BitBuffer
        ldy #0
        rts

ReadBits:
        ; Input:   X = number of bits to read (1..8)
        ;          Y = buffer position (modified)
        ; Output:  A = integer read
        ; Clobber: C,ZN
        lda #0
@loop:  jsr ReadBit
        rol a
        dex
        bne @loop
        rts

ReadBit:
        ; Input:   Y = buffer position (modified)
        ; Output:  C = bit
        ; Clobber: ZN
        asl BitBuffer
        bne @ret
        pha
         lda (InputStream), y
         iny
         beq @wrap
@ret0:   rol a
         sta BitBuffer
        pla
@ret:   rts
@wrap:  inc InputStream+1
        bne @ret0

Ideally, you would store common symbols using few bits and infrequent symbols using more bits. Which brings us to…

Huffman coding

A special case of variable-bit encodings is Huffman coding. Huffman coding defines the optimal coding for a given set of symbols based on a table of frequencies that each symbol is used.

When combined with static dictionary coding, the technique is called Huffword.

Arithmetic coding

Huffman coding is also a special case of arithmetic coding. In arithmetic coding, each symbol is represented by a range of binary fractions rather than a particular number of bits. As arithmetic coding was covered by a number of patents up to 1993, and it is calculation intensive, chances are no NES game uses it. However, on the Super NES, the S-DD1 and SPC7110 coprocessors implement a mathematical model that approximates arithmetic coding under license. And by 1999, a design-around called "range coding" was discovered, leading to LZMA compression.

LZ based methods

LZ77 operates based on references to previous decompressed data. Decompression requires that either the previous decompressed data be readable or that a sliding window of previous data be kept in RAM. This isn't very efficient on the NES for two reasons: the CPU is connected to only 2K of RAM (plus whatever is in the cartridge), and VRAM can be accessed only during vblank.

Lempel-Ziv methods are incapable of efficient random access on a low-RAM system. Random access to an LZ77 or LZ78 stream works in one of three ways:

Decompress from the beginning to retrieve a substring. This is time-inefficient for the decompressor.
Compress each substring independently. As LZ77 relies on correlation within a string, this makes the compressed data larger.
Buffer the entire decompressed data in RAM. This requires more memory in the decompressor, but the tradeoff may work well on a platform with more RAM, such as the Commodore 64, Genesis, Super NES, or Game Boy Color.

See also: Tile compression#LZSS

The frame and NMIs

The PPU generates a video signal for one frame of animation, then it rests for a brief period called vertical blanking. The CPU can load graphics data into the PPU only during this rest period. From NMI to the end of the pre-render scanline, the NTSC NES PPU stays off the bus for 2273 cycles. Taking into account overhead to get in and out of the NMI handler, you can probably use roughly 2250 cycles. To get the most out of limited vblank time, don't compute your changes in vblank time. Instead, prepare a buffer in main RAM (for example, use unused parts of the stack at $0100-$019F) before vblank, and then copy from that buffer into VRAM during vblank. On NTSC, count on being able to copy 160 bytes to nametables or the palette using a moderately unrolled loop, plus one 256-byte display list to OAM.

Original Source: The frame and NMIs by Disch

Contents

1 VBlank, Rendering Time, and NMIs
2 Separating Drawing from Logic
3 Buffer Formats
4 Buffering Other Things
5 When to Turn Off PPU, NMIs
6 Take Full Advantage of NMI
7 Being Interrupt-Aware

VBlank, Rendering Time, and NMIs

Many tutorials don't stress how important understanding the frame layout is - in fact, most don't even cover it. At best, they'll casually say something like "you can only draw during VBlank", leaving the reader wondering what in the world VBlank is. This lack of understanding is a major cause of bugs for new NESDev'ers.

Contrary to how it may seem when you run these programs, the code is not executed instantaneously. All code takes a little bit of time to run. While the CPU is spending this time reading your program and executing code, the PPU is simultaneously doing its own work, like things related to outputting video to the TV. When your program communicates with the PPU via one of the registers, you will be poking it at different stages in this process. During some stages, the PPU will be too busy to deal with you, and you will screw things up by trying. This is why it's important to know what stage the PPU is in.

The PPU operates on a series of frames. The PPU does all this work to output a frame to the TV, then it repeats the exact same process for the next frame, and the next, and the next. The frame can further be split into two generalized sections: VBlank and Rendering time.

Rendering time makes up the bulk of the frame. This is the time during which the PPU is fetching tiles, evaluating sprites, and outputting pixels to the screen. The PPU is very busy during this time, so busy that if you try to access it with drawing code, you will screw it up and have visible and possibly disastrous glitches in your game. VBlank, on the other hand, is when the PPU is idle. This is when you can do all of your drawing code safely.

A good way to visualize this by thinking of a clock face, and imagining one frame as one hour. VBlank would be a small portion of that hour, say the first 5 minutes (when the minute hand is between 12 and 1). No matter what you do in your program the minute hand is always spinning around the clock, moving in and out of that 5-minute butterzone... and the PPU is always moving in and out of VBlank. In order to update the PPU in your game, you must make sure your drawing code falls within that small period of time. Failure to do this will cause all sorts of display glitches.

To make matters even more complicated, as a programmer you have no way to actually see this clock in your code, so there is no way to tell whether or not the PPU is currently in VBlank, or how close to VBlank it is, or how much VBlank time is left. There is, however, a way your program can be notified when VBlank first starts (as soon as the minute hand hits the 12 on the clock). This notification comes in the form of an NMI, or "non-maskable interrupt".

Every time that clock hand reaches the 12 and the PPU starts VBlank again, the PPU will attempt to notify you that this has happened. It does this by sending an NMI to your program. These NMIs can be disabled so that you don't have to use them all the time (this is controlled via $2000 (PPUCTRL)). However, in a game you must use them because they are the only [reliable] way to catch VBlank (and thus allow for realtime drawing without turning the PPU off). Plus they are the easiest, most natural, and most convenient logic framerate regulator.

Now, the drawing code I'm talking about so far is stuff that is to be drawn while rendering is enabled. In your program, you can disable rendering (aka, "turn off the PPU") via $2001 (PPUMASK). If rendering is disabled, it is perfectly sane to perform drawing code at any time (even during rendering time). This, however, does not stop that clock hand from moving. Even when 'disabled'. The PPU is still moving in and out of VBlank, and NMIs will still be generated (if enabled).

Note, however, the clear difference between NMI and VBlank. NMI is a notification, whereas VBlank is a time period. A lot of newbies wonder why their drawing code is spilling outside of VBlank when they finish it all before their rti. They think that because NMI happens at the start of VBlank, then rti must be the end of VBlank. This, of course, is totally wrong. As soon as VBlank happens, it's like a race for you to get all of your drawing code done before time is up. Time may run out long before you hit your rti.

Separating Drawing from Logic

The key to ensuring that all of your drawing code happens in VBlank is to separate your drawing code from your logic code. A lot of newbies have a "do it now" mentality when it comes to drawing. Say, for example, they want to draw a text message to the user when the A button is pressed. They might try something like this:

lda a_button
bne draw_message

This might seem like a good way to do it, but it is bad, bad, bad. You should almost never write code like this. This is mixing logic code (examining user input and deciding what to do) with drawing code (actually outputting something to the screen).

The reason this is bad is because drawing code requires you be in VBlank. Therefore the above code must be run in VBlank because it draws. However it also does non-drawing stuff (logic), which can be done any time. Putting logic code in VBlank means you're wasting precious VBlank time on code that doesn't need to use it. This means you burn up your VBlank time that much faster, which reduces the amount of drawing you can get done in a frame, and increases the risk of having drawing code spill outside of VBlank.

A solution to this is to flag that the drawing needs to be done, and then actually do it next VBlank. This could be done like so:

  ;; when processing game logic
  lda a_button
  beq :+          ; if a was pressed...
    inc drawflag  ; set the draw flag
:

  ;; --------------------
  ;;  then, next vblank:

  lda drawflag
  beq :+              ; if draw flag is set
    jsr draw_message  ; actually draw the message
:

However, this in and of itself isn't much of an improvement. draw_message might require some additional logic of its own. And this method isn't very versatile at all. What if there are 10 different ways the screen could update? Do we keep 10 flags and check them all every VBlank? Not very efficient. In practice, you'll want to do something a little more generalized than this, something that will work with virtually everything.

The better solution to this is to buffer your drawing. That is, you copy what you want drawn somewhere to memory, then copy it to the PPU next VBlank. This extra copy might seem wasteful, but in practice it isn't really. It's not as efficient as direct drawing, but the idea is you're sacrificing Rendering time (which you have lots of), to gain more VBlank time (which you have very little of). Doing a little extra work in your logic code to ease up on your drawing code goes a long way.

Buffering is a very common and practical way to accomplish drawing. In fact, you've probably already done it with sprites in your programs. When you update sprite data, you don't write to OAM ($2004) directly (or at least I should hope not), you write to shadow OAM (i.e. a 256-byte region in standard system RAM, most commonly $0200-$02FF) and then later copy that to OAM with Sprite DMA ($4014). That is the same concept that we're doing here. Instead of drawing to the PPU immediately, we're getting it ready to be drawn, and then saying "don't draw it now, draw it next VBlank".

Buffer Formats

In order to employ this buffering technique, you need to give yourself room for the buffer in RAM. Just like you need to designate a full page of RAM to shadow OAM, you should probably designate a significant portion of RAM to your drawing buffer. It doesn't have to be a full page, but you don't want to run out of space.

You also need to decide on a data format in which to store the information that tells your drawing code what to draw, and how to draw it. The best way to do this is to have the drawing code know as little as possible about the rest of your program. Make this format as generic and flexible as possible. Most techniques use a system where you have a chain of "strings" and each "string" tells the drawing code what to draw, where, and how. This is actually much simpler than it sounds. For example, here's a very simple implementation of such a format, and an example of how it would be used:

  byte    0 = length of data (0 = no more data)
  byte    1 = high byte of target PPU address
  byte    2 = low byte of target PPU address
  bytes 3-X = the data to draw (number of bytes determined by the length)

If the drawing buffer contains the following data:

 05 20 16 CA AB 00 EF 05 01 2C 01 00 00 
  | \___/ \____________/  | \___/  |  |
  |   |         |         |   |    |  |
  |   |         |         |   |    |  length (0, so no more)
  |   |         |         |   |    byte to copy
  |   |         |         |   PPU Address $2C01
  |   |         |         length=1
  |   |         bytes to copy
  |   PPU Address $2016
  length=5

Your drawing code, upon coming across this data, would then do the following:

Copy 5 bytes (CA AB 00 EF 05) to PPU address $2016
Copy 1 byte (00) to PPU address $2C01
Come across a length of 0, and thus stop drawing.

To make this work, you fill this buffer during your logic code instead of drawing straight to the PPU. Then in VBlank, you read this buffer and copy the data to the PPU. Because the format lays it out in simple terms, there isn't any heavy calculation that needs to be done to perform this drawing, and thus the drawing can be done very quickly, helping to make sure that it doesn't spill out of VBlank. A format like this is also very flexible. In fact if you make the format flexible enough, you should be able to use it for everything in the game.

The above format, while simple and somewhat flexible, does have one major flaw. That being it doesn't allow you to specify whether or not you want to draw vertical rows of tiles (inc-by-32). To add that functionality, you could tweak the format by adding a flags byte:

  byte    0 = length of data (0 = no more data)
  byte    1 = high byte of target PPU address
  byte    2 = low byte of target PPU address
  byte    3 = drawing flags:
                bit 0 = set if inc-by-32, clear if inc-by-1
  bytes 4-X = the data to draw (number of bytes determined by the length)

Same idea, but now we can draw rows or columns of tiles! This makes the format generic enough so that you can use it to do any drawing task.

But wait. We can add even more to this. What if the data we want to draw is already sitting in ROM somewhere? It's a little wasteful to copy it to RAM, then copy it to the PPU when we can just copy it straight from ROM. Maybe you want to tweak the format a bit to allow for that:

  byte    3 = drawing flags:
                bit 0 = set if inc-by-32, clear if inc-by-1
                bit 1 = set if copy-from-ROM, clear if copy-from-RAM

     if copy-from-RAM:
  bytes 4-X = the data to draw (number of bytes determined by the length)

     if copy-from-ROM:
  bytes 4,5 = CPU address from which to read the data

But wait, there's more! What if you want to draw a bunch of zeros? Like to clear a row of tiles or something? Why copy a bunch of zeros to RAM when you can put in a basic RLE scheme:

  byte    3 = drawing flags:
                bit 0 = set if inc-by-32, clear if inc-by-1
                bit 1 = set if copy-from-ROM, clear if copy-from-RAM
                bit 2 = set if RLE, clear if not RLE

     if copy-from-RAM, not RLE:
  bytes 4-X = the data to draw (number of bytes determined by the length)

     if copy-from-ROM, not RLE:
  bytes 4,5 = CPU address from which to read the data

     if RLE:
  byte    4 = single byte to repeat 'length' times

The possibilities are endless! Beware, however, that the more of these special conditions you add, the bigger and slower your drawing routine gets, which means less stuff can be drawn. It's up to you how far you want to go before drawing the line. Don't get too carried away with super complicated features you don't really need. Remember, the whole point of this is to simplify and quicken the process of drawing, not to make the most feature-rich routine imaginable.

Buffering Other Things

Drawing code is not the only thing that can be buffered. Changes in PPU state, such as scroll changes, turning the PPU on/off, etc, can (and should) be buffered as well, provided the effect truly isn't desired immediately (timed raster effects, for example, might be desired immediately, but that's a later topic).

The first instinct for the newbie is to turn the PPU on and off directly. They'll finish all the drawing they needed to do to get the first screen to display, and they go to switch the PPU on:

lda #%00011000
sta $2001

They then are shocked to see that when they do this, the screen "jumps" because the PPU was in the middle of Rendering time when they turned it on. The solution for this is simple: Buffer the changes to $2000 (PPUCTRL) and $2001 (PPUMASK). I say you should keep variables called soft2000 and soft2001 (really, call them whatever you like). You should then copy these values to the real $2000/$2001 next VBlank. With this setup, when you want to turn the PPU on, you can do the following:

lda #%00011000
sta soft2001

And take comfort knowing that the PPU will be [safely] turned on next VBlank. This works for turning the PPU off as well, or any other state change. If you need the change to happen "now", like for instance if you want to turn the PPU off so you can draw a full new screen to the nametable you'd need to shut the PPU off before you could do any drawing. You can do the following:

lda #%00011000
sta soft2001
jsr WaitFrame

...where WaitFrame is a routine which waits for an NMI to occur before returning. This will ensure the state is changed before the logic code proceeds, but also makes sure the change is safe (in VBlank).

When to Turn Off PPU, NMIs

Drawing can be separated into two general types of drawing. You have bulk drawing which will happen during a major transition in a game, and you'll have updating which will happen constantly as the user is playing the game.

For an example of each of these types, let's say you're making an RPG where the player walks around a scrolling map. When the player takes a step, new tiles will have to be drawn to show the area of the map they're walking towards. This is an example of updating. Now when the player gets in a battle, or enters a town or dungeon, you'll have to draw an entirely different image on the screen. This is an example of bulk drawing.

Updates should be done in the method we've talked about. Buffer them, and make sure they happen in VBlank. The reason we need VBlank is because you can't switch off the PPU in order to do the drawing otherwise the visual display will black out. Could you imagine the screen flashing black every time you took a step?

Conversely, bulk drawing should not be done with the methods described so far. Buffering bulk drawing serves no benefit, since all the drawing couldn't fit in VBlank time anyway. What's more, turning the screen off and having it black for a few frames might even be desirable during such transitions. Therefore, you should [safely] switch the PPU off, then do your bulk drawing. It doesn't even hurt to put the bulk drawing right in with the logic code! Go ahead and mix it right in. The only reason that was a bad idea before is because you want to keep unnecessary logic code out of precious VBlank. But now since the PPU is off and we can draw whatever we want, that's a nonissue.

The one exception to the "everything is safe if PPU is off" rule is palette updates. Palette updates should be in VBlank (buffered), even if the PPU is off. This is due to a particular quirk of the NES PPU where pointing its I/O address at the palette while rendering is disabled will cause it to display that particular color on the screen - it won't kill anything, but you'll have a weird "rainbow stripe" flash across your screen. This isn't terribly relevant if your game is still booting up, though.

Now you might be thinking, "Well if I'm doing a bulk drawing routine, I want to disable NMIs too because I don't want an NMI to interrupt me while I'm drawing." That is a reasonable thought, but ultimately it's a bad way to go. As a general rule of thumb, leave NMIs on all the time. The only time they should be off is during your startup code where you're initializing everything. After that, once you turn them on, leave them on unless you have a very compelling reason to turn them off. There are many reasons for this:

If you code your NMI handler properly, it will know to do nothing when it has nothing to do. There's no real harm in letting it run even if you don't need it to (other than losing a very small handful of cycles).
There are things you might want to happen every frame, even during these transitions. For example, you might want the music to keep playing rather than require it pause/stop during the transition. This can be done by updating the music engine in your NMI handler, but is virtually impossible to do if you disable NMIs.
Once you turn NMIs off, it is very easy to forget to turn them back on. What's worse, if you forget to read $2002 and you turn them on in the middle of VBlank, it will immediately trigger an NMI and cause your handler to run past the end of VBlank, starting all sorts of havoc.

Take Full Advantage of NMI

Another newbie issue is that they are often unsure how to use NMI. Some of them either have NMI change a single variable and exit immediately ("everything in main"), or they enable NMIs, then run the main code into an infinite loop, and have their whole game run from the NMI handler ("everything in NMI"). Both of these are ill advised for a full, complex game. If you've done things this way, don't feel bad - even some commercial games do it like that. So it's not that those methods don't work, it's just that they're not as advantageous.

What you should realize is that your NMI handler is extremely valuable in that (provided you leave NMIs on) it is the only area of code in your program that is guaranteed to run every single frame. Not only every frame, but every VBlank. Utilizing this gives you a much tighter grip around how you want the game to operate.

The shortcomings of these "everything in XXX" approaches are that they handle game slowdown poorly, and prevent you from doing some basic things that you should be able to do. For example, taking the "everything in NMI" approach causes all sorts of problems:

You probably have to disable NMIs when one trips, then re-enable them when logic is done. Otherwise an NMI could trip when you're still doing NMI stuff, which could be disastrous.
You can't keep the music updated during slowdown, or during bulk drawing transitions, because NMIs will be disabled.
Slowdown will cause you to "miss" frames. If you're doing a screen split or other raster effect, you won't be able to set it up properly, and the status bar or other effect will be visually glitchy in the next frame.

The "everything in main" approach is none better, and it suffers from the same problems, just introduced differently.

So how do you use NMI to take full advantage of it? All you have to do is keep it enabled all the time, and have it do things that you will always want done every frame. You can have a series of flags to make some tasks conditional for some frames (so you don't have to draw anything if there's nothing to draw, etc). Here's an example of what a better NMI handler and some supporting routines might look like:

   ;---------------------------------------

   ;  note I use 'varname = x' for simplicity, but there are many good reasons not
   ; to use this method in a real game.  Assume all these variables have a
   ; unique space in memory

   ; designate a oam and drawing buffer
   oam          = $0200    ; shadow oam
   drawingbuf   = $0300    ; buffer for PPU drawing

   ; other variables
   soft2000     = x    ; buffering $2000 writes
   soft2001     = x    ; buffering $2001 writes

   needdma      = x    ; nonzero if NMI should perform sprite DMA
   needdraw     = x    ; nonzero if NMI needs to do drawing from the buffer
   needppureg   = x    ; nonzero if NMI should update $2000/$2001/$2005
   sleeping     = x    ; nonzero if main thread is waiting for VBlank

   xscroll      = x
   yscroll      = x


   ;--------------------------------------
   ; WaitFrame - waits for VBlank, returns after NMI handler is done

   WaitFrame:
     inc sleeping
     @loop:
       lda sleeping
       bne @loop
     rts

   ;--------------------------------------
   ; DoFrame - same idea as WaitFrame, but also does some other stuff
   ;   that the game logic will want done every frame.  Things that
   ;   shouldn't be put in NMI

   DoFrame:
     lda #1
     sta needdraw
     sta needoam
     sta needppureg
     jsr WaitFrame
     jmp UpdateJoypadData

   ;--------------------------------------
   ; NMI - the NMI handler

   NMI:
     pha         ; back up registers (important)
     txa
     pha
     tya
     pha

     lda needdma
     beq :+
       lda #0      ; do sprite DMA
       sta $2003   ; conditional via the 'needdma' flag
       lda #>oam
       sta $4014

  :  lda needdraw       ; do other PPU drawing (NT/Palette/whathaveyou)
     beq :+             ;  conditional via the 'needdraw' flag
       bit $2002        ; clear VBl flag, reset $2005/$2006 toggle
       jsr DoDrawing    ; draw the stuff from the drawing buffer
       dec needdraw

  :  lda needppureg
     beq :+
       lda soft2001   ; copy buffered $2000/$2001 (conditional via needppureg)
       sta $2001
       lda soft2000
       sta $2000

       bit $2002
       lda xscroll    ; set X/Y scroll (conditional via needppureg)
       sta $2005
       lda yscroll
       sta $2005

  :  jsr MusicEngine

     lda #0         ; clear the sleeping flag so that WaitFrame will exit
     sta sleeping   ;   note that you should not 'dec' here, as sleeping might
                    ;   already be zero (will be the case during slowdown)

     pla            ; restore regs and exit
     tay
     pla
     tax
     pla
     rti

   ;-----------------------------------------

With the above code structure, all your program has to do is keep NMI enabled, and all your drawing, scroll setting, and music updating will be done automagically. All you have to do from there is put the stuff you want drawn in your drawing buffer, and jsr to 'DoFrame' to keep the game going. It couldn't be easier! This will allow you to keep your logic code easy to follow and straightforward, as well as providing all the other benefits talked about in this doc.

A few things to note about the order and the way in which this example routine does things:

Timing-critical stuff (drawing code) is done first. Then it moves on to setting the scroll, then to stuff that can be done any time (music updating).
Nearly everything is conditional (you can make everything conditional if you want). Making the drawing and DMA conditional will prevent the NMI from drawing data that is "not yet finished" (for example, if NMI occurs while you're filling one of the buffers).

Being Interrupt-Aware

The above mentioned approach might seem bulletproof. NMI just does its own thing, the logic code is freed from timing concerns, and all you have to do to make it work is update a few variables when you want an onscreen change. Really, though, this approach opens itself up to a different set of problems that the "everything in XXX" methods don't normally have to worry about. Because your handler for NMIs (and your handler for IRQs, for that matter) are doing a substantial workload, and because they are left enabled most/all of the time, they can cause conflicts with your main code and can really cause you serious problems if they happen when your logic code isn't expecting them. In order to prevent these conflicts from occurring, your code needs to be interrupt-aware.

Conflicts, in this context, are when the NMI/IRQ changes something (either a variable, reg, or other system state) that the main code is using, resulting in the main code doing something totally unexpected. A very simple way to visualize this is changing a 6502 reg:

;;  if this is your NMI handler
NMI:
  lda #0
  rti

;;  and if you do this somewhere else in your program

RefillPlayerHP:
  lda playermaxhp
  sta playerhp
  rts

Do you see the problem? It's subtle, but RefillPlayerHP might actually end up killing the player! The reason why is because NMIs can happen any time, and if an NMI happens between your lda and sta commands, you get totally screwed. Here's a flow of what might happen:

  lda playermaxhp
                   ; -------->NMI------>
                                      lda #0
                                      rti
                   ; <--------RTI<------
  sta playerhp
  rts

The problem is much more obvious when you draw it out like this. You can see that if an NMI happens at that point, you'll be setting the player's hp to zero, instead of refilling it.

Believe it or not, this is much more likely to happen than you might think. And if you're using IRQs, it's almost a guarantee that cases like this will come up. What's worse, these problems are very hard to diagnose from the symptoms, because they're not easily reproduced. This is why it's so important for your code to be interrupt-aware from day 1.

An easy and very common solution to this particular problem is to backup and restore the 6502's registers by pushing them to the stack first thing in your NMI and IRQ handlers and then restoring them just before your rti. This is why many examples (including my example NMI handler above) start with the pha txa pha tya pha business. This ensures that A, X, and Y will be unchanged from their original value when NMI exits.

It's not just cpu registers, though. Variable conflicts can also occur. Say you have a generic ptr variable that you use somewhere in your logic code to read map data that you're loading. And say the NMI handler is also using it in its drawing routine. The conflict here happens if an NMI occurs during your map loading routine. NMI will overwrite the pointer with what it needs, and when control returns to the main path, you'll start reading map data from whatever NMI was pointing to, rather than what you really wanted.

The solution here is also very simple and easy. Just do not have NMI or IRQ share variables or RAM space with your main code (or with each other -- remember that while an IRQ during NMI is impossible, an NMI during IRQ is very possible!). Of course, you'll still need some variables that both your interrupts and your main code use in order to communicate between them, such as needdraw in the above example.

Beware, however, that these variables need to be quickly accessible. You are most vulnerable to conflicts when something critical takes multiple instructions. For example, looking at the above you might think "He's got 3 'needsomething' flags up there, and they're all separate variables. That's wasteful. I'm going to combine all of those into a single variable where each bit is a flag." Sounds smart, right? Use 1 byte of RAM instead of 3, and all the flags are consolidated into a single variable. The downside to this, however, is it makes you vulnerable to conflicts because changing a flag now requires a series of instructions, rather than a single sta command:

  lda needflags     ; grab the need flags
  ora #NEEDFLG_DMA  ; flip on the flag marking sprite DMA
  sta needflags     ; write back

The conflict here happens when NMI trips between the lda and sta commands, and when the NMI routine changes needflags. This will happen sometimes. For instance, the previous NMI handler example performs dec needflags after it finishes drawing. It's a good thing that it does this, because otherwise it will waste time drawing the same thing over and over every frame.

Another interesting and often overlooked problem is a subtle system state change. Say you're doing a bulk drawing routine and you set the PPU address to $2400:

  lda #>$2400
  sta $2006
  lda #<$2400
  sta $2006

;; elsewhere, in your NMI handler:
NMI:
  pha
  bit $2002    ; clear vblank flag

  lda xscroll  ; set the scroll
  sta $2005
  lda yscroll
  sta $2005

  pla
  rti

Harmless, right? But there is a disastrous conflict there. Do you see it? It happens when an NMI occurs between the $2006 writes. It's bad in two ways:

bit $2002 will reset the PPU toggle so that the next write to $2006 is the first write. This means that your main code won't actually be setting the PPU address to $2400, because the second write actually becomes another first write because of the toggle.
Setting the scroll changes the temp PPU address (aka loopy_t). This messes with the address the main code is trying to set with its $2006 writes.

Yet another example of this happening is on mappers which require two or more writes in order to bankswitch. If the NMI or IRQ also needs to bankswitch, you have yourself yet another conflict.

Just remember the key to being interrupt-aware is to spot vulnerabilities. You're most vulnerable when something seemingly basic takes several instructions to do. Just be extra careful when writing code like that in your program, and make state changing code in your NMI/IRQ handlers conditional so that your main code can disable it for sections where it might introduce conflict vulnerabilities.

Tile compression

Tile compression refers to techniques that allow fitting more graphics data into a smaller space. Programs using CHR ROM cannot use compressed tiles, as their tile data must be stored in the PPU's native format. But programs using CHR RAM can process tile data while copying it from PRG ROM to CHR RAM, and this processing allows storing more tiles in the same space.

Contents

1 Run-length encoding

1.1 PCX
1.2 PackBits
1.3 Konami RLE
1.4 GBA RLUnComp
1.5 PB53
1.6 RLEINC
1.7 Bit-based RLE
1.8 NES Stripe Image RLE
1.9 SNES Stripe Image RLE

2 Pixel based

2.1 Codemasters

2.1.1 Tokumaru

3 Common byte

3.1 Oracle common byte

4 LZSS

4.1 LZ77UnComp
4.2 Oracle LZ
4.3 Pokémon LZ
4.4 Chrono Trigger LZ

5 External links

Run-length encoding

Run-length encoding transforms runs of identical bytes into a shorter sequence of bytes that specifies the length of the run.

In NES tile data, byte-level run-length encoding works well when a row of 8 pixels in a tile is identical to the row above it. It also works well for nametable data because a horizontal run of blank tiles becomes a single tile.

Pixel-level run-length encoding is much slower but can achieve impressive results within a tile.

There are several different RLE data formats.

PCX

The PCX image format became popular on PC.

Value | Meaning
00-BF | Write this byte to the output.
C0-FF | Read another byte, and write it to the output n - 192 times.

PackBits

The PackBits format was invented by Apple for MacPaint. It is also used in TIFF files and a few homebrew releases by Damian Yerrick.

Value | Meaning
00-7F | Copy n + 1 bytes from input to output.
80 | No operation
81-FF | Read another byte, and write it to the output 257 - n times.

Konami RLE

This format is used in Blades of Steel, the U.S. version of Contra, and the Japanese version of Simon's Quest. It can be decoded and encoded with the Python program GraveyardDuck. Compression ratio is more or less identical to PackBits.

Value | Meaning
00-80 | Read another byte, and write it to the output n times.
81-FE | Copy n - 128 bytes from input to output.
FF | End of compressed data

GBA RLUnComp

The BIOS of the Game Boy Advance and Nintendo DS contains a decompressor for an RLE format very similar to PackBits and Konami. As described in GBATEK, it has a 4-byte size header followed by this:

Value | Meaning
00-7F | Copy n + 1 bytes from input to output.
80-FF | Read one byte from input and write it to output n - 125 times.

PB53

This codec was conceived by Damian Yerrick as an alternative to PackBits for the Action 53 multicart, and a Python packer and 6502 unpacker are included in the Action 53 menu distribution. Unlike freeform RLE formats such as Konami and PackBits, PB53 operates on 16-byte units, making it easy to divide the decompressed data into fixed-size packets to be sent to the PPU during vblank while rendering is turned on. Like LZSS, PB53 uses unary coding on the lengths of literal runs to save on overhead from switching between literal and run modes. This means that like LZSS, it has a worst case expansion of 12.5%, but it works fairly well on real tile data and OK on nametable data, which have shorter runs than the high-resolution files for which PackBits was designed. It also has a special mode to accommodate the layout of Shiru's NROM games LAN Master, Lawn Mower, and Chase, which have many identical tiles between the two pattern tables to allow tile animation.

Each tile consists of several 8-byte planes, two planes in the NES implementation. For the first plane in a tile:

Value | Meaning
00-7F | Copy one byte from input to output. Then, for each bit from 6 to 0, if the bit is 1, repeat the previous byte; otherwise, copy another byte from the input. This is somewhat similar to how control bytes are formatted in LZSS.
80 | Write eight $00 bytes.
81 | Write eight $FF bytes.
82 | Copy one tile (16 bytes) starting one tile back. (Used for a repeated tile, such as the unused tiles in many games.)
83 | Copy one tile starting one segment back, usually 4096 bytes. (Used for pattern tables that share tiles, as seen in several Shiru games. The decoder switches between two instances one segment apart, each with its own input stream and output buffer.)
84 | Write sixteen $00 bytes. (Solid color 0)
85 | Write eight $FF bytes then eight $00 bytes. (Solid color 1)
86 | Write eight $00 bytes then eight $FF bytes. (Solid color 2)
87 | Write sixteen $FF bytes. (Solid color 3)

For other planes:

Value | Meaning
00-81 | Same as first plane
82 | Copy previous 8 bytes. (Used for 1-bit tiles with colors 0 and 3.)
83 | Copy previous 8 bytes, bit-inverted. (Used for 1-bit tiles with colors 1 and 2.)

RLEINC

This RLE variant was used by Joel Yliluoma in the Simon's Quest retranslation project. It is very efficient when compressing nametables, which often contain redundancy in more complex forms than simple runs of repeating bytes. Examples include brick walls, which repeat two tiles, and complex graphics that is formed from an ascending series of successive tiles. For bitmap compression, it is slightly inferior to simpler RLE methods.

Value | Meaning
00–3F | LIT: Copy (n+1) bytes from input to output backwards
40 | END: End of stream
41–7F | SEQ: Read next byte b. Put b, (n−0x3F) times; add 1 to b after each iteration
80–9F | DBL: Read next byte b1, and next byte b2. Put b1, (n−0x7D) times; swap b2 and b1 after each iteration
A0–FF | RUN: Read byte b. Put b, (0x101−n) times.

A compressor for this scheme can be found at http://bisqwit.iki.fi/src/nes-ppu_rleinc_compress.php.txt (PHP), and a decompressor at http://bisqwit.iki.fi/src/nes-ppu_rleinc_v2b.inc (CA65).

JRoatch made PBJ, which adds the PB8 mode from PB53 and a common-byte mode to a modified RLEINC.

Bit-based RLE

Most RLE schemes deal with whole bytes. There are also schemes where the compressed data forms a bitstream, that contains integers of different bit widths.

When compressing the combined tile graphics of Super Mario Bros. and Kirby's Adventure, a simple reference RLE algorithm (PackBits) gets a 12% reduction in data size. However, if the algorithm is modified as indicated below, a 21% reduction is achieved. For comparison, the graphics specialized algorithm in PB53 achieves 25% for that data set. Tokumaru compression manages to reduce the data by 41%.

Bit sequence | Meaning
0000 | End of stream.
0nnn | Copy the next n×8 bits, i.e. n bytes, to the output.
1nnn | Read the next 8 bits, and output this byte n+2 times.

A possible reason why bit-based compression methods are not popular on the NES is that bit-shifts are cumbersome and slow with the 6502 CPU, as it can only shift one bit at a time. The above algorithm is still relatively simple to implement, as it operates on units of 4 bits for the input and full bytes for the output. Coincidentally, it also produced the best compression out of all bit-based RLE algorithms that were brute-force-tested for that dataset.

NES Stripe Image RLE

A RLE format mostly used by Nintendo for use in thier Arcade ports as well as their Mario games, Also used in some homebrew games!

Format: dest, len, data, end

dest: PPU Destination: Two byte value for $2006 (write x 2)

len: Length (Byte) of PPU Buffer Data:

Length Value | Meaning
00-3F | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer
40-7F | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer, with RLE
80-BF | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer, skip 32 Bytes
C0-FF | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer, with RLE, skip 32 Bytes

data: PPU Data to display

end: End of Data marker, The value must be $00

SNES Stripe Image RLE

Same RLE format used by Nintendo as above, but for SNES.

Format: dest, len, data, end

dest: PPU Destination: $2116 and $2117

len: Length (Word) of PPU Buffer Data:

Length Value | Meaning
0000-3FFF | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer
4000-7FFF | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer, with RLE
8000-BFFF | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer, skip 32 Bytes
C000-FFFF | Copy n + 1 bytes to PPU buffer, with RLE, skip 32 Bytes

data: PPU Data to display in 2-byte increments (or word increments)

end: Unlike the NES version, the end byte is $FF or $FFFF.

Pixel based

Codemasters

This is a Markov chain (predictive) algorithm that packs predictions in varying number of bits. It works on packets measured in whole tiles, and compresses mostly pixel by pixel, making it slow. Explained on forum.

Tokumaru

Tokumaru discovered an improvement to the way the frequency tables are changed in Codemasters algorithm, and released the compressor and decompressor as open source. And open-source rewrite of the encoder and decoder with slightly better performance can be downloaded at: http://bisqwit.iki.fi/source/tokumaru.html

The compressed data begins with a byte that tells how many tiles it encodes. 256 is maximum. Technically this byte can be ignored, if you already know how many tiles you are going to decode.

After the byte, any number of blocks follows. Each block begins with a color description table. This table tells how to encode transitions between colors in tiles belonging to this block.

There are four elements in this table, from 3 to 0, for color n. Each element begins with a two-bit integer ncolors[n], that tells how many different colors that may follow a pixel of this particular color. After the number of colors, comes a pivot color a that is encoded as follows:

Value | Applicable when | Meaning
nothing | ncolors[n]=0 | No pivot color
1 bit: 0 | ncolors[n]>0 | Pivot color a is 1 if n < 1, 0 otherwise.
2 bits: 10 | ncolors[n]>0 | Pivot color a is 2 if n < 2, 1 otherwise.
2 bits: 11 | ncolors[n]>0 | Pivot color a is 3 if n < 3, 2 otherwise.

The table of transition colors is then calculated using n, a, and the number of colors ncolors[n]. First, two other colors b and c are calculated. They are the first color indexes that are neither n nor a. E.g. if a=2 and n=1, b and c become 0 and 3 respectively.

When ncolors[n] is | Table of possible transition colors next[n] is
0 | []
1 | [a]
2 | [b,c]
3 | [a,b,c]

For compression purposes, ideally ncolors[n] should be chosen to be the numbers of distinct colors that actually can follow the color n, based on measuring the tile data, and, if ncolors[n]=3, the pivot color a should be the color that is transitioned into most often from color n. This transition in tile data will be encoded in two bits, while the other transitions are encoded in three bits. For other values of ncolors[n], the choice of pivot color is mandated by the actual possible colors.

After the color description table, comes tile data encoding 16 bytes, or 8×8 pixels. Each tile is comprised of eight rows of pixels. Each pixel row begins with 1 bit, that tells whether the row is to be copied. If the bit is set, the previously decoded row is duplicated, and no other data is encoded for this pixel row. At the start of the block, the "previously decoded row" is assumed to contain zero bytes. The previous row is not reset between different tiles, unless a new block begins. If the bit was clear, eight pixels follow for x coordinates 0 to 7. Each pixel is encoded as follows, depending on the color c of the previous pixel:

Value | Applicable when | Meaning
2 bits | x = 0 | The color of the first pixel c is encoded as a 2-bit integer.
nothing | ncolors[c]=0 | c does not change, and nothing is encoded.
1 bit: 1 | ncolors[c]>0 | c does not change from previous pixel.
1 bit: 0 | ncolors[c]=1 | c becomes next[c][0].
2 bits: 00 | ncolors[c]>1 | c becomes next[c][0].
2 bits: 01 | ncolors[c]=2 | c becomes next[c][1].
3 bits: 010 | ncolors[c]=3 | c becomes next[c][1].
3 bits: 011 | ncolors[c]=3 | c becomes next[c][2].

After each full tile, if there are still remaining tiles to be decoded, comes one bit that tells what comes next. Value 1 means a new block start, with a new color description table. Value 0 means that more tile data will follow.

Common byte

Oracle common byte

This codec, used in The Legend of Zelda: Oracle of Seasons and The Legend of Zelda: Oracle of Ages according to Dwedit, is roughly comparable to RLE in complexity. For each 16-byte block, the compressor determines the most common byte in that block. The compressed data for each block starts with a 2-byte mask, then the most common byte, then other bytes in order that aren't the most common.

To decode a block: First read the two-byte mask. If the entire mask is zero, set the bit corresponding to the first byte to true. Then read the most common byte. For each bit in the mask, if the bit is 1, write the most common byte to output; otherwise, copy one byte.

Maximum expansion is 12.5% for any block that has 16 different bytes in it: two bytes of mask and 16 bytes of data.

LZSS

A lot of games on platforms after the NES use LZ77 family compression methods such as LZSS, which generalizes run-length encoding to allow copying data from several bytes ago, not just the previous byte. Few NES games use LZ77 because the NES's limited work RAM and limited access to video memory make it difficult to resolve back references. (Fewer still use LZW or any other LZ78-based method because of patents that subsisted through the NES, Super NES, and Nintendo 64 eras.)

In LZSS, the mask contains 8 commands, each either to copy a literal byte or to copy a back reference. determines whether the next 8 things are literal bytes or back references. Once all commands have been processed, read another mask.

Read a mask byte from input.
For each bit in the mask byte:

If the bit is 0, this is a literal:

Copy one byte from input to output.

Otherwise, this is a back-reference:

Read and decode a length and distance from input. These will be positive integers.
Copy length bytes from the previous output, distance bytes before now, to output.

LZSS flavors vary mainly in how they encode lengths and distances.

LZ77UnComp

The BIOS of the Game Boy Advance and Nintendo DS has a built-in decompressor for a straightforward LZSS flavor with 3- to 18-byte references into the previous 4096 bytes of output. The data format is described in Martin Korth's GBATEK.

Caution: In data intended for decompression directly to the GBA or DS video memory, the second byte of a 16-bit word cannot refer to the first byte of the same word. So the encoder must not write a run with distance 1 that starts at an odd offset.

Oracle LZ

This flavor of LZSS is used in The Legend of Zelda: Oracle games for Game Boy Color according to Dwedit.

An entire compressed block can be compressed with one of two subtypes of Oracle LZ: short word mode and long word mode. Short words use references of 2 to 8 bytes into the previous 32 bytes of output, and long words use references of 3 to 33 bytes into the previous 2048 bytes. (A length value of 0 means read an additional byte and use that as the length.) Only short words would work very well on NES.

Pokémon LZ

This compression scheme is used in the first-generation Pokémon games on the Game Boy. It is used for bitmap compression.

A byte n is read and split into two parts: code = n >> 5, and c = n & 0x1F. Byte 0xFF marks the end of the stream. Otherwise the code is interpreted as follows:

code | Meaning
0 | Copy the next c + 1 bytes to the output.
1 | Read another byte, and write it to the output c + 1 times.
2 | Read another byte b1 and byte b2, and write byte b1 to the output c + 1 times, swapping b1 and b2 after each write.
3 | Write a zero byte (0x00) to the output c + 1 times.
4 | Read byte b. If b < 0x80, then read byte b2; offset is b×256+b2 bytes from the output stream beginning. Else offset = b bytes behind from the current output stream end. Copy c + 1 bytes from the output stream at offset to the output.
5 | Read byte b. If b < 0x80, then read byte b2; offset is b×256+b2 bytes from the output stream beginning. Else offset = b bytes behind from the current output stream end. Copy c + 1 bytes from the output stream at offset to the output, reversing the bits in each byte.
6 | Read byte b. If b < 0x80, then read byte b2; offset is b×256+b2 bytes from the output stream beginning. Else offset = b bytes behind from the current output stream end. Copy c + 1 bytes from the output stream at offset to the output, decrementing the read position after each write (i.e. reverse the data).
7 | Read another byte b. Change code = (c >> 2), and change c = (c & 3) × 256 + b. Re-interpret code according to this table.

Chrono Trigger LZ

This compression scheme is used in Square‘s Chrono Trigger for the SNES for compression of graphics and various data.

The data consists of packets. Each packet begins with a 16-bit offset, which gives the packet ending offset relative to the beginning of compressed data. At that offset, there is always a control byte. The first control byte sets the size of offsets: If the byte is < 0xC0, then offsetsbits=12. Else offsetbits=11. Interpreting the offsetbits is done only once. The higher-order two bits in the control bytes of all other packets are ignored. The counter is assigned a default value of 8.

The decompression loop goes as follows:

If the packet end has been reached, a control byte is read, and counter is assigned the low 6 bits of that byte (i.e. counter = byte & 0x3F). If the counter is zero, the decompression is complete and ends there. If the counter was nonzero, a new 16-bit packet end offset is read.
If the end of the packet has not yet been reached, a mask byte is read.

If the mask byte is zero, then next eight bytes are copied verbatim to the output. The counter is not affected.
If the mask byte was nonzero, its each bit is read, beginning from the lowest-order bit. The number of bits to be read is determined by counter (which is in range 1—63, i.e. it can be both smaller and greater than eight).

If the bit is zero, a single byte is copied verbatim to the output.
If the bit is nonzero, a 16-bit number is read from the input. offset becomes the lowest-order offsetbits from that number, and length is the rest of the bits plus 3. The decompressor copies length bytes from offset bytes behind to the output.
After all bits have been read, the counter is reset to the default value of 8, and the decompression loop continues.

External links

Ad Hoc Compression Methods: RLE describes various pixel-level RLE methods applied to a drawing of a Pokémon

Tricky-to-emulate games

At the very least the following games depend on hard-to-emulate or just obscure behavior:

Adventures of Lolo 2, Ms. Pac-Man (Tengen), and Spelunker rely on 1 cycle NMI delay when PPUSTATUS ($2002) bit 7 gets set inside vblank (if $2002 has not been read yet), in which PPUSTATUS bit 7 can be read as true.
Balloon Fight relies on reading the nametables through PPUDATA ($2007) to twinkle the stars in the background. (The code is at $D603.) The scroll split in "Balloon Trip" also depends to an extent on the correct number of CPU cycles from the start of NMI to the start of display, but it's not particularly picky.
Bases Loaded II glitches after a pitch is thrown (screenshot) if writing $00 then $80 to PPUCTRL during vertical blank does not cause an additional NMI.
Battletoads requires fairly precise CPU and PPU timing (Including the cycle penalty for crossing pages) and a fairly robust sprite zero implementation. It leaves rendering disabled for a number of scanlines into the visible frame to gain extra VRAM manipulation time and then enables it. If the timing is off so that the background image appears too high or too low at this point, a sprite zero hit will fail to trigger, hanging the game. This usually occurs immediately upon entering the first stage if the timing is off by enough, and might cause random hangs at other points otherwise.
Battletoads & Double Dragon crashes at the first boss if emulated with WRAM (memory in the $6000-$7FFF range) present and initialized to $FF. ($00 does not seem to cause problems, for some reason.) The real cart does not contain WRAM and produces open bus reads. This is caused by a usually inert bug in the game's code.
Bee 52 needs accurate DMC timing and relies on PPUSTATUS bit 5 (sprite overflow) as well
Bill & Ted's Excellent Adventure and a few other MMC1 games depend on the mapper ignoring successive writes; see iNES Mapper 001 (the talk page for that page might be informative too). Bill & Ted… also turns off and re-enables rendering midframe to switch CHR banks (e.g. in the black border above dialog boxes).
Burai Fighter (U) accesses PPUDATA during rendering to draw the scorebar. Incorrect emulation clips the scorebar to half size. See the notes on accessing PPUDATA during rendering on the PPU scrolling page.
B-Wings writes to CHR ROM and expects the writes to have no effect.
Cobra Triangle and Ironsword: Wizards and Warriors II rely on the dummy read for the sta $4000,X instruction to acknowledge pending APU IRQs.
Crystalis, Fantastic Adventures of Dizzy, Fire Hawk, and Super Off Road do mid-frame palette changes.
Fire Hawk, Mig 29 Soviet Fighter, and Time Lord need accurate DMC timing because they abuse APU DMC IRQ to split the screen.
Galaxian requires proper handling of bit 4 of the P register for /IRQ.
G.I. Joe and Mickey in Letterland turn show sprites off and MMC3 mapper relies on sprites fetches to clock the scanline counter.[1]
Huge Insect depends on obscure OAMADDR ($2003) behavior; see PPU registers.
The Magic of Scheherazade maps two non-contiguous PRG-ROM pages next to each other, then executes code across the page boundary. Emulators which use pointers to fetch sequential instruction bytes from ROM will fail when taking damage in the RPG-style battles. (Use password 5W to test this easily)
Marble Madness switches CHR banks mid-scanline to draw text boxes (e.g. at the beginning of each level). Getting these to render correctly requires fairly precise timing.
Micro Machines requires correct values when reading OAMDATA ($2004) during rendering, and also relies on proper background color selection when rendering is disabled and the VRAM address points to the palette (see the "background palette hack" on the PPU palettes page).
Paperboy relies on the open bus behavior of controller reads and expects them to return exactly 0x40 or 0x41; see Standard controller.
Punch-Out!! requires fetching the 34th tile; otherwise, the ring will be glitched.
Puzznic and Reflect World (FDS) use unofficial opcode $89, which is a two-byte NOP on 6502 and BIT #imm on 65C02. (Puzznic tasvideos discussion) The instruction in Puzznic is 89 00; emulating $89 as a single-byte NOP will trigger a BRK that causes the screen to shake.

Several other games use other unofficial opcodes.

Slalom does a JSR while the stack pointer is 0, so that half of the return address ends up at $0100 and the other half at $01FF.
Super Mario Bros. is [probably the hardest game to emulate among the most popular NROM games, which are generally the first targets against which an emulator author tests his or her work. It relies on JMP indirect, correct palette mirroring (otherwise the sky will be black; see PPU palettes), sprite 0 detection (otherwise the game will freeze on the title screen), the 1-byte delay when reading from CHR ROM through PPUDATA (see The PPUDATA read buffer), and proper behavior of the nametable selection bits of PPUSTATUS and PPUADDR. In addition, there are several bad dumps floating around, some of which were ripped from pirate multicarts whose cheat menus leave several key parameters in RAM. If you're looking for a good first game for your new emulator, try anything made in 1984 or earlier, such as Donkey Kong.
Super Mario Bros. 3 relies on an interaction between the sprite priority bit and the OAM index to put power-ups behind blocks.
Time Lord is sensitive to the power-on state of the NES. The Vblank flag in PPU Status must be set for the first time within 240 scanlines, otherwise there will be a frame IRQ which is never acknowledged, which will mess up the DMC IRQs used elsewhere and cause the game to crash.
Wizards and Warriors 3 writes new tile graphics for the sprites at the screen split after the sprites have been drawn, but before the frame has ended. Emulators which draw the sprites all at once using graphics data from the end of the frame will have glitches in the main character's sprite.
The Young Indiana Jones Chronicles accesses PPUDATA during rendering to perform a glitchy y scroll (to make the screen shake when cannon balls hit the ground). See the notes on accessing PPUDATA during rendering on PPU scrolling page.

Game bugs lists games that have glitches on NES hardware, so you won't go "fixing" them while breaking your emulator.

Troubleshooting games

If a scroll split doesn't work, and a garbage sprite shows up around the intended split point, then the game is probably trying to use a sprite 0 hit, but either the wrong tile data is loaded or the background is scrolled to a position that doesn't overlap correctly. This could be a problem with nametable mirroring, with CHR bankswitching in mappers that support it, or with the CPU and PPU timing of whatever happened above the split. Battletoads, for one, uses 1-screen mirroring and requires exact timing to get the background scroll position dead-on.

UNIF

UNIF (Universal NES Image Format) is an alternative format for holding NES and Famicom ROM images.

Its motivation was to offer more description of the mapper board than the popular iNES 1.0 format, but it suffered from other limiting constraints and a lack of popularity. The format is considered deprecated, replaced by the NES 2.0 revision of the iNES format, which better addresses the issues it had hoped to solve.

There are a small number of game rips that currently only exist as UNIF. (board list)

Contents

1 History
2 Format

2.1 Types

3 Shortcomings
4 References

History

The originator of the UNIF format, Tennessee Carmel-Veilleux, publically abandoned the format in December of 2008, and had its website deleted.

Since 2011 the UNIF standard has been maintained as part of the libunif project. See: http://github.com/eteran/libunif

UNIF is currently considered a deprecated standard. Further updates to UNIF are unlikely, and it is recommended that new games or rips requiring special mapper specifications use the NES 2.0 format instead of attempting to extend UNIF.

Format

UNIF images start with a 32-byte header:

Offset | Length (bytes) | Value
0 | 4 | "UNIF"
4 | 4 | le32, minimum version number required to parse all chunks in file
8 | 24 | all nulls

Followed by any number of Type+Length+Value blocks:

Offset | Length (bytes) | Value
0 | 4 | Type, varies, defined below
4 | 4 | le32, length
8 | length | content encoding varies by type

Types

The following Types are known:

Type | Length | Minimum version required | Encoding | Content meaning
MAPR | variable | 1 | null-terminated UTF-8 | A unique human-readable identifier specifying the exact hardware used; not an iNES mapper number, and not a full text description of the mapper; required
PRGn | variable, usually power of two | 4 | raw | the contents of the nth PRG ROM; at least PRG0 is required; n is in hexadecimal
CHRn | variable, usually power of two | 4 | raw | the contents of the nth CHR ROM
PCKn | 4 | 5 | le32 | the CRC-32 of the nth PRG ROM
CCKn | 4 | 5 | le32 | the CRC-32 of the nth CHR ROM
NAME | variable | 1 | null-terminated UTF-8 | the name of the game
WRTR | variable | unknown | null-terminated UTF-8 | unofficial, invalid. The name of the dumping software. Should be in a DINF chunk instead
READ | variable | 1 | null-terminated UTF-8 | comments about the game, especially licensing information for homebrew
DINF | 204 | 2 | special | Dumping information

Offset | Length (bytes) | Value
0 | 100 | null-terminated UTF-8 dumper name
100 | 1 | day-of-month of dump
101 | 1 | month-of-year of dump
102 | 2 | le16, year of dump
104 | 100 | null-terminated UTF-8 the name of the dumping software or mechanism

TVCI | 1 | 6 | byte | TV standard compatibility information-

0. | NTSC only
1. | PAL only
2. | compatible with both

CTRL | 1 | 7 | byte | Controllers usable by this game (bitmask)

1. | Standard controller
2. | Zapper
4. | R.O.B.
8. | Arkanoid controller
16. | Power Pad
32. | Four Score
64. | expansion (leave cleared)
128. | expansion (leave cleared)

BATR | 1 | 5 | byte | Boolean specifying whether the RAM is battery-backed.
VROR | 1 | 5 | byte | "If this chunk is present, then the CHR-ROM area will be considered as RAM even if ROM is present."
MIRR | 1 | 5 | byte | What CIRAM A10 is connected to:

0. | PPU A11 (horizontal mirroring)
1. | PPU A10 (vertical mirroring)
2. | Ground (one-screen A)
3. | Vcc (one-screen B)
4. | Extra memory has been added (four-screen)
5. | Mapper controlled

Shortcomings

Prior to 2013, no encoding was specified for any of the fields; 7-bit-clean ASCII was assumed, making NAME inadequate for the vast majority of non-US games. In the first quarter of 2013, UTF-8 became the encoding.

Chunks can come in any order, so conventional patching tools cannot work without going through an "unpacked" intermediary stage.

MAPR chunks are nominally supposed to use the text on the PCB, such as "NES-SNROM". However, some games have no identifying text on the PCB at all. Other games have only symbols in Japanese or Chinese. Sometimes the same PCB can have different incompatible behavior, depending on how things are populated or what things are jumpered. The workaround has been to add extra text the MAPR chunk (in the Crazy Climber case, "HVC-UNROM+74HC08").

There is no ability to specify PRG RAM outside of the MAPR chunk. Two games using VRC4 (Gradius II and Bio Miracle Bokutte Upa) use the exact same PCB, but the former adds 2KiB PRG RAM and the latter adds none.

For greater emulator compatibility, people sometimes use already-known-supported MAPR chunks to get something that's "close enough", rather than specifying a new MAPR for not-necessarily-identical behavior.

BATR chunks do not disambiguate which RAM is battery-backed, if more than one is present.

It's not clear exactly what VROR is supposed to mean—"Do not throw an error if this MAPR normally has CHR ROM but there are no CHRn chunks, just give me 8KiB of CHR RAM"? "All the data I gave you for CHR-ROM, that was actually RAM, make it writeable"? As such, Nestopia, Nintendulator, and FCEUX just ignore it.

CTRL chunks do not specify which controller should be plugged into which port, nor Famicom-only controllers, nor Super NES controllers plugged into a Famiclone or through an adapter (such as the 12-key controller or the mouse). Then again, iNES and NES 2.0 don't even try to include controller metadata in the ROM file; instead, there is a proposal in the works for a separate metadata file.

No way to fully describe PlayChoice 10 or Vs. System games.

References

libunif project on github: http://github.com/eteran/libunif
Last published version of the standard: http://raw.githubusercontent.com/eteran/libunif/master/UNIF_current.txt

UNIF/COOLBOY

UNIF MAPR COOLBOY describes a mapper designed for MMC3 multicarts. Unlike almost all other mappers, it is currently being manufactured. (Search for "COOLBOY" on eBay or AliExpress).

It adds four extra registers in lieu of (in addition to?) the normal PRG-RAM. FCEUX claims that all four of these registers are cleared on power up and reset.

Contents

1 Registers

1.1 $6000
1.2 $6001
1.3 $6002
1.4 $6003

2 Register interpretation

2.1 Banking mode = $00
2.2 Banking mode = $10
2.3 Banking mode = $40
2.4 Banking mode = $50

Registers

These registers overlay, but are independent from, any PRG-RAM present.

Mask: $E003

$6000

 7  bit  0
 ---- ----
 ABCC DEEE
 |||| ||||
 |||| |+++-- PRG offset (PRG A19, A18, A17)
 |||| +----- Alternate CHR A17
 ||++------- PRG offset (PRG A24, A23)
 |+--------- PRG mask (PRG A17 from 0: MMC3; 1: offset)
 +---------- CHR mask (CHR A17 from 0: MMC3; 1: alternate)

$6001

 7  bit  0
 ---- ----
 GHIJ KKLx
 |||| |||
 |||| ||+--- GNROM mode bank PRG size (1: 32 KiB bank, PRG A14=CPU A14; 0: 16 KiB bank, PRG A14=offset A14)
 |||+-++---- PRG offset (in order: PRG A20, A22, A21)
 ||+-------- PRG mask (PRG A20 from 0: offset; 1: MMC3)
 |+--------- PRG mask (PRG A19 from 0: offset; 1: MMC3)
 +---------- PRG mask (PRG A18 from 0: MMC3; 1: offset)

$6002

 7  bit  0
 ---- ----
 xxxx MMMM
      ||||
      ++++-- CHR offset for GNROM mode (CHR A16, A15, A14, A13)

$6003

 7  bit  0
 ---- ----
 NPxP QQRx
 || | |||
 || | +++--- PRG offset for GNROM mode (PRG A16, A15, A14)
 || +------- 1: GNROM mode; 0: MMC3 mode
 || |         (1: PRG A16...13 from QQ, L, R, CPU A14, A13 + CHR A16...10 from MMMM, PPU A12...10;
 || |          0: PRG A16...13 from MMC3 + CHR A16...A10 from MMC3 )
 |+-+------- Banking mode
 |+--------- "Weird MMC3 mode"
 +---------- Lockout (prevent further writes to these four registers, only works in MMC3 mode)

Register interpretation

The following things are always true, regardless of mode:

The CCKK bits are always connected to PRG A24..A21.
The PRG and CHR mask controls (I, H, G, B, & A) always control whether PRG A20..A17 and CHR A17 are connected to the internal MMC3 registers, or the literal values in other controls (J, EEE, & D).

Banking mode = $00

“Normal” oversize MMC3 mode.

Supports MMC3 anywhere between 128 KiB and 2 MiB, otherwise identical to ordinary MMC3. Goofy mask values will produce goofy memory layouts.

The combined register of CCKKJEEE could be thought of as a way to select one of 256 different 128 KiB PRG MMC3 games, or CCKK selecting one of 16 different 2 MiB MMC3 games.

Lockout works in this mode.

Banking mode = $10

“Normal” GNROM mode.

PRG A16 and A15 come from the QQ controls.

When in 16 KiB PRG mode (L control), PRG A14 comes from the R control. Otherwise, it comes from CPU A14.

CHR A16, A15, A14, and A13 come from MMMM controls. CHR A12, A11, and A10 come from PPU A12, A11, and A10.

The combined register of CCKKJEEEQQR could be thought of as a way to select one of 2048 different 16 KiB NROM games.

Note: The CHR and PRG mask registers STILL AFFECT THIS MODE, allowing weird splicing of MMC3 banking (with 128 KiB granularity) overlaying GNROM-style banking.

Lockout DOES NOT work in this mode.

Banking mode = $40

“Weird” MMC3 mode.

If MMC3 PRG ROM bank mode is "normal" (8+8+16F), then the PRG banks at 0xC000 and 0xE000 are fixed to 8 KiB bank 0, instead of 0xFE and 0xFF. Supposedly this effect is completely ignored when MMC3 PRG ROM bank mode is inverted (8F+8+8+8F).

The second half of each of the 2 KiB CHR banks is replaced with bank 0, and the LSB of MMC3 registers 0 and 1 work (instead of being replaced by PPU A10).

Otherwise, behaves as “normal” MMC3 mode above.

Banking mode = $50

“Weird” GNROM-ish mode.

Combine the rules mentioned above for “Normal” GNROM mode with “Weird” MMC3 mode. (These descriptions should not be contradictory.)

Lockout DOES NOT work in this mode.

Categories: Mappers with scanline IRQs, ASIC mappers, MMC3-like mappers

UNROM 512

UNROM 512 is a discrete-logic board made by RetroUSB as an extension of UNROM with up to 512kB of PRG ROM, bankable CHR RAM, an option for mapper-controlled single-screen mirroring, as well as a self-flashable configuration for rewriting PRG. Games that use this board include Study Hall and Battle Kid 2: Mountain of Torment. Since its initial creation InfiniteNesLives has replicated its design and also added an optional four-screen mirroring variation.

The iNES format assigns iNES Mapper 030 to UNROM 512.

The UNIF names for this board are UNROM-512-8, UNROM-512-16 and UNROM-512-32, depending on how much CHR RAM is present.

Contents

1 Overview
2 Board
3 Mapper
4 References

Overview

PRG ROM size: Up to 512kB (Up to 256kB on 8Bit XMAS)
PRG ROM bank size: 16kB
PRG RAM: None
CHR capacity: Up to 32kB RAM
CHR bank size: 8kB
Nametable mirroring: Solder pads select vertical, horizontal, mapper-controlled one-screen. (InfiniteNesLives variation permits four-screen mirroring)
Subject to bus conflicts: Yes, in the non-flashable configuration

Board

The example board in question is marked as follows: "Sealie Computing", "12/29/2011 revA", "UNROM 512". The backside of the board was mislabeled with "ReproPak MMC3".

The board includes 4x banks worth of full 8kB CHR-RAM (Configurable by jumpers) and 32x 16kB PRG banks.

The board can be wired in a non-flashable or self-flashable configurations.

Mirroring can be selected between Horizontal, Vertical, and Mapper-controlled One Screen. The InfiniteNesLives variation optionally adds 4-screen mirroring capabilities.

Bus conflicts are only present on the non-flashable configuration of the board.

Some images of the board:

Study Hall PCB Front
Battle Kid 2 PCB Front
PCB Back
8BIT XMAS revD PCB Front
8BIT XMAX revD PCB Back

When board is not flashable:

  Registers:
  ---------------------------
  
  Range,Mask:   $8000-FFFF, $8000
  
    $8000:  [MCCP PPPP]
      M = One screen Mirroring select
      C = CHR RAM bank
      P = PRG ROM bank
  
  PRG Setup:
  ---------------------------
       $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
      +-------------------------------+
      |     $8000     |     { -1}     |
      +---------------+---------------+
  
  CHR Setup:
  ---------------------------
        $0000   $1000   
      +-------+-------+
      |     $0000     |
      +-------+-------+

When board is self flashable:

  Registers:
  ---------------------------
  
  Range,Mask:   $8000-BFFF, $8000
                $C000-FFFF, $C000
  
    $8000:  [.... ....]
      Write a sequence of bytes here for writing to the flash. The sequence is as follows 

(This code must exist in wram):
        Erase 4KB Flash Sector:
        $C000:$01, $9555:$AA
        $C000:$00, $AAAA:$55
        $C000:$01, $9555:$80
        $C000:$01, $9555:$AA
        $C000:$00, $AAAA:$55
        $C000:BANK, ADDR:$30 (Where BANK is $00-1F, ADDR is $8000,$9000,$A000,$B000)
        Read the written location twice until you get $FF twice.

        Write a byte:
        $C000:$01, $9555:$AA
        $C000:$00, $AAAA:$55
        $C000:$01, $9555:$A0
        $C000:BANK, ADDR:DATA (Where BANK is $00-1F, ADDR is $8000-$BFFF, DATA is $00-$FF)
        Read the written location twice until you get DATA twice.

Additionally, on 8Bit XMAS boards, any writes here controls the LEDs as follows.

    $8000:  [BYGR bygr]
        B = Blue 3, Blue 4
        Y = Yellow 3, Yellow 4
        G = Green 3, Green 4
        R = Red 3, Red 4
        b = Blue 1, Blue 2
        y = Yellow 1, Yellow 2
        g = Green 1, Green 2
        r = Red 1, Red 2

  
    $C000:  [MCCP PPPP]
      M = One screen Mirroring select
      C = CHR RAM bank
      P = PRG ROM bank
  
  PRG Setup:
  ---------------------------
       $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
      +-------------------------------+
      |     $8000     |     { -1}     |
      +---------------+---------------+
  
  CHR Setup:
  ---------------------------
        $0000   $1000   
      +-------+-------+
      |     $8000     |
      +-------+-------+

Here's a schematic of the board:

             ____
A14 ---------\    \
              )    >--- ROM A14
377 Q0 ------/____/

             ____
A14 ---------\    \
              )    >--- ROM A15
377 Q1 ------/____/

             ____
A14 ---------\    \
              )    >--- ROM A16
377 Q2 ------/____/

             ____
A14 ---------\    \
              )    >--- ROM A17
377 Q3 ------/____/

             ____
A14 ---------\    \
              )    >--- ROM A18
377 Q4 ------/____/

16/32KB CHRRAM
377 Q5 --[]--+-- CHRRAM A13
             |
VCC -----[]--+
8KB CHRRAM

8/16KB CHRRAM
VCC -----[]--+
             |
377 Q6 --[]--+-- CHRRAM A14
32KB CHRRAM

ONE
377 Q7 --[]--+
             |
VERT         |
PPU A10 -[]--+-- CIRAM_A10
             |
HORIZ        |
PPU A11 -[]--+

FLASHLOCKED3
R/W ------[]-+
             |
FLASHABLE    |
GND ------[]-+-- 377_/CE

FLASHLOCKED1
VCC ------[]-------+
          ½74LS139 |
          .------. |
CPUA14----|A   Y0|-+- PRGROM_/WE
R/W ------|B   Y1|-+- 377_CLK
          |    Y2| |
/ROMSEL-+-|G   Y3| |
        | '------' |
        |          |
        +---[]-----+
       FLASHLOCKED2

FLASHLOCKED4
GND ------[]-----+
        ½74LS139 |
        .------. |
R/W ----|A   Y0| |
GND ----|B   Y1|-+- PRGROM_/OE
        |    Y2|
/ROMSEL-|G   Y3|
        '------'

With 8Bit Xmas Board, there is a second 377 chip for the LEDs, and 2 jumpers to control whether the 377 is sourcing
current to the LEDs or sinking current from them.  Additionally, the board has no flash control jumpers, and is hard-wired
flashable,  and has no CHR ram control jumpers, is hard-wired as 32KB, and it does not have the second 74LS32 chip,
required for a 512KB board, so its max size is 256KB.

Q0-----R1-----RED1-----RED2-------+
Q1--+--R6-----GRN1----------------+
    +--R5-----GRN2----------------+
Q2-----R3-----YEL1-----YEL2-------+
Q3--+--R9-----BLU1----------------+
    +--R10----BLU2----------------+
Q4-----R2-----RED3-----RED4-------+
Q5--+--R7-----GRN3----------------+
    +--R8-----GRN4----------------+
Q6-----R4-----YEL3-----YEL4-------+
Q7--+--R11----BLU3----------------+
    +--R12----BLU4----------------+
                                  |
VCC---------[]--------------------+
GND---------[]--------------------+

The board is wired in one of the following configurations:

Not Flashable:

All 4 Flash Locked jumpers are soldered.
Flashable jumper is not soldered.
74*139 is not mounted.
This configuration is subject to bus conflicts

Flashable:

All 4 Flash Locked jumpers are not soldered.
Flashable jumper is soldered.
74*139 is mounted.
This configuration is not subject to bus conflicts

The Self-flashable configuration should be implemented according to the SST39SF040's datasheet.

Example flash writing code - Flash.asm

InfiniteNesLives four-screen mirroring variation:

Two of the unused OR gates are used in combination with jumpers to disable NES mainboard VRAM/CIRAM and utilize cartridge VRAM for all pattern, name, & attribute tables.
This variation only allows CHR-RAM size of 32KB, however the last CHR-RAM bank is designated for non-pattern table use.

- This restricts the user to only having free use of the first 3 CHR-RAM banks (24KB) for pattern table tile data.

The last 8KB CHR-RAM bank is mapped to PPU $2000-3FFF (effectively $2000-3EFF due to palette data.)

The first 4KB of this last CHR-RAM bank is mapped to PPU $2000-2FFF to provide four-screen mirroring.
PPU $3000-3EFF are no longer mirrors to nametables, and actually have RAM mapped to each byte which aren't used by the PPU for rendering.

- This 3.75KB of RAM can be used by the developer as a 'scratch RAM' space only accessible via CPU $2006/2007.
- The last 256bytes of the last CHR-RAM bank are not normally accessible due to pallette data being mapped to PPU $3F00-3FFF.

Setting of both CHR RAM bank bits ($8000: 0bx11xxxxx) is permissible, but extreme care must be used when the PPU is rendering as it has the effect of mapping the last CHR-RAM bank to both PPU $0000-1FFF (Pattern tables), and PPU $2000-3F00 (Name/Attribute tables) at the same time.

- Improperly operating in this mode will render NT/AT data as tiles in PT0, and writes to PT0 will corrupt NT/AT data.
- This mode is the only means of gaining access to the last 256bytes of the last CHR-RAM bank which are normally hidden behind PPU pallette address space.

PPU memory map:

Address range | Size | Description
$0000-$0FFF | $1000 | Pattern Table 0
$1000-$1FFF | $1000 | Pattern Table 1
$2000-$23FF | $0400 | Nametable 0
$2400-$27FF | $0400 | Nametable 1
$2800-$2BFF | $0400 | Nametable 2
$2C00-$2FFF | $0400 | Nametable 3
$3000-$3EFF | $0F00 | Scratch RAM
$3F00-$3F1F | $0020 | Palette RAM indexes
$3F20-$3FFF | $00E0 | Mirrors of $3F00-$3F1F

Electrical Schematic:

             ____
PPU A13 -----\    \
              )    >--- CHRRAM A13
377 Q5 ------/____/

             ____
PPU A13 -----\    \
              )    >--- CHRRAM A14
377 Q6 ------/____/

NON-4SCREEN
PPU A13 ----[]--+
                |
GND --------[]--+---- CHRRAM /CE (Cartridge VRAM)
4SCREEN MIRROR

NON-4SCREEN
PPU /A13 ---[]--+
                |
VCC --------[]--+---- CIRAM /CE (NES mainboard VRAM)
4SCREEN MIRROR

Mapper

NES 2.0 may specify the CHR-RAM size from 8 to 32 kB, but the default for iNES should to use 32 kB.

If the Battery flag is set, which indicates the mapper is flashable, then no bus conflicts should be emulated. On the other hand, bus conflicts should be emulated if the battery flag is cleared.

Mapper controlled one-screen mirroring is only emulated if the Four-Screen mirroring flag is set, otherwise, it is hard-locked on either horizontal or vertical mirroring. This needs to be officially disambiguated in order to define how to differentiate between one-screen and four-screen. Utilization of the Four-Screen mirroring flag to denote one-screen mirroring does not follow logically from the nes 2.0 header definition.

Mapper 30 is currently only using sub mapper 0. The other sub mappers are reserved for future use.

Supported in FCEUX as of r3071, Supported in BizHawk as of r6322

References

INES Mapper DischDocs

Categories: Discrete logic mappers, Mappers with CHR RAM, Mappers with bus conflicts

User:Banshaku/CA65 Constants

; NES registers: PPU releated
;--------------------------------------------------------
; PPU Controler (write)
; Various flags controlling PPU operation
;
;Input:
;========
;76543210
;||||||||
;||||||++- Base nametable address
;||||||    (0 = $2000; 1 = $2400; 2 = $2800; 3 = $2C00)
;|||||+--- VRAM address increment per CPU read/write of PPUDATA
;|||||     (0: increment by 1, going across; 1: increment by 32, going down)
;||||+---- Sprite pattern table address for 8x8 sprites (0: $0000; 1: $1000)
;|||+----- Background pattern table address (0: $0000; 1: $1000)
;||+------ Sprite size (0: 8x8; 1: 8x16)
;|+------- PPU master/slave select (has no effect on the NES)
;+-------- Generate an NMI at the start of the vertical blanking interval (0: off; 1: on)
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_CTRL   = $2000

; Flags for PPU
PPU_CTRL_ADR_NT0    = %00000000 ; Select name table 0
PPU_CTRL_ADR_NT1    = %00000001 ; Select name table 1
PPU_CTRL_ADR_NT2    = %00000010 ; Select name table 2
PPU_CTRL_ADR_NT3    = %00000011 ; Select name table 3
PPU_CTRL_INC32      = %00000100 ; Increment PPU address by 32 bytes, going down
PPU_CTRL_SPR_PT1    = %00001000 ; Sprite pattern table 1
PPU_CTRL_BG_PT1     = %00010000 ; Background pattern table 1
PPU_CTRL_SPR_8x16   = %00100000 ; Sprites are 8x16
PPU_CTRL_NMI        = %10000000 ; write this value to PPUCTRL to enable NMI

;--------------------------------------------------------
; PPU Mask (write)
; Screen enable, masking, and intensity 
;
;Input:
;========
;76543210
;||||||||
;|||||||+- Grayscale (0: normal color; 1: AND all palette entries
;|||||||   with 0x30, effectively producing a monochrome display;
;|||||||   note that colour emphasis STILL works when this is on!)
;||||||+-- Enable background in leftmost 8 pixels of screen (0: clip; 1: display)
;|||||+--- Enable sprite in leftmost 8 pixels of screen (0: clip; 1: display)
;||||+---- Enable background rendering
;|||+----- Enable sprite rendering
;||+------ Intensify reds (and darken other colors)
;|+------- Intensify greens (and darken other colors)
;+-------- Intensify blues (and darken other colors)
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_MASK    = $2001

PPU_MASK_GREYSCALE  = %00000001 ; All colors becomes grey scales
PPU_MASK_BG_NOCLIP  = %00000010 ; enables background no clip
PPU_MASK_SPR_NOCLIP = %00000100 ; enables sprite no clip
PPU_MASK_BG_ON      = %00001000 ; enables background rendering
PPU_MASK_SPR_ON     = %00010000 ; enables sprite rendering
PPU_MASK_INT_RED    = %00100000 ; Intensify red
PPU_MASK_INT_GREEN  = %01000000 ; Intensify green
PPU_MASK_INT_BLUE   = %10000000 ; Intensify blue


;--------------------------------------------------------
; PPU status (read)
; 
;
; Caution: Reading PPUSTATUS at the exact start of vertical blank will return a 0 
;          in D7 but clear the latch anyway, causing the program to miss frames. See 
;          NMI for details.
;
;output:
;========
;76543210
;||||||||
;|||+++++- Unimplemented
;||+------ Sprite overflow. The PPU can handle only eight sprites on one
;||        scanline and sets this bit if it starts dropping sprites.
;||        Normally, this triggers when there are 9 sprites on a scanline,
;||        but the actual behavior is significantly more complicated.
;|+------- Sprite 0 Hit.  Set when a nonzero pixel of sprite 0 'hits'
;|         a nonzero background pixel.  Used for raster timing.
;+-------- Vertical blank has started (0: not in VBLANK; 1: in VBLANK)
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_STATUS = $2002 ; Can be read to get current PPU status

PPU_STATUS_SPR_OVERFLOW = %00100000 ; More than 8 sprites per scanline
PPU_STATUS_SPRITE0      = %01000000 ; Sprite 0 was hit
PPU_STATUS_IN_VBLANK    = %10000000 ; The vlbank as started

;--------------------------------------------------------
; OAM address (write)
;
; Write the address of OAM you want to access here. Most games just 
; write $00 here and then use OAM_DMA ($4014).
;
; This register also seems to affect Sprite 0 Hit, though it is not
; yet understood exactly how it does. The upper 5 bits of this register 
; seem to select which SPR-RAM data is used for sprites 0 and 1 (instead 
; of the first 8 bytes of SPR-RAM), though actual behavior varies between resets. 
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_OAM_ADDR  = $2003 ; OAM address. Rarerly used (why?)


;--------------------------------------------------------
; OAM data port (r/w)
;
; Write OAM data here. Writes will increment OAMADDR; reads won't.
;
; Most games access this register through $4014 instead. Reading 
; OAMDATA while the PPU is rendering will expose internal OAM accesses 
; during sprite evaluation and loading; Micro Machines does this. 
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_OAM_DATA = $2004 ; OAM data port


;--------------------------------------------------------
; Scroll register (2x write)
;
; After reading PPUSTATUS to reset the address latch, write the horizontal
; and vertical scroll offsets here just before turning on the screen:
;
; Example:
; 	bit PPUSTATUS
; 	; possibly other code goes here
; 	lda cam_position_x
; 	sta PPUSCROLL
; 	lda cam_position_y
; 	sta PPUSCROLL
;
; Horizontal offsets range from 0 to 255. "Normal" vertical offsets range from
; 0 to 239. (Values of 240 to 255 are treated as -16 through -1 in a way, pulling 
; tile data from the attribute table.)
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_SCROLL = $2005 ; Sets X/Y scrolling of background


;--------------------------------------------------------
; VRAM address register (2x write)
;
; After reading PPUSTATUS to reset the address latch, write the 
; 16-bit address of VRAM you want to access here, upper byte first. 
; Valid addresses are $0000-$3FFF.
;
; Access to PPUSCROLL and PPUADDR during screen refresh produces 
; interesting raster effects; the starting position of each scanline 
; can be set to any pixel position in nametable memory. For more information, 
; see "The Skinny on NES Scrolling" by loopy, available from the main site. 
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_ADDR   = $2006 ; Sets VRAM address in PPU


;--------------------------------------------------------
; VRAM data register (r/w)
;
; When the screen is turned off in PPUMASK or during vertical blank, 
; read or write data from VRAM through this port.
;
; Reads are delayed by one cycle; discard the first byte read. Do not 
; attempt to access this register while the PPU is rendering; if you do, 
; Bad Things^(TM) will happen (i.e. graphical glitches and RAM corruption). 
;--------------------------------------------------------
PPU_DATA   = $2007 ; Writes data to current VRAM address

;--------------------------------------------------------
; MMC3 registers
;
; No doc yet, must check wiki
;--------------------------------------------------------
MMC3_CTRL        = $8000
MMC3_PAGE        = $8001
MMC3_MIRROR      = $A000
MMC3_SRAM        = $A001
MMC3_IRQ_COUNTER = $C000
MMC3_IRQ_RELOAD  = $C001
MMC3_IRQ_DISABLE = $E000
MMC3_IRQ_ENABLE  = $E001

MMC3_MIRROR_V =	0
MMC3_MIRROR_H =	1

MMC3_SRAM_DISABLE = 0
MMC3_SRAM_ENABLE  = 1

;------------------------
; Common memory addresses
OAM               = $0400

; Sprite DMA
SPR_DMA           = $4014

; Joypads related
JOYPAD_PORT1      = $4016
JOYPAD_PORT2      = $4017

BTN_A             = %10000000
BTN_B             = %01000000
BTN_SELECT        = %00100000
BTN_START         = %00010000
BTN_UP            = %00001000
BTN_DOWN          = %00000100
BTN_LEFT          = %00000010
BTN_RIGHT         = %00000001

; Sound related
APU_REGISTER      = $4000
APU_SQUARE1       = $4000
APU_SQUARE2       = $4004
APU_TRIANGLE      = $4008
APU_NOISE         = $400C
APU_DELTA         = $4010
APU_MASTERCTRL    = $4015
APU_FRAMECOUNTER  = $4017   ; Note: same as joy 2

; flags
APU_FRAMECOUNTER_IRQ_CLEAR = %01000000


;--------------------------------------------------------
; Sprites attributes:
;76543210
;||||||||
;||||||++- Palette (4 to 7) of sprite
;|||+++--- Unimplemented, reads back as 0
;||+------ Priority (0: in front of background; 1: behind background)
;|+------- Flip sprite horizontally
;+-------- Flip sprite vertically
;--------------------------------------------------------
SPR_PRIORITY_BACK   = %00100000 ; The sprite priority is behind background
SPR_PRIORITY_FRONT  = %00000000 ; The sprite priority is in front of background
SPR_FLIP_HORIZONTAL = %01000000 ; The sprite is flipped horizontally
SPR_FLIP_VERTIAL    = %10000000 ; The sprite is flipped vertically

User:Koitsu

My name is Jeremy Chadwick, otherwise known as koitsu, k9, or (more famously) Y0SHi/Yoshi. I've done lots of things, just like every other human.

I'm an administrator for the nesdev forum and nesdev wiki. If you have problems requiring attention with either of these, I'm pretty easy to reach.

Contents

1 Accomplishments

1.1 Parodius Networking
1.2 Console development / homebrew
1.3 FreeBSD
1.4 Other

2 Ramblings
3 Personal
4 Links
5 References

Accomplishments

Parodius Networking

I ran Parodius Networking, a free web/shell/mail/etc. hosting service, for about 18 years. We closed our doors on August 2012. We hosted numerous emulation, console, and romhacking websites, such as:

nesdev (NES/Famicom console development)
NES World (NES/Famicom fan site)
Donut/The Whirlpool (major romhacking hub) (R.I.P.)
Archaic Ruins (emulation news site) (R.I.P.)
NESticle (NES/Famicom emulator) (R.I.P.)
Genecyst (Genesis/Megadrive emulator) (R.I.P.)
Joy Electric (analog synth-pop band)

I've tried to take photos of our co-location cages over the years.

Console development / homebrew

Author of public-domain SNES documentation during the early-to-mid 90s.
Author of public-domain NES documentation, a.k.a. nestech.txt, during the late 90s into the early 21st century.
Author of the replacement Final Fantasy 2 intro for Neo Demiforce's English translation.

In March 2015, I decided to re-do the intro code, comment it, and make it public (in hopes of it being good learning material), along with a "why/how" write-up. I've finished the revamped code, but not the write-up. I'll release it when everything is polished.

Author of TRaCER, a 6502/65816 disassembler for MS-DOS, written in Turbo Pascal. And yes I'm aware of a bug in its 65816 opcode table.  :-(
Still actively doing NES/SNES romhacking projects of my own, including a bunch of work on Otogirisou.

FreeBSD

FreeBSD community member from 1997 to 2008.

I still use FreeBSD but I do not participate in the community any longer.[1]
I still report lots of bugs though.[2][3]
I keep an archive of random things I've dealt with or fixed on FreeBSD.

Ex-FreeBSD ports committer.
Author of bsdhwmon, an open source SMBus-focused hardware monitoring utility for FreeBSD.

Other

Was in an Apple IIGS demo group called Digital Exodus back in the early 90s. We released some useful CDAs (ex. DOCVu) and an Xmas Demo in 1993.[4]
Was in a console/"hacking" group called Damaged Cybernetics in the mid-90s. I'm still not exactly sure why; it was very odd.  :-)
News poster for Zophar's Domain during the "emulation peak" of the late 90s.
Publicized several flaws with Logitech products, especially USB mice.
Working with storage subsystems, particularly ATA/SATA (including protocol and SMART), and doing reliable software-based data recovery. You'll find me helping out occasionally over on the DSLReports/BBR forum.

I still actively do this today.

Ramblings

Why I still run Windows XP in 2015 — highly detailed. If only Microsoft listened... :-( -- Update: since roughly April 2015, I've grudgingly upgraded to Windows 7 Ultimate
Why I stopped doing nesdev for almost a decade (the related nesdev forum thread).
A bit egocentric, but: I still wonder why nobody has ever gotten around to interviewing me about either Parodius Networking or my role in emulation and/or console development.

On the flip side, The New 8-Bit Heroes folks did an in-person interview with me in March 2015 about my NES documentation and homebrew efforts.
In May 2015, MIT Press published Nathan Altice's book titled I AM ERROR, in which my aforementioned efforts are cited as references. I'll admit it's kinda weird seeing your name in published print.

Personal

I was born January 1977.
I'm originally from Oregon but presently reside in California (Silicon Valley).
The first programming language I ever used was Logo on an original Apple II. I enjoyed it, but really took to Applesoft BASIC shortly thereafter. I started doing 6502 assembly/machine language in 7th grade (1988 or so?), and then 65816 once I got my own Apple IIGS. I've done lots of other assembly over the years (ex. 6810, PIC16c84, x86/486), but enjoy the 65xxx series CPUs the most.
I studied Mandarin for 4 years (high school) and about 6 months outside of school. I've also since learned to read/write Korean (maybe 1st or 2nd grade level, but hey, better than nothing).
For transporation, I ride a mountain bike; I don't drive (by choice).
..and I don't vote (by choice); I have no political affiliations.
I like all kinds of music (you will find Iron Maiden next to Henson Cargill next to Lionel Ritchie next to De Lyckliga Kompisarna next to Carpenter Brut).
I'm an avid fan of the horror genre (movies, books, whatever); I absolutely adore H.P. Lovecraft.
Since 2001 I've had moderate-to-severe IBS and experience some form of its effects on a daily basis.

I only mention this because IBS has significantly impacted my life (in a very negative way) and helps explain both some parts of my behaviour (maybe even personality?) and how I live my life the way I do.
Partially as a result of my condition, my weight has fluctuated wildly over several years (maximum being 195 pounds, lowest being 140 pounds; I'm 5 foot 9 inches). I felt my best at around 165, but that was also when I was working out every other day.

Links

Home page: http://jdc.koitsu.org/
Blog: https://koitsu.wordpress.com/
Twitter: https://twitter.com/koitsu2009
LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/jeremychadwick
DSLReports/BBR profile: http://www.dslreports.com/profile/659143

References

↑ Why I left the FreeBSD Project: https://koitsu.wordpress.com/2008/12/13/why-i-left-the-freebsd-project/
↑ FreeBSD PRs for jdc@koitsu.org: https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/buglist.cgi?email1=jdc%40koitsu.org&emailreporter1=1&emailtype1=substring&order=Importance&query_format=advanced
↑ FreeBSD PRs for freebsd@jdc.parodius.com: https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/buglist.cgi?email1=freebsd%40jdc.parodius.com&emailreporter1=1&emailtype1=substring&order=Importance&query_format=advanced
↑ Ninjaforce - Special - IIGS Demo Scene reviewed - Xmas Demo: http://www.ninjaforce.com/html/special_demoscene_dexmas.html

User:Koitsu/Game cheats

Contents

1 Game cheats

1.1 1943 - The Battle of Midway
1.2 Adventures of Dino Riki, The
1.3 Code Name: Viper
1.4 Legend of Zelda, The
1.5 Mega Man 2
1.6 River City Ransom

Game cheats

Throughout the years I've reverse-engineered a lot of games, as well as Game Genie or Pro Action Replay/Rocky codes, to figure out the internals. In most cases I do this because I don't want have to "grind" -- given enough time, I'd be able to accomplish the task at hand, so why not skip all that nonsense? A good example is gold/currency. I paid my dues sitting in front of a TV for hours as a kid, so I think I've earned the right.  :-)

Anyway, I wanted to make a list of games and memory locations locations of such things. I tend to focus on just zero page/RAM data and not stuff in ROM, but technically any memory location can be used (the tricky part with NES games is being precise about which PRG page has the cheat applied to it -- that's one of the reasons many emulators have a "Compare" field alongside "Location" and "Value"!).

All below games are assumed to be the NTSC versions. I'll try to denote differences between game versions (e.g. PRG0 vs. PRG1) if it applies.

1943 - The Battle of Midway

Location | Description
$0410 | Current energy, ones place. Range $00 to $09
$0411 | Current energy, tenths place. Range $00 to $09
$0412 | Current energy, hundredths place. Range $00 to $09

For infinite energy, setting $0410, $0411, and $0412 all to $09 is needed -- just $0412 by itself is insufficient: you CAN die in some situations!

Adventures of Dino Riki, The

Location | Description
$0089 | Current health (energy) value. Range $00 to $04
$009D | Active weapon type: $00 = rock, $01 = axe, $02 = boomerang, $03 = torch. Other values result in glitches and/or game crashing
$009E | Wings status: $00 = player lacks wings, $01 or greater = player has wings

Code Name: Viper

Location | Description
$06E0 | Handgun bullet count. Range $00 to $80
$06E2 | Machine gun bullet count. Range $00 to $80
$06F8 | Current health (energy) value. Range $00 to $04

The current health (energy) value can exceed the number of health containers (ex. if health container count is 2 and $06F8 = $04, then player will actually have 4 health)

Legend of Zelda, The

Location | Description
$04F0 | Invincibility timer value. Range $00 to $FF. See below notes
$0658 | Current bombs. Range $00 to $10, though game core will work with values up to $FF
$066D | Current rupies. Range $00 to FF
$066E | Current keys. Range $00 to $09, but game core will work with values up to $FF

Invincibility timer: the game core decrements this by 1 fairly quickly (a value of $FF will reach $00 in approximately 8 seconds). For "visually accurate" permanent invincibility, use a value $FF with a compare value of $00 (i.e. timer resets to $FF once reaching $00)
Details of how the bomb/rupie/key printing code works

Mega Man 2

Location | Description
$004B | Invincibility timer value. Range $00 to $FF. See below notes

Invincibility timer: the game core decrements this by 1 fairly quickly (a value of $FF will reach $00 in approximately 4 seconds). For "visually accurate" permanent invincibility, use a value $FF with a compare value of $00 (i.e. timer resets to $FF once reaching $00)

River City Ransom

Location | Description
$04C7 | Player 1 money, cents value. BCD encoded. Range $00 to $99
$04C8 | Player 1 money, dollars value. BCD encoded. Range $00 to $99
$04C9 | Player 1 money, 100-dollars value. BCD encoded. Range $00 to $09

Money example: for player 1 to have $367.49, you'd need $04C7 = $49, $04C8 = $67, $04C9 = $03

User:Lidnariq/Mapper thoughts

Contents

1 EtherNES 1

1.1 Option 1

1.1.1 Parts
1.1.2 Memory map

1.2 Option 2

2 Easier nametables, finer palette zones
3 Pixel-perfect IRQs with clockslides
4 Fake sprite 0 IRQs
5 Very fine-grained CHR banking
6 8×8 attributes

6.1 8x16 attributes, compatible with all famiclones

7 Hardware vertical parallax
8 Oversize PRG for some ASIC mappers

8.1 MMC4
8.2 Sunsoft 3 and Sunsoft 4
8.3 VRC3
8.4 LZ93D50
8.5 TAM-S1
8.6 FCG-1 and -2

EtherNES 1

A cartridge designed to provide ethernet in as simple a manner as practical, for use with Contiki.

Option 1

The design is intentionally similar to the 64NIC+ ethernet cartridge for the Commodore 64, even though the CS8900A is comparatively expensive.

Parts

1 × SST39SF010A, 128 KiB FLASH EEPROM, for booting
2 × AS6C1008, 128 KiB static RAM, one each for PRG RAM and CHR RAM
2 × 74'161, both set up to clear on reset.

One selects a 32 KiB slice of PRG
The other selects an 8 KiB slice of CHR RAM.

1 × 74'139
1 × 74'20

One NAND4 produces /INTSEL=NAND4(M2,/ROMSEL,A14,A13) and one decoder produces /RD6xxx, /WR6xxx, /RD7xxx, and /WR7xxx.
Other NAND4 produces /RD.
2nd decoder selects RAM or ROM as appropriate.

CS8900A or LAN91C96 already have drivers in the Contiki source tree

Other cheaper options: RTL8029, CP2200, ENC424J600, AX88796

Ethernet transformer

Memory map

$7xxx - CS8900A

http://www.cirrus.com/en/products/cs8900a.html
Unlike the C64 NIC, use the memory-mappable portion of the CS8900A.
CS8900A does not have a separate enable, just /{MEM,IO}{R,W}; the address bus must be stable before these signals fall.
Why does the 64NIC+ not connect /IRQ ?
Obviously no DMA controller.

READS from $6xxx - latching CPU A0..A3: PRG bank '161 (0,1,2,3 = ROM; C,D,E,F=RAM). Q3 determines which IC. Cleared on hardware reset.
WRITES to $6xxx - latching CPU D0..D3: CHR bank '161
$8000-$FFFF: PRG ROM or RAM, according to value at $7xxx.

Option 2

The ENCx24J600 is a still-actively manufactured parallel I/O network IC made by Microchip. Fortunately, it can support the 6502's R/W interface, but unfortunately it uses +ve sense signalling for all other signals.

Possibility: This IC supports a 15-bit address memory-mapped form; allowing mapping the NIC into $8000-$FFFF.

Problem: the 6502 vectors now point at garbage. Ask Microchip what reading from those addresses do? If not acceptable, invert A14?
Another problem: The driver has to either fit in the NIC's RAM, or do everything via trampolines
Nifty feature: stream DPCM over ethernet. (Packets will have to be realigned, but this IC has an internal DMA feature that could do copies accordingly)

Possibility: Re-use the PRG or CHR bank to select a 4 KiB slice to map.

Weird feature: stream OAM over ethernet (why?)

Possibility: Only allow I/O to the the 512 bytes starting at $7Exx; all access to the internal memory is via the indirect registers.

If the NIC's A9..A11 are tied high, a latch and an OR gate lets us hijack OAM DMA (which writes to $2004) to write data to the NIC (pointer writes via 0x7E84) ... but is it useful to be able to transfer data to the NIC rapidly?

Possibility: Use multiplexed bus, latching the 8 LSBs while directly driving the 7 MSBs. Need a 4th write trigger (ethernet ALE, ethernet CE, CHR bank, PRG bank) or to combine PRG/CHR banking register.
Simplest possible option #1: NOT self-writable NROM with a 74'21 (quad AND) to map the NIC from $6000-$7FFF. Slightly clever rewiring (CPU A12→NIC A14,CPU A11→NIC A13,12,11) allows 6 KiB of the 24 KiB of RAM inside the NIC (0x0000-0x07FF, 0x3800-0x47FF) to be directly available to the NES, while ensuring that the NIC registers (0x7E00-0x7FFF) are always available.
Option #1a: 74'20 and 74'04, allows self-writable NROM, and increasing available RAM to 12 KiB. Maps NIC 0x0XXX to $7XXX, 0x3XXX to $6XXX, 0x4XXX to $5XXX, and NIC registers at $4E00-$4FFF.
Simplest possible option #2: use NIC RAM in lieu of CHR-RAM. Addressing NIC becomes a total PITA because of the PPU's auto-increment. But streaming graphic data becomes very easy.

Unfortunately, the shape of the front-loader means that the ethernet jack itself will have to be mounted both rotated 90°, and at the very top of the cartridge (22mm clearance, 16mm wide jacks)

Easier nametables, finer palette zones

Replace standard PPU nametable/attribute table with just one nametable, 32x30 tiles in size, each tile is 16x16 and uses 8x1 palette zones.

using 32×30 allows us to reuse the scroll registers, rather than having fine X be magically somewhere else
Each tile is thus 72 bytes (256 pixels × (18 bits/8 pixels)).
Total memory for tiles in this manner: 18 KiB.

Pixel-perfect IRQs with clockslides

An interface to fire an IRQ at a specific X/Y coordinate that works by

firing the IRQ approximately 14cy too early
uses an injected clockslide to fix up any slop in initial IRQ firing time

Since there's already 3 pixels of intrinsic slop, the two axes can be X/2 and Y. Y is ever-so-slightly larger than a byte, so setting (255=scanline before NMI) and not allowing interrupts during the first 6 scanlines of vblank is an ok compromise.

Fake sprite 0 IRQs

IRQ when PPU address reads from a specific address, or
Snoop on CPU reads, monitoring for reads from $2002, and fire an IRQ

Very fine-grained CHR banking

64 banks of 64 bytes (4 tiles) each, allowing changing the bank a sprite comes from mid-render. Not clear if useful for anything but masking sprites.

Could be combined with some amount of address-line math to prevent sprite pop-on on PAL systems, and with a barrel shifter to prevent sprite pop-on on the left side of the screen without using the PPU's native masking.

8×8 attributes

Assuming a mapper with 4 banks of 8 KiB each of CHR-RAM.

On nametable reads: latch y and x in address: 1x YXYY YYyX XXXx

Detect attribute reads: 1x YX11 11YY YXXX

On attribute reads, disable NTRAM and select one of four banks depending on y and x.

/AttrIO = NAND4(PPU A9..A6)
CIRAM/OE = NAND2(PPU A13,/AttrIO)
NTread = '139 (/RD=0, PPU A13=1, /AttrIO=1)

NTread: latch PPU A0, A5 in a 74'75 or whatever

ATTRread = '139 (/RD=0, PPU A13=1, /AttrIO=0)
CHRRAM/OE = PPU A13 AND /AttrIO
CHRRAM A13,A14 = multiplex(ATTRread,BankedA13..A14,LatchedA0A5)
Separately, use other half of NAND4 and/or 74'139 and 74'75 to latch requested CHR bank from CPU

Total parts: ½ 74'20, ½ 74'139, 74'00, 74'75, 74'153

With both 4KiB and 8KiB banking, all four nametables will have different attributes, ignoring what CIRAM A10 is connected to. If used with a mapper that supported 1 or 2 KiB banking will, it would allow something with more finesse.

8x16 attributes, compatible with all famiclones

Compatible with all famiclones because CIRAM/CE is still tied to ground.

Using three 74xx ICs:

74'21: AttrIO = AND4(PPU.A9..A6)
74'161: 74161./PE = AttrIO ; 74161.CP = PPU./RD ; 74161.D0 = PPU.A0 ; LA0 = 74161.Q0
74'153: CIRAMA10 = AttrIO?LA0:PPUA11

Using PPU A5 instead of A0 allows for 16x8 attribute zones.

Latching both A0 and A5, changing AttrIO to include PPU A13, and connecting to CHR ROM address lines allows for 1024 different tiles per nametable.

Hardware vertical parallax

Putting an N-bit adder between PPU and CHR A0…A2,A4…A11 would allow for tiles to be scrolled independently. Inverting the result of that adder would flip that set of tiles vertically.

In combination with a mapper that provided 1 KiB banks, and depending on how many address lines passed through the adder vs just directly connected to CHR, it would allow 1,2,4,8,16,32, or 64 independent 8-pixel-wide scrolling regions that were 512,256,128,64,32,16, or 8 pixels high, respectively.

Oversize PRG for some ASIC mappers

Almost all ASIC mappers that support 16+16F banking can trivially be extended to a full 8 bits of PRG address space.

For example:

MMC4

74'138, 4+ bit latch, 74'32. 74'138 decodes writes to $Axxx. Latch latches D4 through D7 during those writes. 74'32 implements fixed upper bank.

Sunsoft 3 and Sunsoft 4

Same hardware. 74'138 decodes writes to $F8xx or $Fxxx, respectively. Otherwise identical.

VRC3

Same hardware, decode writes to $Fxxx. ASIC only implements three bits, so to maximize the address space, a full five bits of latch and OR gates are needed.

LZ93D50

Same hardware. Decode writes when (A & 0x800F) == 0x8008

TAM-S1

74'161, 74'00. Invert D4 and D5 using two NAND gates. Latch /D4 and /D5 on /ROMSEL=0 & R/W=0 (standard discrete logic mapper '161 circuit). Generate PRG A18 and A19 as NAND2(/Q4,A14) and NAND2(/Q5,A15).

FCG-1 and -2

Decode writes when (A & 0x200F) == 0x2008; this just fits into the 7 inputs on a 74'138 + 74'161. One mirror of this register overlaps a mirror of the PPU, and two mirrors overlap the PRG, but that shouldn't matter.

User:Myask/Myapper thoughts

Contents

1 8x8 attributes, beginning of 8x1
2 8x1 attributes?
3 Flipping
4 DMA theft
5 Slideshow mirroring
6 Fill Mode

8x8 attributes, beginning of 8x1

User:Myask/MyaGrafx

8x1 attributes?

It's all in the fine Y and keeping it in mind. The intensive solution is to watch the PPU bus and keep our own copy of PPUSCROLL, which requires knowing the latch and thus watching several of the registers. Pattern-fetch snooping can yield it, but as it is after the attribute fetch, it does not work for the first fetch of a scanline. Triple fetch is after said 2 pre-fetched tiles. Is really a double-fetch duplicating next one normally, but VBLANK is between the last line's double-fetch and the first of pre-render, which is interrupted by whatever the program wants to access. One could count tiles, then:

if(this_fetch == last_fetch) reset(counter);
if(is_AT(this_fetch) && is_NT(last_fetch)) counter += 1;
if(counter == (32? 33? 34?)) //override the usual pattern, we're doing first prefetch
///...after which we can just let the pattern fetch give us the information

But is this any simpler than register-snooping? This segues nicely into a scanline counter interrupt, though for some reason I have the thought of a nametable-relative Y-based interrupt instead (which is just a different frame of reference on the same thing.) Resetting to "scanline 0" if no triple-fetch detected in 128 CPU clocks seems workable.

Flipping

BG tileflipping is pretty easy.

chr_a[2:0] = ppu_a[2:0] ^ {3{is_chr_access & vert_flip}};
ppu_d[7:0] = (is_chr_access) ? (horiz_flip ? chr_d[0:7] : chr_d[7:0]) : something_else);

If one stored the attributes in the same byte you can piggyback that to set the flip bits. But what to use the other four bits for? Just do two tiles per byte? Allow MMC5-like extended tile index allowance? Allow swapping of two colors in the attribute?

wire invert_cur = ppu_a[4] ? invert_plane1 : invert_plane0;
ppu_d[7:0] = (is_chr_access) ? (invert_cur ^ (horiz_flip ? chr_d[0:7] : chr_d[7:0])) : something_else);

Rotation would require orthogonal accesses, all-but requiring in-chip CHR. Note: one should only do this if things are following (AT,NT,PT,PT) pattern. If not, one is fetching sprite patterns. While it is of mild interest that there are 64 sprites filling out the 32x32 count, OAM already deals with that better.

Though, one could use the garbage NT fetches (which are a double fetch, can leech off logic detecting the triple fetch!) to add extended per-sprite banking, though detecting which sprite is which is Another Problem, requiring either duplicating/spying OAM's tile entry, or requiring some specific pattern of sprite arrangement (useful for static images?). This also allows some odd bits, like changing sprite tile mid-sprite (vertically).

DMA theft

If you watch for a $4014 write, you can then watch the DMA happen...and thus have another destination to copy it to. This could alleviate the VBLANK crunch a bit (for e.g. the 8x1 mapper), as DMA copies much faster than program can. Obviously bringing it into the chip 'à la' MMC5 means one could allow access to both buses, but that costs a lot of chip resources.

Slideshow mirroring

PPUDOUT[0:7] = PPUDIN[0:7] & {8,{~PPUA[11]&PPUA[9]}};// (relies on tile 0 being blank)
CIRAMA10 = PPUA[10];
//ab
//00

Of course, the slideshow effect could be done without any special hardware just by using a render-disable raster effect instead of a scroll.

Fill Mode

…is an expansion of the above:

wire is_fill_mode = (nt_mapping[PPU_A[11:10]] == FILL_MODE) && is_nt_fetch;
PPUDOUT[0:7] = is_fill_mode ? fill_chr[0:7] : chrdin[0:7];

Actually, now I think it, "CIRAM0, CIRAM1, disable, fill mode" isn't a bad set of 4. Catch is, of course, that that would mean cartside NT0-3 makes it 12 bits of mirroring to allow full control, two writes. That leaves four bits of unused write…

User:Myask/Universal Mapper Description Language

Discussion thread.

Contents

1 Needed features
2 Specification

2.1 Comments
2.2 Declarations:
2.3 Statements:
2.4 Operators
2.5 Execution blocks
2.6 Handy Shorthand Defines

3 NROM-256 example

Needed features

Been thinking about making some better way to talk about mappers, as described in this post among several other places on our boards. Parts/functions

Define state bits

include easy ROM/RAM chip(/internal) declaration; don't want to exclude MagicFloor nor MMC5/6 from "correct" description

Logic
Arbitrary address bus size for chips?

Convenience addtions

Conditional operations (optional but helps user-side…but makes it harder program-side)

some header fields as parameters might be desirable (mirroring, chip sizes)
on the other hand, they are different boards in some manner. Perhaps only as solder-pad options?

Cartridge connector pins as predefined signal names, or a module (to allow picking 60 or 72-pin)
Option to autoconnect power, ground, address lines that are not in file

like connecting PPU_A[0:7] to CHR_ROM_A[0:7] if CHR_ROM_A[0:7] do not appear in the description)
Also autoconnect CIC

Extra function thoughts

Outputs (e.g. LED)
Inputs (e.g. DIPswitch, solder pads)
Describing expansion port devices in similar manner
Describing controller port devices in similar manner

Hard Part

Expansion audio (analog, can involve extra oscillators as VRC7 audio does)

Specification

Comments

//c-style
/*and c-style*/
//Let's also treat all whitespace the same (except newlines terminating //, blocks)
//and "to" should be ignored in whitespace

Declarations:

mapper name begin
//contents
end name;

The outer part. Technically a block started with begin/end. Name optional.

mem name (address lines, data lines, writable, class);

writable can be RAM or ROM.
Class can be PRG, CHR, VRAM, [audio?] and MISC. Class controls default connections, and helps make obvious to readers what a thing is.

(see NROM example for default connections. Any prg gets CPU_A, CPU_D, /ROMSEL ("ROMSEL_n"), and optionally the R/W signal if it's a RAM. chr/vram gets PPU_A, PPU_D, read/writes, and enable depending on PPU_A[13] (or /A13 if VRAM)

solder name to /*contents*/; //can block if desired
jumper name to /*contents*/; //can block if desired
dip name to /*contents*/; //can block if desired: same as solder for emulator

dipswitch

Just different name, really both just a state-based if statement, and these state bits are not settable except hardware(emulator)-side, unlike…

register name; 
reg name;//short form

init name to value; //can refer to iNES header fields like mirroring

Not that iNES is something we want much of, but it'll cut down on file redundancy.

Statements:

connect x to y to z; //any size netlist, whitespace-separated
= x y z; //shortform
set name to value; //set a state bit
<= x y; //shortform

Operators

bitwise & AND | OR ^ XOR ~ invert
logical &&AND ||OR ^^XOR !not
mathematical + - * binary operations, -negation
{concatenate, concatenatee} [bus-index:range] {3 duplicate} //as in verilog

Execution blocks

on CPU_WRITE /*do stuff*/;
on PPU_WRITE
on CPU_READ
on PPU_READ
on CLOCK

Handy Shorthand Defines

bankreg name (which bus, width, address lines replaced, address mask selecting=equals what, which bus to write [inc A or D to write], mask to write=equals what,, written bits);
fixedbank (which bus, width, address lines replaced=with what, address mask selecting=equals what);

e.g.

bankreg bnrom (CPU, 2, 16:15, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D[1:0]);

bankreg bxrom (CPU, 8, 22:15, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D[7:0]);

bankreg gnrom_cpu (CPU, 2, 16:15, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D[5:4]);
bankreg gnrom_ppu (PPU, 2, 14:13, 16'h2000=16'h0000, CPU_D, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D[1:0]);

bankreg magic_series_cpu (CPU, 7, 21:15, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D[7:1]);
bankreg magic_series_ppu (PPU, 8, 20:13, 16'h2000=16'h0000, CPU_D, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D[7:0]);

bankreg unrom (CPU, 3, 16:14, 16'hC000=16'h8000, CPU_D, 16'h8000=16'h8000, CPU_D[2:0]);
fixedbank unrom_hi (CPU, 3, 16:14=3'b111, 16hC000=16'hC000);

The idea here is that it autogenerates a register of appropriate width, and statements in ON_x_WRITE to write that register when its write mask equality is met, and sets the appropriate address lines when its select mask is met. fixedbank does not need a register, obviously. So, for bnrom, it would expand to

reg bnrom_bank[1:0];
on CPU_WRITE begin
	if (CPU_A & 16'h8000 == 16'h8000) bnrom_bank <= CPU_D[1:0];
	if (CPU_A & 16'h8000 == 16'h8000) prg.a[16:15] = bnrom_bank;
end CPU_WRITE;
on CPU_READ if (CPU_A & 16'h8000=16'h8000) prg.a[16:15] = bnrom_bank;

NROM-256 example

mapper NROM_256V begin
 //without autofills
 //aside from the mirroring, strikes me as the same as "default connections"?
//component section
 prgrom prg(32KiB); 
 //could also write 256Kib..but seems like a source of many typo problems
 //perhaps go by address line, data line counts?
 chrrom chr(8KiB);
 //only difference between PRG and CHR def'ns are its default connections
 //and outputs
 CIC cic(NES);//allow other chips I guess?

//dynamic components section
 solder h to connect CIRAM_A10 to PPU_A[10];
 solder v to connect CIRAM_A10 to PPU_A[11]; 
 init h iNES.6[0];
 init v ~iNES.6[0];
  //technically redundant per wiki as only V-using boards had solder pads?
  //make "to" as whitespace, allowing nice codelook but not requiring 
 connect CIRAM_CE_n to PPU_A13_n;

//connections: power
 connect VCC prg.vcc cic.vcc chr.vcc;
 connect GND prg.gnd cic.gnd chr.gnd;
  //allow multiple connections per statement
  //considering a shortform lke "=" for connect
//connections: CIC 
 //[omitted]
//connections: PRG
 connect prg.a[14:0] CPU_A[14:0];
 //NROM_128: connect prg.a[13:0] CPU_A[13:0];
 //and connect prg.a[14] VCC; //several ways to do it, really.
 connect prg.d[7:0] CPU_D[7:0];
 connect prg.oe_n prg.ce_n ROMSEL_n; //I suspect I've got these mildly wrong
//connections: CHR
 connect chr.a[12:0] PPU_A[12:0];
 connect chr.d[7:0] PPU_D[7:0];
 connect chr.oe_n chr.ce_n PPU_A[13];

end NROM_256V;

User talk:Hamtaro126

H126-ROM1 and H126-RAM1 mapper format (for next letter of ZZO38's Mapperset)

This mapper will be a DIY thing, I will not make carts, But it is possible to make them!

Based off a combo of UxROM and MMC3

PPU (H126-ROM1):

$0000-$03FF: 4k CHR bank 1 (uses $40C0)
$0400-$07FF: 4k CHR bank 2 (uses $40C1)
$0800-$0BFF: 4k CHR bank 3 (uses $40C2)
$0C00-$0FFF: 4k CHR bank 4 (uses $40C3)
$1000-$13FF: 4k CHR bank 5 (uses $40C4)
$1400-$17FF: 4k CHR bank 6 (uses $40C5)
$1800-$1BFF: 4k CHR bank 7 (uses $40C6)
$1C00-$1FFF: 4k CHR bank 8 (uses $40C7)

PPU (H126-RAM1):

$0000-$1FFF - 8k CHR RAM ($40C0-$40C7 are unused!)

RAM:

$5000-$5FFF: 2k WRAM (optional)
$6000-$7FFF: 8k SaveRAM or WRAM

ROM:

$8000-$9FFF: 8k ROM bank 1 (uses $40C8)
$A000-$BFFF: 8k ROM bank 2 (uses $40C9)
$C000-$DFFF: 8k ROM bank 3 (uses $40CA)
$E000-$FFFF: 8k ROM bank 4 (Fixed)

PPU Mirror:

$40CB: Mirroring (0 = 1-Screen $2000, 1 = 1-Screen $2400, 2 = Horizontal, 3 = Vertical)

IRQ (optional):

$40CC: Control Disable
$40CD: Control Enable
$40CE: Cycle IRQ Counter Value (MMC5 style)

This is a WIP, May Change!!! --Hamtaro126 (talk) 08:10, 29 June 2013 (MDT)

Discussion

I suggest to use $40C8, $40C9, $40CA for the PRG ROM bank select, and having $40CB unused. I think this would be more logical and probably simpler to build. --Zzo38 (talk) 12:10, 29 June 2013 (MDT)

EDIT1: Adjustments are Made, Tell me more, --Hamtaro126 (talk) 23:59, 29 June 2013 (MDT)

This is very similar to Taito's X1-017 or TC0350. —Lidnariq (talk) 13:12, 29 June 2013 (MDT)

NOTE1: I actually based the format off of complex mappers like Sunsoft and Taito's, But wanted the user to choose what options needed for their game, But this mapper is not too complex, It is designed for a variable sized package for cheapness, And the reason that MMC5-style instead of MMC3 IRQs are used because of ease of use! --Hamtaro126 (talk) 08:32, 30 June 2013 (MDT)

I'd call this the logical evolution of the TC0350. You've increased it to 8x1 CHR banking instead of 2x2+4x1, moved the control registers, changed it to a scanline instead of cycle-counting IRQ, and increased the amount of memory. Note that 2KiB RAMs aren't really available anymore; if you're going to specify a form with more than 8KiB of flat RAM, you may as well specify all of it to be and put 16320 bytes of RAM from $4040-$7FFF instead. (Or, keep an eye to implementation, and allocate 512*31 bytes from $4200-$7FFF from an iCE40 FPGA). Also, even thought people thought banking CHR RAM to be odd for Lagrange Point, on the balance it's useful. I wouldn't prohibit it a priori. (Also, is "4k" a typo?) —Lidnariq (talk) 19:34, 30 June 2013 (MDT)

You said you have no intention to build this cartridge, which might be OK, but you should at least have some idea of how to build such a cartridge (using discrete logic, Verilog, whatever). --Zzo38 (talk) 15:13, 4 July 2013 (MDT)

I actually planned to learn all that, But the problem is I never actually wanted to until I learn to create better stuff, I have lots that are unfinished, Some that are study cases (mostly SMBDIS hacks), Some are actual works studying the PPU and ROM hacking, So I cannot do anything until I am done with my actual experience, actually LEARNING, and try to release actual stuff before doing this, I am sorry...

Should I leave this info here, or should I erase it until then? --Hamtaro126 (talk) 15:39, 4 July 2013 (MDT)

Hamtaro126's Code/Macro Examples (WIP)

See the page on implenting a Macro for Multibyte Constant (specifically my ASM6 example) for my first macro submitted on this wiki, using the HEX command for ASM6

Macros:

;Easy Super Mario Bros. 3 TileMap Macro (16x16 Metatiles, 8x8 Split Tiles)
;ASM6 version
;By Hamtaro126, With thanks to Southbird for disassembling Super Mario Bros. 3
;Can also be used for Homebrew!!!
; 
;Example: SMB3Tile, $8000, $01, $23, $45, $67
;this splits these tiles into 256-byte SECTIONS at $8000, $8100, $8200, and $8300... have fun

.macro SMB3Tile address, t1, t2, t3, t4
  .org address
  .db t1
  .org address+$0100
  .db t2
  .org address+$0200
  .db t3
  .org address+$0300
  .db t4
.endm

Routines:

;Straight from Super Mario World (SNES), but usable for NES now!
;BRA is changed to JMP for usability in any 6502 processor

;This code is useable since it is just generic code!

HexToDec:
	LDX #$00
SetTens:
	CMP #$0A
	BCC ExitHToDRt
	SBC #$0A
	INX
	JMP SetTens
ExitHToDRt:
	RTS

User talk:Lidnariq

Leaving anonymous edits open

In this revert, you asked: "Are we sure about leaving anonymous edits open?"

Look how quickly and easily it was reverted, and it didn't need an administrator's help. After you noticed vandalism, it took you three clicks to remove it: diff, undo, save. Then compare to how much work an administrator needed to do to get someone's account set up properly under the trusted/role account system. Also notice the lack of a working link to the vandal's web site because the editor couldn't solve the NES trivia question that the wiki presents to someone new who adds an external link. --Tepples 22:09, 12 October 2012 (MDT)

Thank you for your help in fighting vandalism. But I've noticed a peculiar sentiment in the edit summaries for your reverts. Without anonymous edits, how would you recommend contacting someone in case of problems creating an account on or logging in to the forum or wiki? --Tepples (talk) 14:36, 19 February 2013 (MST)

What if anonymous edits were allowed on one special talk page in particular? Users who are not logged in could be redirected there or given a link to it automatically if they try to make an edit. The entire wiki-talk doesn't need to be an emergency messageboard. To me, reverting the vandalism is less of a problem I think than just how the vandalism+revert pollute the recent changes list. Revering the changes is the problem of one person who finds it, but everyone who reads the RC has to read/parse this stuff. (Putting it all on a single page wouldn't help RC much though, but might make it easier to parse/ignore.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 00:29, 20 February 2013 (MST)

Administrators and users with 500 or more edits can mark RC entries as "bot" so that they're hidden from the default view of Recent Changes. My practice here has been to hide spam, reverts, and other administrivia after two other users have made edits. The reason I left talk namespaces open is so that people could report problems with the content of pages. --Tepples (talk) 08:33, 20 February 2013 (MST)

Ah, so in about 20 more edits, I'll be able to botify spam edits? Well, that'll be good. - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:22, 20 February 2013 (MST)

At least for me, people have been contacting me by PM on the forum in preference to anonymous edits in the wiki. However, I would stop complaining if a two-click-and-no-scrolling "get rid of it from the page and the changelog" option were available. But now the work flow is "click on diff, click on undo, scroll to bottom, click submit, go to S:RCC, click to hide my undo (which reloads the page rather than using AJAX to just change the field!), click to hide their edit", and that's just obnoxious. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:23, 21 February 2013 (MST)

I'll see what I can do about making a rollback group. But you'll need to be careful with it, as bumping the rollback button on my own wiki has caused me to accidentally revert good edits. --Tepples (talk) 17:41, 21 February 2013 (MST)

User talk:Ndwiki

If your intent is to transfer the contents of the old wiki to this one, it would be much simpler to Export all of the pages from the old wiki (revision histories included) to an XML file, then Import it here. --Quietust 15:47, 11 June 2009 (UTC)

Ho... I was not aware of this option. Thanks for the comment. I have imported by hand the most common page already so I don't know how much it would clash if I do an import now. hmm.. How much value is the history of the old one, this is more the question now.

You may find this page to be of significant convenience. Especially take note of the "Namespace" dropdown. --Quietust 03:54, 13 June 2009 (UTC)

Thanks for the comment. I have been checking all the special page one by one yesterday to see which one were relevant. Now I will just use the export option for the few pages left. They are mostly pages that will be re-located in the "getting started" section (tutorial etc). I don't know much about wiki editing so I still have a lot to learn but hey, at least we have content now :)

By the way, your emulator is great. Continue the good work. If you could add shortcuts for the key in the debugging mode like visual studio, that would be quite useful! --Banshaku 04:07, 13 June 2009 (UTC)

User CSS

I'm away from the computer with ndwiki's password. Can someone turn on user CSS in LocalSettings.php so that I can test site styles before I su to deploy them? If not, I will in a few hours.

$wgAllowUserCss = true;

--Tepples 14:20, 2 April 2010 (UTC)

Done. It took me a while to get used to koitsu's FreeBSD installation: it lacks nano, and its vim lacks the insert-mode key bindings that another popular Free operating system has. --Tepples 21:16, 2 April 2010 (UTC)

User talk:Zzo38/DotFami

Contents

1 ROM size
2 CPU mode
3 VRC7 Audio
4 Shortkana
5 VT/OneBus Series Emulation Support
6 Nova's Mapper
7 Trainer

ROM size

I saw this in Recent Changes, and it looks like you left only 8 bits for "bnk: Number of 8K ROM banks." Action 52 and Chinese Final Fantasy VII already don't fit, having 2048 KiB (256 banks) each. --Tepples 18:30, 3 August 2012 (PDT)

And that is one reason why it is a draft (the other reason being that it is not complete). Thanks for telling me. Is 256 the maximum? (If so, the "bnk" can be one less than the number of 8K banks; if not, it can be expanded to a sixteen bit number of banks.) Other things that could be fixed is the "cpu" field for CPU flags; it could be entirely rewritten or expanded to sixteen bits whatever seems important; if you have ideas you can post. --Zzo38 20:35, 3 August 2012 (PDT)

By now, I'd probably just use a 32-bit integer for the number of bytes and be done with it. If I really wanted to pack it into 8 bits, I'd use a IEE754-like quarter-precision structure with a 2-or-3 bit significand and a 5-or-6 bit unsigned and non-offset exponent. Almost all—but not quite—NES roms use powers of two, and while the vast majority of things cataloged as not a power of two are complete garbage, there are a few that would require awkward padding without it. Of course, not having a power of two of data is already a strange concept, since at its most basic address lines are binary. (To answer your question: there are already 3 and 4MB PRG dumps known) --Lidnariq 01:15, 4 August 2012 (PDT)

Thanks for information. (However note that this format is not only for existing ROM dumps but also for homebrew games; some of which might use their own mappers as long as their components do not differ too much from the existing ones.) Perhaps I should just make the "bnk" field to indicate the number of address lines like you suggested so it is 2 to the power of the number 0 to 255 as number of bytes (obviously this can result in extremely larger than anyone will ever need). Another possibility is to use sixteen bits for a number of banks (of some size); see what is preferred. CPU flag (not only for CPU, actually) could also be fixed, expanded to 16 bits if necessary, including also such things as the PPU differences that are switched in some VS Unisystem games and that the intensity bits have a different meaning in some systems. --Zzo38 10:41, 4 August 2012 (PDT)

Plenty of NES games don't use a power of 2. Particularly games that use CHR ROM will often be 3 or 5 times a power of 2, and there's one game that's 136 KiB (Morita Shogi: SNROM, 128 KiB PRG ROM, 8 KiB CHR ROM). --Tepples 10:55, 4 August 2012 (PDT)

And here I was misreading your "number of 8kB blocks" meaning for each PRG and CHR. Yeah, the total size is usually going to be 2ⁱ+2ⁿ; the exceptions I was mentioning above were ones where the size of PRG wasn't a power of two. --Lidnariq 11:17, 4 August 2012 (PDT)

OK. Thank you. I could expand this field to sixteen bits, and then decide what to do with it (perhaps can be total number of 8K ROM banks, unless you have better idea). --Zzo38 11:50, 4 August 2012 (PDT)

CPU mode

What's your objective in supporting nonstandard clock frequencies? AFAIK, none of the famiclones support under- or over- clocking their NES-equivalents, so breaking hardware compatibility seems odd to me. --Lidnariq 11:17, 4 August 2012 (PDT)

OK, so there are none, I suppose there is no use, I can remove that. Thanks for notifying me; I think there is still more to fix about the CPU flags though (things to add, things to remove, things to change). --Zzo38 11:50, 4 August 2012 (PDT)

VRC7 Audio

The VRC7 only existed in one hardware instantiation, with 6 channels and an admittedly unknown but nonetheless fixed group of built-in instruments; allowing these to be configured by the ROM image specifically allows the description of things that don't exist in reality. (And if you want that, you may as well define a cartridge with a full OPL2; and if you want that, you may as well use some random FM tracker.)

I'm not actually clear where any of the mapper audio bits are referred to, come to think of it. They make it seem like this format is trying to be a replacement for both .NSF and .NES at the same time.

In general, the mapper audio needs to be tightly coupled to the mapper hardware described anyway, otherwise there's no way to play it; it feels odd to call it out separately. --Lidnariq 19:12, 5 August 2012 (PDT)

I do not intend to include full OPL2 and all that stuff; I don't want too many things which are not used in existing Famicom cartridges (although some simple things might be added on, if they are both easy to emulate and easy to build hardware). I removed the number of channels, but you could change the instrument setting since "VRC7 built-in instruments are not the same as OPLL instruments" so obviously if you change the hardware then you can change the music (especially since register layout is the same anyways; so you could use OPLL but just not use the rhythm channels). For where it is mentioned: "Note that you can have multiple instances of each and that their parameters can differ as well as how the address lines are connected by using other mapper codes." The mapper codes that will tell them to be connected simply is not yet described in this document (but eventually will be). But still it is draft so things are added, removed, and changed, in order to make improvement. --Zzo38 03:40, 6 August 2012 (PDT)

If you want to allow the existence of the OPLL, which also has another different unique set of predefined instruments, you should probably define it as another mapper, or a variant of the VRC7 mapper. By putting the full instrument definitions as bundled-with but not configurable-by the ROM image, you both prevent an emulator from providing the most accurate emulation because the included numbers were (by some definition) wrong, and if the numbers don't strictly correspond to either OPLL or the VRC7 you now also describe something that cannot exist in hardware. (I am defining FPGAs as "software emulation") --Lidnariq 11:54, 6 August 2012 (PDT)

Shortkana

Please just use UTF8 (or UCS2,UTF16,UCS4, whatever). We do NOT need Yet Another encoding for printable characters—especially one based on something as hostile as CP437/CP850. --Lidnariq 14:45, 14 August 2012 (PDT)

This may be considered. Thanks for your suggestion. However: Why do you hate CP437? I happen to like CP437. I don't like Unicode that much. Translating a UTF-8 stream into numbers is not too difficult, although it still uses varying length and actually displaying Unicode text becomes much more difficult. Have you read about difficulty some people were having to make hardware .NSF player to display Unicode text? (not that DotFami is likely to be directly interpreted by hardware; it would be converted into the needed hardware format such as VHDL or whatever if you wanted to use DotFami with hardware) So possibly since .NSF can be, it is a possibility to use with .NSF for hardware .NSF players as well. CHR ROM could be implemented using this format not too difficult, you have 34 extra spaces too. --Zzo38 17:19, 14 August 2012 (PDT)

CP437's completely inadequate for anything other than English text (wikipedia:Code_page_437#Internationalization). By using it as a starting point, and obliterating what might be CP850 characters with kana, you restrict the range of options to just US, UK and Japanese musicians. Plus, it's about equally correct to present (e.g.) Uematsu in romaji or kana; either way his name is actually 植松 伸夫. --Lidnariq 21:44, 14 August 2012 (PDT)

VT/OneBus Series Emulation Support

I would love to see OneBus console support (VT02, VT03, etc), I may create a page on it for this reason. Ca4h3e had made a incomplete UNIF mapper for FCEUMM.

I will post the link once it is done... --Hamtaro126 05:49, 15 August 2012 (PDT)

I don't know what that means, but yes do post it especially if there is some relation to DotFami or some way they can help each other. --Zzo38 13:14, 15 August 2012 (PDT)

It is essentialy an enhanced NES with double the APU (if 2 APUs are used) and added 4BPP graphics, as well as DMA. But it is not very well emulated or documented, because the emulator is a modded NESTER, and it seems closed.

It uses $2008-201F, as well as $4018-$402F? More details will tell if it is more than that...

The Document (WIP, in rewrite mode.) is originally in 2 types of Chinese, as well as Engrish (English with lots of Translation Errors) But I understand it enough to rewrite it.

I am still working on it, and will post it when the time comes! --Hamtaro126 22:39, 16 August 2012 (PDT)

Nova's Mapper

I read about Nova's Mapper on the Pin Eight wiki. Perhaps it may be possible to implement using DotFami's .cart files? (But first needs completing more of the DotFami specification) --Zzo38 13:41, 24 August 2012 (MDT)

That design looks interesting, but it needs a lot of cleaning up. First of all, the register layout could use a complete rework, and I'll run this by Nova this weekend. Second, there appear to be two binary adders in the chain from PPU A12-A8 to CHR A15-A8; would that pose a delay problem in CPLD implementation? --Tepples 20:13, 24 August 2012 (MDT)
I've rewritten it from the ground up, and he liked it. But he told me that MMC3 with a 32 KiB CHR RAM provides most of the same benefits while being already possible with NES 2.0 or with very minor changes to existing boards. --Tepples 09:53, 26 August 2012 (MDT)

Trainer

Here is an idea of loading trainer data which I think is compliant with both iNES and DotFami:

If battery RAM file exists, keep its contents.
If trainer exists, write trainer into $7000-$71FF the same as the CPU would write there. Ignore any IRQ triggered while doing so.
If battery RAM file exists, load battery RAM chip(s) with battery RAM data (directly, not through the CPU). (This may overwrite the trainer.)
If CPU ever subsequently tries to read from $7000-$71FF and gets open bus, return the trainer data instead, if there is one.

--Zzo38 15:05, 29 September 2012 (MDT)

User talk:Zzo38/Mapper D

Common init code

I like your idea to make an MMC5 subset: it's more or less UNROM with banked PRG RAM but can be tested in any emulator with rudimentary support for MMC5 and NES 2.0. You may want to add two things: a canonical set of init code to get the MMC5 into a state where it acts like this mapper, and a caveat about writes to the RAM mirror at $1000-$1FFF. --Tepples (talk) 08:32, 11 August 2013 (MDT)

Thank you; I think you are correct, and I will add this information. (I did, in fact, create it specifically because emulators do not support the mappers that I just made up by myself!) (Also, if you don't need more than 64K RAM, then you don't need an emulator supporting NES 2.0, either.) --Zzo38 (talk) 09:47, 11 August 2013 (MDT)

If it's marked as MMC5, the NES 2.0 header is needed to get the emulator to provide more than 8K of memory in the first place. And do you intend to hardwire 8 KiB of CHR ROM/RAM, or do you intend to make it respond to $5xxB as if it were CNROM? --Tepples (talk) 15:19, 11 August 2013 (MDT)

Hardwire 8K CHR ROM or CHR RAM. (Also, when I read it, it seems to me that it means the default amount of PRG RAM for MMC5 is 64K, isn't it? It is 8K for most mappers but for some the default amount is supposed to even be zero? Disch's notes specify the default amount of PRG RAM for MMC5 is 64K because existing games do not depend on the mirrors of the RAM, I think.) --Zzo38 (talk) 15:49, 11 August 2013 (MDT)

Hardware required

74'138, wired to select M2=high, R/W=low, A13=low, A12=high, and A4=address input

There is one spare input, which is probably most usefully connected to A14=high.

6 bit latch for ROM banking, such as 74'174
3 bit latch for RAM banking, such as 74'161
1 or 2 74'32s, for 256KiB PRG ROM or more, respectively

—Lidnariq (talk) 19:21, 4 January 2014 (MST)

User talk:Zzo38/Mapper H

Status

This can't be fully finished yet... the following things don't make sense:

Why PPU A8…A11 == b'0000'? That's the first sixteen patterns in the both pattern tables and the top eight rows of the top-left-most nametable.
Why latch PPU A8 and A9 when PPU A8…A11 already == b'0000' ?
Why latch PPU A12 and A13? They're rather difficult to control in a useful fashion.

—Lidnariq (talk) 23:15, 13 September 2014 (MDT)

That first one is a mistake; it should be only A10 and A11. Thank you for notifying me. --Zzo38 (talk) 20:32, 18 September 2014 (MDT)

That doesn't really help. Let's try a simple cycle-by-cycle description of what's going on. Assuming for the moment that scrollX=scrollY=0, and MODE=SCROLL=COLOR=0 at the very start.

Fetch $2000, data=VV ; MODE←$80 ; COLOR←V&3
Fetch $23C0, data=COLOR*85 ; MODE←$BC
Fetch $0VV0, data=PP ; actual fetch comes from ROM at $16VV4 ; SCROLL←0 ; COLOR←P&3
Fetch $0VV8, data=QQ ; actual fetch comes from ROM at $16VVC ; SCROLL←0 ; COLOR←Q&3
Fetch $2001, data=WW ; MODE←$80 ; COLOR←W&3
Fetch $23C0, data=COLOR*85 ; MODE←$BC
Fetch $0WW0, data=RR ; actual fetch comes from ROM at $16WW4; SCROLL←0 ; COLOR←R&3

So that pretty clearly shows that since the attribute table fetches interfere with MODE, we can't usefully control MODE when PPU A13 = 1. The value will ALWAYS be between $BC and $BF, producing normal display for the top 64 scanlines, and weird aliasing for the following 176. Furthermore, there is thus NO way to get values from $80 through $BB or $C0 through $FF.

What if we prevented attribute table fetches from updating MODE? It's both a little better and a bit worse. There's still no way to select values from $C0 through $FF, because the PPU normal fetch order never fetches from $3xxx. On the other hand, every scanline will flip between MODE&0xFE and MODE|1, left and right: fairly hard to compensate for. AND to no real benefit.

So let's set scrollX=256 and scrollY=240, so that MODE is only ever updated during the pattern table fetches.

For brevity's sake, ignore fetches from $2C00 and $2FC0, it only affects COLOR
Fetch $0VV0. If VV<64, then set MODE=VV ... Wait, why didn't we just latch VV on the nametable fetch in the first place ? Also, COLOR = VV&3 = which also = MODE&3. If the user flipped between left and right pattern tables, flipping PPU A12, flipping SCROLL D6, that effectively ties CHR A12 to CHR A15: the only way to fetch tiles where CHR A12 != CHR A15 is by raster effects, changing the tables mid-screen, after MODE is set.

This is entirely ignoring the dummy nametable fetches during sprite fetch. Those will clobber MODE, although it should usually be 0. It does keep the user from using a quarter of the sprite tables, because the values fetched will cause weird internal scrolling.

Here's something that will provides the same meat, but is far more predictable:

On nametable (but not attribute table) fetches, latch the two LSB of the byte fetched. That's COLOR.
On nametable (but not attribute table) fetches, IF the MSB is CLEAR, latch the remaining five bits. That's MODE.
CHR-ROM is not connected to PPU A11. i.e. both $45 and $C5 fetch the same tile: the former just has a side effect.
The four LSB of MODE and SCROLL have the same effect as before.
The MSB and final bit of MODE selects between 8 KiB banks of CHR. There just aren't enough variables to provide any more.

—Lidnariq (talk) 23:58, 19 September 2014 (MDT)

Thank you, although my intention was that you would not use the $2000-$23FF nametable at all, and that it would include tiles to switch the mode, at the beginning of each row and possibly also later in the row. Thank you for writing all of this stuff anyways though (maybe it can still help)! --Zzo38 (talk) 20:28, 20 September 2014 (MDT)

User talk:Zzo38/Submappers

There's a bunch here that seem unnecessary to me. For example:

Mapper 1, all of these boards are disambiguated just with the PRG-RAM size register, so why allocate submappers?

That said, SEROM and SHROM are not describable using other details, so there's an argument for why they should.

Mappers 2,3 submappers should probably also apply to 7 and 34
Mapper 4 MMC3 vs MMC6 can also be disambiguated using the PRG-RAM size register
I'm not clear why any of the VRC2x/VRC4x/VRC7x layouts need to be disambiguated.

That said, using submappers to disambiguate VRC2 from VRC4 is a great idea.

Mappers 38,79: I think enshrining either behavior as official is a bad idea, especially since Nestopia's implementation is a superset of FCEUX's in both cases. (And FCEUX happens to be on crack with m79's register at $8000)

—Lidnariq 20:13, 10 September 2012 (MDT)

Thanks for your comments. OK, I have listed 7 and 34 under the 2 and 3 heading. For mapper 38 and 79 I have added a comment; hopefully someone who understands better will fix it. I don't know much about the differences of SEROM, SHROM, SOROM, SXROM, SUROM, but at least to me it would make sense that the same mapper/submapper number is used if and only if it makes sense that it is otherwise similar enough other than the PRG-RAM size! For VRC7a/VRC7b, I quote: "VRC7a uses $x010 for regs, and VRC7b uses $x008." I suppose it could be mirrored but doesn't make sense from a hardware perspective (unless, perhaps, you use a OR gate on bit3 and bit4 of the address; which seems strange to me, though). As I have written above, the reason I think MMC3 and MMC6 different numbers, and I quote again: "It is also mapped a bit differently, and is enabled/disabled differently from MMC3." For the VRC4x, registers are mapped differently. Some of these reasons are in case you want to write a homebrew using these mappers with different ROM/RAM amounts (of course, the RAM amounts should always be zero if the mapper does not specify any registers to control it, and in some cases there are simple changes to the registers just using different number of bits so they shouldn't have a different number, but in some cases they really are different other than just the ROM/RAM amounts). At least this is my opinion. You can ask other people working on NES/Famicom to see if they know better; I don't know it that well, and as I wrote in the document, these are only suggestion (subject to change) and not official specifications in any way (this is why it is a subpage of my userpage instead of main namespace). --Zzo38 22:56, 10 September 2012 (MDT)

Uh, that's a big pile of stuff, so I'm going to break them out again:

I should have added mapper 66 (GNROM) to the list of discrete mappers that have/don't have bus conflicts along with UxROM, CNROM, AxROM, BNROM.
The best description of the MMC1 variants I can think of is either at SxROM or at MMC1 pinout. At least SOROM, SXROM, and SUROM are exactly described by the preexisting fields of the NES2.0 header: SOROM necessarily has 16KiB PRG RAM, ≤8KiB CHR RAM+ROM. SUROM always has ≤8KiB PRG RAM, ≤8KiB CHR RAM+ROM, 512KiB PRG ROM. SXROM always has 32KiB PRG RAM, ≤8KiB CHR RAM+ROM. On the other hand, SEROM, SHROM, and SH1ROM always have 32KiB PRG ROM, but so does SIROM, and only the last doesn't entire ignore the MMC1's PRG banking abilities.
The VRC2x/VRC4x/VRC7x collapse is handled is emulator sources I've read exactly as you say: the registers are (e.g.) (address&0x42). An emulator that required NES2.0 would be able to be clearer, but given that there are 5 different layouts for VRC4 it wouldn't actually make the code any simpler. (As an academic exercise, it would be interesting to make a ROM that autodetected which variant of VRC4 it was running on)... I think I've talked myself out of objecting to these.
0 or 8KiB PRG RAM → MMC3. 1 KiB PRG RAM → MMC6, and the behavior of the protection register would follow from that. Furthermore, since 1024x8 RAMs are at best ancient, saying "1 KiB RAM implies MMC6 behavior, 0,2ⁿ (n=7,8,9,11,12,13) imply MMC3 behavior, ≥16384 is an error" is unambiguous and seems cleaner to me.

The counterargument would invoke the X1-017 IC, since its internal memory (5KiB) isn't directly expressible in NES2.0.

—Lidnariq 01:25, 11 September 2012 (MDT)

I can't tell from INES Mapper 082 exactly how the X1-017 is supposed to map its battery-backed memory ("$7000-$6FFF"?), but I'd guess that non-power-of-two memory sizes would round up the same way they do in the Super NES internal header. --Tepples 06:52, 11 September 2012 (MDT)

User:Zzo38/6502 programming tricks

Contents

1 Toggle the zero flag
2 Rotate accumulator left 8-bits
3 Signed compare
4 Tail recursion
5 Fall-through tail recursion
6 Compressed data in CHR ROM
7 Storing high byte and low byte of an address in separate tables
8 Dealing with carry flag
9 Clear accumulator and carry flag and reset bank
10 Self-modifying codes
11 See also

Toggle the zero flag

PHP
PLA
AND #2

Bytes: 4
Cycles: 9

Main-effect:

Zero flag: toggled.

Side-effect:

Accumulator: set to 0 or 2.
Negative flag: cleared.

Rotate accumulator left 8-bits

ASL A
ADC #0

Bytes: 3
Cycles: 4

Main-effect:

Accumulator: shifted left, with shifted-out bit shifted-in.

Side-effect:

Carry flag: cleared.

Signed compare

One way to do this is by toggling the high bit of both numbers before comparison. For example, if 8-bit numbers:

EOR #$80

Tail recursion

Bytes: -1
Cycles: -9

This can be done by replacing a JSR/RTS with just a JMP, since the subroutine it jumps to will have its own RTS.

Fall-through tail recursion

Bytes: -4
Cycles: -12

Instead of jumping to another subroutine, you can just fall-through into it. In fact you can even JSR to it and then fall through to it (possibly doing something else in between if wanted), if you want to run it twice; Super Mario Bros. uses this pattern.

Note: This should be done itself inside of a subroutine which finally does the same effect as another, so it still needs to be called.

Compressed data in CHR ROM

Compressed level data may be stored in CHR ROM, rather than PRG ROM, if it helps. One thing that can help is the automatic address increment in the PPU, and faster addressing modes. The data can start at an arbitrary address without much difficulty.

Storing high byte and low byte of an address in separate tables

For the RTS trick and other things, you can use separate 256 byte pages for different pieces of a record, such as low and high half of an address.

Here is an example of a macro for use with Unofficial MagicKit which will automatically do this for you (here, it is called player_tile, and uses the tables pmrttl and pmrtth; you can, in fact, use exactly this macro and just change the names around):

	macro player_tile
	if ?X=1
	macset 2,4,*
	macset 3,4,?B
	bank 3
	org pmrttl+(\1)
	db low((\2)-1)
	org pmrtth+(\1)
	db high((\2)-1)
	bank \3
	org \2
	endif
	endm

Dealing with carry flag

Several things can be done with the carry flag, such as:

If you want to use a AND instruction and clear the carry flag at the same time, you can use the unofficial ANC instruction, if the high bit of the operand is cleared.
Often you can tell that the carry flag will have a specific state (such as after a conditional branch), which can help when using a ADC or SBC instruction.

Clear accumulator and carry flag and reset bank

CLC
RLA ident

Bytes: 4
Cycles: 8

In this program, "ident" should point to a zero byte in ROM. The "official" way would be:

CLC
LDA #0
STA ident

Bytes: 6
Cycles: 8

Self-modifying codes

See also

RTS Trick
Synthetic instructions
Programming with unofficial opcodes

User:Zzo38/DotFami

This is a draft for .fami format of NES/Famicom ROM image files. This format allows title text, debugging information, custom mapper, and a few more.

(N.B. Do not delete or move this file until the draft is completed.)

Difference of this format with others includes:

You can specify NTSC and PAL.
Can include descriptive text.
There is no fixed set of mapper numbers; instead the components of the cartridge are configured individually.
Debugging symbols can be included.

Contents

1 File Order
2 Header
3 Mapper Codes

3.1 ($00) Add non-audio component
3.2 ($01) Add audio component
3.3 ($04) Connection of components to components
3.4 ($05) Connection of components to cartridge pins
3.5 ($06) Connection of cartridge to cartridge
3.6 ($FD) External condition
3.7 ($FE) External parameter
3.8 ($FF) External selector

4 Symbol Data
5 Mapper Components

5.1 ($00) ROM
5.2 ($01) RAM
5.3 ($02) Logic gates
5.4 ($03) Multiplication
5.5 ($04) Shift register
5.6 ($05) Flip-flops
5.7 ($06) Multiplexer
5.8 ($07) Diskette drive
5.9 ($08) File loading interface
5.10 ($09) Bandai EEPROM
5.11 ($0A) Expansion terminal
5.12 ($0B) Counter
5.13 ($0C) System reset initializer
5.14 ($0D) Addressable register

6 Mapper Audio

6.1 ($00) Extra 2A03 audio
6.2 ($01) Famicom Disk System audio
6.3 ($02) VRC6 audio
6.4 ($03) VRC7 audio
6.5 ($04) MMC5 audio
6.6 ($05) Sunsoft audio
6.7 ($06) Namco audio
6.8 ($07) JF-13 audio
6.9 ($08) Digital to analog converter

7 ASCII/shortkana Table
8 Other File Formats

8.1 .rom
8.2 .cart
8.3 .symb
8.4 ines.map
8.5 unif.map
8.6 .native

9 Supported programs

9.1 Emulators (compile time)
9.2 Emulators (run time)
9.3 Hardware programmers
9.4 Assemblers/compilers
9.5 Hardware description language
9.6 Miscellaneous

File Order

Header
ROM data
Mapper codes
Symbol data
Descriptive text

(Note: Sixteen bit numbers throughout the file are small-endian form.)

Header

  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7   8   9   A   B   C   D   E   F
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|'F'|'A'|'M'|'I'|cpu| * | banks |textLen|mapLen |symLen | * | * |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+

The first four bytes of the header must be the ASCII codes for "FAMI".
banks: Number 8K ROM banks.
cpu: CPU mode flag:

bit0: Set if decimal mode should work (not used in NES/Famicom, although some Famiclones may have decimal mode).
bit1: Set if the 2A03 APU noise Mode flag should be ignored.
bit2: Swap PPUCTRL and PPUMASK (used in some Vs. System games).
bit3: RGB PPU (tint bits maximize intensity, and some other differences).
bit4: Buggy Famiclone audio (switched bit7/bit6 or duty 1 and 2 are switched).
bit5: Can be used with Dendy TV mode.
bit6: Can be used with PAL TV mode.
bit7: Can be used with NTSC TV mode.

*: Reserved bytes; set to zero.
textLen: Length of descriptive text.
mapLen: Length of mapper codes.
symLen: Length of symbol data.

Note for TV modes: It can set multiple bits to indicate if it is OK with multiple TV modes. If none of these bits are set, it means to use NTSC timing, but use RGB palettes, no NTSC color artifacts, square pixels, and the entire 256x240 screen to be visible.

Note: It is recommended that the user be able to change all the settings listed in the CPU mode flag.

Mapper Codes

Each mapper command consists of a length byte, followed by a command code, an ID number, and the parameters which have the length indicated by the length byte (the first byte of parameters is called parameter $00, etc).

($00) Add non-audio component

ID number: ID of added component (must be unique for each component; non-audio and audio components additionally may not share ID numbers with themselves or each other).
Parameter $00: Type of component to add.
Parameter $01...: Parameters of component (depends on type of component).

($01) Add audio component

ID number: ID of added component (must be unique for each component; non-audio and audio components additionally may not share ID numbers with themselves or each other).
Parameter $00: Type of component to add.
Parameter $01: Volume from 0 to 64.
Parameter $02: Panning from 0 (left) to 64 (right), or 100 for surround. This parameter can be safely ignored by emulators and hardware.
Parameter $03...: Parameters of component (depends on type of component).

($04) Connection of components to components

ID number: ID of first component.
Parameter $00: ID of second component.
Parameter $01: Low 4 bits = impedance (0=direct, 15=high). High 4 bits = propagation delay (0=not applicable).
Parameter $02: Pin of first component.
Parameter $03: Pin of second component.
Parameter $04...: Repeat of parameters $02 and $03 for each connection.

($05) Connection of components to cartridge pins

ID number: ID of component.
Parameter $00: Reserved for future use; please set to zero.
Parameter $01: Low 4 bits = impedance (0=direct, 15=high). High 4 bits = propagation delay (0=not applicable).
Parameter $02: Pin of component.
Parameter $03: Pin of cartridge.
Parameter $04...: Repeat of parameters $02 and $03 for each connection.

The pin numbers are the same as the 60-pin Famicom cartridge, except that pins 16, 31, 45, and 46 are not used.

($06) Connection of cartridge to cartridge

ID number: Reserved for future use; please set to zero.
Parameter $00: Reserved for future use; please set to zero.
Parameter $01: Low 4 bits = impedance (0=direct, 15=high). High 4 bits = propagation delay (0=not applicable).
Parameter $02: First pin.
Parameter $03: Second pin.
Parameter $04...: Repeat of parameters $02 and $03 for each connection.

($FD) External condition

This command should only appear in a .cart file; not in a .fami file. The ID number is the ID number of an external parameter, parameter $00 is the number of commands in a block, and the rest are values which, if the external parameter has any of them the commands in the block will be used, and if they don't have them then the commands in the block will be ignored.

($FE) External parameter

This command should only appear in a .cart file; not in a .fami file. The ID number is the ID number of an external parameter, and the rest are numbers of parameter slots of the next command which should be XORed by the external parameter value.

For example:

01 FE 00 03
04 01 00 05 40 20 00

This adds a Sunsoft audio but the clock speed is configured from external parameter number zero.

($FF) External selector

This command should only appear in a .cart file; not in a .fami file. The ID number is the ID number of an external parameter, and the rest are numbers of commands in the corresponding block (parameter $00 for block zero, parameter $01 for block one, etc). Whatever the value of the external parameter is, that is the only following block which will be used; the other blocks mentioned will be ignored. (If the value specifies a block which there are not enough parameters to specify length of a used block, the length is treated as zero.)

Symbol Data

Symbol data consists of zero or more blocks consisting of a 16-bit ID followed by a 16-bit address followed by data. (If the mode is 0, 1, or 2, then the address must be an address within the ROM, mapper component, or CPU memory, and the data is an ASCII text giving its name).

The ID is formed as follows:

bit0-bit5: Length of data (0 to 63 bytes).
bit6-bit7: Mode (0=ROM, 1=mapper, 2=CPU memory, 3=extra)
bit8-bit15: Depend on mode as follows:

0: High bits of address.
1: Component ID.
2: bit8=read, bit9=write, bit10=execute, bit11=16-bit data, bit12-bit15=reserved (set to zero).
3: ID number of what kind of extra it is.

The extras would be:

$00: Arcade cabinet switch. Bit0-bit2 of address is the switch number, bit8 of address is the default setting (1=on, 0=off). Data is the name of the switch.
$01: Cartridge component name. Address bit0-bit7 = component ID, bit8-bit15 = pin. Data is name of component.
$02: ASCII/shortkana text. Address indicate what the text means: 0=title, 1=author, 2=copyright, 3=mapper name, 4=license, 5=publisher, 6=version, 7=date, 8=composer of original, 9=composer of cover, 10=Nintendo four-letter code (do not use for homebrew/unofficial unless an emulated version is made available officially on Wii Virtual Console or whatever), 11=arcade cabinet model number, 12=programmer.
$03: RGB palette. Address is from 0 to 63 indicating which palette index is used at first, data is the RGB triples (one byte per channel) starting from the specified palette index, ranging from 0 for black to 255 for full intensity. (This is basically like the .pal format but made into 63-byte chunks) It is recommended that the user can change this setting.
$04: Track name. Address is track number (0 to 255 only). Data is the name of the track in ASCII/shortkana text. Names can be blank, and if higher track number is given name but lower one is not, the lower numbered tracks still exist and have blank name. If this field is used, the initial value of accumulator is the track number to start at, and the mapper codes can also use the track number (which will not change at runtime unless the mapper code tells it to) to decide which ROM bank to enable and so on.
$05: CIC region code. Data should be empty or ASCII name of region code. Address should be a number identifying the region code (0=unused or Japan). (needs more list? does Nintendo or any other format define 8-bit ID numbers for CIC?)

Mapper Components

Note: In all cases, unconnected/unmentioned pins are not used, rather than being undefined or whatever else.

($00) ROM

Parameters:

$01...$20: Address of ROM data in ROM area of file.

Pins:

$00...$07: Data
$08...$7D: Address
$7E: Chip select (inverted)
$80...$FE: Second port, same as above

($01) RAM

The RAM can be used as a single byte register if none of the address pins are connected.

Parameters:

$01: Set to 1 for battery RAM, 0 if not battery.

Pins:

$00...$07: Data
$08...$7D: Address
$7E: Chip select (inverted)
$7F: Write enable (inverted)
$80...$FF: Second port, same as above

($02) Logic gates

Parameters:

$01: Gate type: 0=AND, 1=OR, 2=XOR, 16=NAND, 17=NOR, 18=XNOR.
$02: Number of inputs per gate (this can be 1 if just using as a buffer or inverter).

Pins:

$00: Output of first gate.
$01...$xx: Inputs of first gate.
$xx+1: Output of second gate.
And so on for each gate.

($03) Multiplication

This is a hardware multiplication for MMC5.

Parameters:

(none)

Pins:

$00...$0F: First input data.
$10...$1F: Second input data.
$20...$3F: Output data.
$40: First input enable (inverted).
$50: Second input enable (inverted).
$60: Output enable (inverted).

($04) Shift register

($05) Flip-flops

This component represents thirty-two JK flip-flops. You can leave some pins unconnected to act as D flip-flop, SR flip-flop, etc.

Parameters:

(none)

Pins:

$x0: Clock
$x1: Data
$x2: Set
$x3: Reset
$x4: J
$x5: K
$x6: Out
$x7: Out (inverted)

($06) Multiplexer

Parameters:

(none)

Pins:

$00...$7F: Signal inputs
$80...$86: Selector inputs
$FE: Output
$FF: Output (inverted)

($07) Diskette drive

Parameters:

$01: Hardware copy protection enable (0=no protection, 1=use protection)

($08) File loading interface

Parameters:

$01: Base 2 log of bits per byte of file. (Value: $00=1 bit, $01=2 bits, $02=4 bits, $03=8 bits, $04=16 bits, etc)

Pins:

$00...$7F: Data out
$80: Chip select (inverted)
$81: Clock
$82: Rewind
$83: End of file

($09) Bandai EEPROM

($0A) Expansion terminal

($0B) Counter

($0C) System reset initializer

($0D) Addressable register

Mapper Audio

Note that you can have multiple instances of each and that their parameters can differ as well as how the address lines are connected by using other mapper codes.

($00) Extra 2A03 audio

(see APU)

This need not be indicated if using only the NES/Famicom internal audio; this is if you need an additional 2A03 audio as well as the internal one.

Parameters:

(none)

($01) Famicom Disk System audio

(see FDS audio)

Parameters:

(none)

($02) VRC6 audio

(see VRC6 audio)

Parameters:

(none)

($03) VRC7 audio

(see VRC7 audio)

Parameters:

Parameter $03: Register write delay (1=on/0=off) (should be on; turn it off if it is necessary to emulate a program that does not properly wait for the register to be ready)
Parameter $04..$7B: Internal patch set (8 bytes each for 15 instruments) (optional; please set the length to 4 if you are not using this parameter)

($04) MMC5 audio

(see MMC5 audio)

Parameters:

(none)

($05) Sunsoft audio

(see Sunsoft 5B audio)

Parameters:

Parameter $03: Clock speed (0=half, 1=full) (should be 0 to emulate Sunsoft 5B audio)

($06) Namco audio

(see Namco 163 audio)

Parameters:

(none)

($07) JF-13 audio

Parameters:

Parameter $03...$22: ROM address of audio data

($08) Digital to analog converter

Parameters:

Parameter $03: Default normalized output level
Parameter $04: (linear/non-linear?)

Pins:

Pin $00: 1x audio level.
Pin $01: 2x audio level.
Pin $02: 4x audio level.
Pin $03: 8x audio level.
etc, up to pin $FF for an extremely high level.

ASCII/shortkana Table

# | 0 | 1 | 2 | 3 | 4 | 5 | 6 | 7 | 8 | 9 | A | B | C | D | E | F
0 | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | ***
1 | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | *** | ***
2 | sp | ! | " | # | $ | % | & | ' | ( | ) | * | + | , | - | . | /
3 | 0 | 1 | 2 | 3 | 4 | 5 | 6 | 7 | 8 | 9 | : | ; | < | = | > | ?
4 | @ | A | B | C | D | E | F | G | H | I | J | K | L | M | N | O
5 | P | Q | R | S | T | U | V | W | X | Y | Z | [ | \ | ] | ^ | _
6 | ` | a | b | c | d | e | f | g | h | i | j | k | l | m | n | o
7 | p | q | r | s | t | u | v | w | x | y | z | { | | | } | ~ | ***
8 | Ç | ü | é | â | ä | à | å | ç | ê | ë | è | ï | î | ì | Ä | Å
9 | É | æ | Æ | ô | ö | ò | û | ù | ÿ | Ö | Ü | ¢ | £ | ¥ | « | »
A | ア | カ | ガ | サ | ザ | タ | ダ | ナ | ハ | バ | パ | マ | ヤ | ャ | ラ | ァ
B | イ | キ | ギ | シ | ジ | チ | ヂ | ニ | ヒ | ビ | ピ | ミ | ワ | ン | リ | ィ
C | ウ | ク | グ | ス | ズ | ツ | ヅ | ヌ | フ | ブ | プ | ム | ユ | ュ | ル | ゥ
D | エ | ケ | ゲ | セ | ゼ | テ | デ | ネ | ヘ | ベ | ペ | メ | ッ | ヲ | レ | ェ
E | オ | コ | ゴ | ソ | ゾ | ト | ド | ノ | ホ | ボ | ポ | モ | ヨ | ョ | ロ | ォ
F | á | í | ó | ú | ñ | Ñ | ??? | ??? | ¿ | ??? | ??? | ??? | ??? | ¡ | ー | ***

*** indicates permanently reserved codes would should not be used in ASCII/shortkana text.
??? indicates codes which are reserved for future use.

There are suggestions to use different encodings (such as UTF-8 or UTF-16, although I don't want UTF-16 or anything else that is incompatible with ASCII), so it might be changed in future. For now use only ASCII please.

Other File Formats

.rom

This file consists of the ROM data only, with no header. The file size should be a multiple of 8K.

.cart

This file consists of the mapper codes only, with no header.

.symb

This file consists of the symbols only, with no header.

ines.map

This plain text file is used to automatically associate .cart files with .nes files, based on mapper numbers, ROM sizes, checksums, and other things. Values of external parameters can also be specified.

I intend that it can make the official "ines.map" and FamicomHDL files on this wiki, and can then be updated emulators, both static (the ines.map and *.cart are compiled into a C code and compiled with the emulator), and dynamic (the emulator converts .nes to .fami at runtime and JIT-compiles and emulates the mapper codes).

Description of file: User:Zzo38/ines.map and unif.map

unif.map

This plain text file is used to automatically associate .cart files with .unif files based on the contents of the file. Values of external parameters can also be specified.

Description of file: User:Zzo38/ines.map and unif.map

.native

The format of this file depends on the emulator using it, and some might not use it; however, the first eight bytes should indicate what emulator it is for and what computer it is for, so that one program does not get mixed up by another program.

Generally this file would contain a native code for emulating the mapper codes.

Supported programs

Emulators (compile time)

Emulators (run time)

Hardware programmers

Assemblers/compilers

Hardware description language

FamicomHDL (Haskell library)

Miscellaneous

User:Zzo38/Hardware NSF

!!! WARNING !!! THIS HAS VARIOUS MISTAKES IN IT !!!

These are some of my ideas for hardware NSF.

Contents

1 Hardware
2 PRG ROM Layout
3 CHR ROM Layout
4 Main Routine
5 Interrupt Routine
6 File Loading
7 Miscellaneous Information

Hardware

Memory from $4018-$403F would be filled by a 40-byte ROM used for an interrupt routine. (Famicom Disk System uses some of these addresses but NSF only uses the audio registers, not these ones.)

When the main routine is enabled, $8000-$BFFF is a single byte of RAM (used to store the current song number; mirrored) and $C000-$FFFF is ROM (also mirrored; not much ROM is needed).

Writing to even bytes of $4018-$403F: If bit2 is set, the memory from $8000-$DFFF becomes read/write (except main routine ROM which is always read-only), otherwise it is read-only. If bit0 is set, VRC6 audio will play, otherwise it will be muted. If bit1 is set, VRC7 audio will play and otherwise is muted. If bit5 is set, Sunsoft 5B audio is played and is otherwise muted. Other bits (bit3, bit4, bit6, and bit7) are ignored.

Writing to odd bytes of $4018-$403F enables main routine ROM if the low bit of the data is set, and disables if the low bit is clear. Other bits are ignored.

The hardware generate IRQ at the rate specified in the NSF header. When IRQ is called, the IRQ vector should be read as $4018 whenever it is checked.

Another thing the hardware will do is convert the audio to digital and whenever the name tables are being accessed, make the pattern tables read as a waveform view of the music being played.

PRG ROM Layout

(note: somewhat obsolete with new specification)

+-----+-----------------------+
| 1FF | Interrupt vectors     |
| 1FA |                       |
+-----+-----------------------+
| 1F9 | Main routine          |
| 100 |                       |
+-----+-----------------------+
| 0FF | .NSF header           |
| 080 |                       |
+-----+-----------------------+
| 07F | Main routine helper   |
| 040 |                       |
+-----+-----------------------+
| 03F | Interrupt routine     |
| 018 |                       |
+-----+-----------------------+
| 017 | Stop routine          |
| 000 |                       |
+-----+-----------------------+

CHR ROM Layout

CHR ROM is ASCII, but tile $00 is blank, and tiles $10-$1F contain the hex digits "0" to "F".

Printable ASCII characters use color 3 for the foreground, and hex digits use color 1 for the foreground. All tiles use color 0 for the background. This way, the palette can be changed to make it change color of the song number digits to indicate play/stop.

While rendering rows below the fourth row, the CHR ROM will not be accessible and instead they will be connected to a analog-to-digital converter which puts the same data regardless of address (but which is depending on the position on screen).

Main Routine

(note: somewhat obsolete with new specification)

Disable IRQ.
Wait for PPU.
Write the starting song number (offset $07 of header) to $8000, and then decrement it.
Copy expansion chip byte (offset $7B of header) to $4018.
Set up palette.
Fill up the nametable with the title and so on from the NSF header, and with the current and maximum song number, and indicate the music is stopped.
Enable background.
Loop:

Update the display of the current song number.
If LEFT is pushed:

Decrement current song number. If it is zero it wraps around.
Wait for button is not pushed.

If RIGHT is pushed:

Increment current song number. If it is too high it wraps to zero.
Wait for button is not pushed.

If START is pushed:

Initialize the sound registers by writing $00 to $4000-$4013, $0F to $4015.
Initialize the frame counter to 4-step mode ($40 to $4017).
Write initial bank values to $5FF6-$5FFF. (If the initial bank values are all zero, instead compute them from the load address.)
Update display to indicate song is playing.
Load value at memory $8000 into the accumulator.
Load zero into the X register.
Jump to the start routine.

Stop routine:

Disable interrupts.
Turn off all audio.
Reset the stack pointer.
Update display to indicate song is stopped.
Go to main loop checking which button is pushed.

Interrupt Routine

Check if the A button is pushed.
If the A button is pushed (it should branch if button pushed rather than skip over if unpushed because this way uses less clock cycles):

Enable main routine ROM.
Jump to the stop routine.

Reset the stack pointer.
Call the play subroutine.
Enable interrupts.
Run an idle loop doing nothing.
Start routine:

Disable main routine ROM.
Call the init subroutine.
Enable interrupts.
Run an idle loop doing nothing.

Code (40 bytes, 30 clock):

        .ORG $4018
intr    LDX #1       ; 2/2 (X=1)
        STX $4016    ; 3/4 (strobe)
        DEX          ; 1/2 (X=0)
        STX $4016    ; 3/4 (allow buttons to be read)
        LDA $4016    ; 3/4 (read "A" button)
        BNE stopa    ; 2/2 (branch if button pushed)
        DEX          ; 1/2 (X=255)
        TXS          ; 1/2 (reset stack)
        JSR play     ; 3/6
        CLI          ; 1/2
wait    JMP wait     ; 3/- (wait)
stopa   STA $4019    ; 3/- (write 1 to $4019)
        JMP stop     ; 3/-
start   STX $4019    ; 3/- (write 0 to $4019)
        JSR init     ; 3/-
        CLI          ; 1/-
        JMP wait     ; 3/-

File Loading

Depending on how the data is loaded onto the cartridge, some things may need to differ a bit, for example it may need to include codes to read the file. This may mean having 128 bytes of RAM in $8000-$BFFF instead of only 1 byte, and use this for the .NSF header (header $07 could be reused for the current song number), and then have another code to load the banks by first setting bit2 of $4018, and then after it is loaded, copy header $7B to $4018 which may or may not clear bit2.

The header bytes at $78 and $79 could be used for telling the cartridge what IRQ period to use. It could do something like this when loading:

Disable interrupts.
Read the first 128 bytes of the file into the RAM reserved for the header ($8000-$807F).
Check the first six bytes of the header. If they are wrong:

Change background to red.
Play error tone.
Halt.

Detect TV system.

If NTSC: Copy header $6E to $78 and $6F to $79.
If bit1 of header $7A is not set, and bit0 of the header $7A is not equal to detected TV system:

Change background to yellow.
Play error tone.
Halt.

Write the detected TV system to header $7A.

Read header $70 to $77. If all of them are zero:

Load header $09 into a register.
Right shift four spaces.
Copy it to the X register.
Load zero into the A register.
While X is not equal to ten:

STA $8068,X
Increment X register.
Add one to A register.

Bitwise AND header $09 with literal $0F.
Bitwise OR header $09 with literal $60.
Write $40 to $4018.
Write zero to Y register and $5FF6.
Until end of file:

Read one byte from file.
Use header $08 and $09 as address to write the byte which has been read from the file.
Add one to header $08 and carry over to header $09.
If bit4 of header $09 is set:

Increment Y register.
Write contents of Y register to $5FF6.
Clear bit4 at header $09.

Start loading the nametable and so on, and wait for buttons pushed.

Here is a description of a possible file-loading interface (you could use it in other hardware designs too; not only this one):

A port with 12 pins on the cartridge: Data0 to Data7, Clock, EOF, Power, and Ground.
A device which connects to that port will use the simple file-loading protocol: When Clock is received, it reads a byte from the file and updates the Data0 to Data7 pins. If a byte cannot be read because it is the end of the file, EOF pin is set instead.
Cartridge has some way of connecting this port to the memory accessible by CPU.

This hardware NSF could have it implemented as follows:

When powered on, the range $4040-$40FF accesses the file-loading port. A clock will be set and the data pins will be readable in this memory.
When EOF is set, IRQ will be triggered and then memory range $4040-$40FF will be used as FDS audio from then on.

Miscellaneous Information

All audio expansion are always implemented, although the Sunsoft 5B, VRC6, and VRC7 can be muted (individually).
Memory range $6000-$7FFF is always RAM.
Memory $8000-$FFFF is either the NSF RAM or the "main routine" memory, which is 128 bytes of RAM and 512 bytes of ROM (only 1 byte of RAM if not using the "file loading" above).
RAM banks of 4K each can be written to when writing $6000-$DFFF is enabled, and can be switched using the NSF bankswitching registers.
Memory $E000-$FFFF is read-only, although it is a RAM bank, you can never write the RAM using these addresses; you must map it to different addresses to write it.
Memory $6000-$DFFF is banked RAM, and is writable when enabled, and otherwise read-only.
Some mirrored registers can be implemented, although done such that the addresses specified in the NSF specification always work without conflicts.

User:Zzo38/Mapper 768

I am reserving mapper 768 for my own use. This is not currently an official specification, nor is it currently supported by any emulators at the time of this writing, which is why it is not currently in the main namespace.

In all cases, the NES 2.0 file is arranged like (some parts may be omitted, depending on the header):

Header
Trainer
PRG ROM
CHR ROM
INST-ROM
PROM
128-byte null-terminated ASCII title
Extra data for mapper 768 (depending on submapper number)

Omitting parts of the file that are required (according to the header) is not allowed if mapper 768 is used. There is some discussion of extending the format to specify that extra data exists, but this is currently unknown.

Use of UNIF is supported by this specification, but is not recommended; it is meant to be used with NES 2.0.

Contents

1 Submapper 0

1.1 Commands
1.2 NSF Interface
1.3 Examples

1.3.1 Simple bankswitching
1.3.2 Mapper 218
1.3.3 Double bus CHR RAM

2 Submapper 1

Submapper 0

The UNIF name for this mapper is "X-Custom", and has the "XTRA" block for extra data.

The extra data stores the code for a virtual machine, to control the mapper. The commands are sixteen bits in small endian format, and are split into subroutine blocks. At the beginning of each block is one byte to tells how many sixteen-bit commands are in this subroutine block (this includes immediate values too).

The first block is always the initialization block.

Anything other than what is written in the codes acts like NROM (iNES mapper 0) (only the first 16K or 32K of PRG ROM is accessible, though).

There is sixteen registers, with sixteen bits each. R0 and R1 are local to a subroutine call, and the R2 to R15 are global registers (all general purpose). There is also two more local registers, called W (working register) and W' (shadow working register).

Subroutine numbers are eight bits long. Each subroutine takes two parameters which is the initial assignment of R0 and R1 registers, and returns a sixteen bit number.

Commands

0000 0000 xxxx yyyy (XCAL) = Call a subroutine indicated in the low eight bits of Rx, with this call's R0 and R1 as its parameters, and store the result in Ry (leave Ry alone if the result is open bus or CIRAM).
0000 0001 0000 xxxx (COPW) = Copy W to Rx.
0000 0001 0001 xxxx (COPR) = Copy Rx to W.
0000 0001 0010 xxxx (ADDW) = Add W to Rx.
0000 0001 0011 xxxx (ADDR) = Add Rx to W.
0000 0001 0100 xxxx (SUBW) = Subtract W from Rx.
0000 0001 0101 xxxx (SUBR) = Subtract Rx from W.
0000 0001 0110 xxxx (ANDW) = Bitwise AND W to Rx.
0000 0001 0111 xxxx (ANDR) = Bitwise AND Rx to W.
0000 0001 1000 xxxx (IORW) = Bitwise OR W to Rx.
0000 0001 1001 xxxx (IORR) = Bitwise OR Rx to W.
0000 0001 1010 xxxx (XORW) = Bitwise XOR W to Rx.
0000 0001 1011 xxxx (XORR) = Bitwise XOR Rx to W.
0000 0001 1100 xxxx (NANW) = Bitwise NAND W to Rx.
0000 0001 1101 xxxx (NANR) = Bitwise NAND Rx to W.
0000 0001 1110 xxxx (NOTW) = Copy NOT W to Rx.
0000 0001 1111 xxxx (NOTR) = Copy NOT Rx to W.
0000 0010 0000 xxxx (RETR) = Return the value in Rx from this subroutine.
0000 0010 0001 0000 (OPEN) = Return open bus from this subroutine.
0000 0010 0001 0001 (RETW) = Return the value in W from this subroutine.
0000 0010 0001 0010 (CIR0) = Return CIRAM bank 0 from this subroutine. (Returning CIRAM banks is the same as open bus unless the PPU is accessing this memory.)
0000 0010 0001 0011 (CIR1) = Return CIRAM bank 1 from this subroutine.
0000 0010 0001 0110 (CIRC) = Return CIRAM bank 0 if condition flag is set, or bank 1 if condition flag is clear.
0000 0010 0001 0111 (CIRS) = Return CIRAM bank 1 if condition flag is set, or bank 0 if condition flag is clear.
0000 0010 0001 1xxx (RETL) = Return the literal value x (all other bits zero) from this subroutine.
0000 0011 0000 0000 (SWAP) = Swap W with W'.
0000 0011 0001 xxxx (IMMR) = Store an immediate value into Rx. The condition flag is set to if the value changed.
0000 0011 0010 xxxx (ASLR) = Shift left Rx. The shifted out bit is stored in the condition flag.
0000 0011 0011 xxxx (ADDI) = Add an immediate value to Rx. The condition flag is set to if there is the signed overflow.
0000 0011 0100 xxxx (ASRR) = Arithmetic shift right Rx. The shifted out bit is stored in the condition flag.
0000 0011 0110 xxxx (RORR) = Rotate right Rx.
0000 0011 0111 xxxx (ANDI) = Bitwise AND an immediate value to Rx. The condition flag is set to if the value changed.
0000 0011 1001 xxxx (IORI) = Bitwise OR an immediate value to Rx. The condition flag is set toif the value changed.
0000 0011 1010 xxxx (LSRR) = Logical shift right Rx. The shifted out bit is stored in the condition flag.
0000 0011 1011 xxxx (XORI) = Bitwise XOR an immediate value to Rx. The condition flag is set to if the value changed.
0000 0011 1100 xxxx (INVR) = Bitwise invert Rx.
0000 0011 1101 xxxx (NANI) = Bitwise NAND an immediate value to Rx. The condition flag is set if and only if the value changed.
0000 0011 1110 xxxx (ZERO) = Set the condition flag if Rx is zero, or clear the condition flag otherwise.
0000 0011 1111 xxxx (EQUA) = Set the condition flag if the immediate value is equal to Rx, or clear the condition flag otherwise.
0000 0100 000x xxxx (SKIT) = Skip x+1 instructions (counting immediate values as instructions) if the condition flag is set.
0000 0100 001x xxxx (SKIF) = Skip x+1 instructions (counting immediate values as instructions) if the condition flag is clear.
0000 0100 0100 0000 (TIRQ) = Trigger IRQ.
0000 0100 0101 0000 (WPR1) = Force battery RAM to be write-protected.
0000 0100 0101 0001 (WPR0) = Turn off the forced write-protection of battery RAM.
0000 1000 xxxx yyyy (COPY) = Copy Rx to Ry.
0000 1010 xxxx yyyy (COPT) = Copy Rx to Ry if condition flag is set.
0000 1011 xxxx yyyy (COPF) = Copy Rx to Ry if condition flag is clear.
0001 0000 xxxx xxxx (RPRG) = Using W as a start address, W' as a end address, and R15 as a mask (any set bits in the mask correspond to address bits that must match that of the start address), set the subroutine calls for reading PRG memory to the subroutine x.
0001 0001 xxxx xxxx (WPRG) = Set the subroutine calls for writing PRG memory to the subroutine x.
0001 0010 xxxx xxxx (RCHR) = Set the subroutine calls for reading CHR memory to the subroutine x.
0001 0011 xxxx xxxx (WCHR) = Set the subroutine calls for writing CHR memory to the subroutine x.
0001 0100 xxxx xxxx (ACHR) = Set the subroutine calls for what happens when the PPU address bus changes without a read or write.
0001 1000 xxxx xxxx (RSET) = Set the subroutine calls for reset to the subroutine x.
0001 1001 xxxx xxxx (DISK) = Set the subroutine calls for FDS IRQ to the subroutine x.
0100 xxxx yyyy yyyy (CTIM) = Set a timer for Rx CPU clocks to call subroutine y (just once, when the timer expires). If Rx is -1 then it is turned off.
0101 xxxx yyyy yyyy (PTIM) = Set a timer for Rx PPU reads to call subroutine y (just once, when the timer expires). If Rx is -1 then it is turned off.
1000 xxxx yyyy yyyy (CALL) = Call subroutine y with this subroutine's W and W' as parameters, and store the result in Rx (leave Rx alone if the result is open bus or CIRAM).
1001 0000 xxxx yyyy (RNSF) = Read from the NSF interface, address in Rx, into Ry.
1001 0001 xxxx yyyy (WNSF) = Write to the NSF interface, address Rx, value Ry.
1001 0010 xxxx yyyy (ROPR) = Read from the PRG ROM, address Rx, into Ry.
1001 0100 xxxx yyyy (ROCH) = Read from the CHR ROM, address Rx, into Ry.
1001 0110 xxxx yyyy (ROTR) = Read from the trainer ROM, address Rx, into Ry.
1001 1000 xxxx yyyy (RNPR) = Read from non-battery PRG RAM, address in Rx, into Ry.
1001 1001 xxxx yyyy (WNPR) = Write to non-battery PRG RAM, address Rx, value Ry.
1001 1010 xxxx yyyy (RNCH) = Read from non-battery CHR RAM, address Rx, into Ry.
1001 1011 xxxx yyyy (WNCH) = Write to non-battery CHR RAM, address Rx, value Ry.
1001 1100 xxxx yyyy (RBPR) = Read from battery PRG RAM, address Rx, into Ry.
1001 1101 xxxx yyyy (WBPR) = Write to battery PRG RAM, address Rx, value Ry.
1001 1110 xxxx yyyy (RBCH) = Read from battery CHR RAM, address Rx, into Ry.
1001 1111 xxxx yyyy (WBCH) = Write to battery CHR RAM, address Rx, value Ry.

When a subroutine call is triggered due to CPU or PPU read/write, R0 will be the address, and R1 will be the data for writing (R1 is undefined if reading). Returning CIRAM bank 0 or CIRAM bank 1 from PPU read routines causes it to read the CIRAM instead of the cartridge. Returning CIRAM banks from PPU write routines causes it to write to the CIRAM of the specified bank (the routine can do other things too). Returning open bus or any number from any write routine, or any CIRAM bank from any PRG write routine, does nothing. The default return value (if a block ends without an explicit return) is open bus. If a read routine is called for addresses below $4020, it must return open bus or CIRAM banks, otherwise the result is undefined.

NSF Interface

$0000-$00FF: General purpose RAM (stored in the cartridge; not the same as the CPU RAM, or the cartridge PRG RAM and CHR RAM mentioned in the header; this is only accessible by the NSF interface).
$2000,$2001 (CART_CPU_COUNT): Sixteen bit CPU clock counter; can be written as well.
$2002,$2003 (CART_PPU_COUNT): Sixteen bit PPU read counter; can be written as well.
$2005 (CART_BUS_CONFLICT): Write the number of bus conflicts that happen at one time into here. Writing zero does nothing. This might be used by an emulator which counts bus conflicts in order to detect errors in your program.
$2006 (CART_PRG_ROM_BANK): PRG ROM bank select.
$2007 (CART_CHR_ROM_BANK): CHR ROM bank select.
$2008 (CART_PROTECT): Clear the low bit to force battery RAM to be write-protected.
$2009 (CART_MUTE): Write-only. If bit0 is set, 2A03 audio is muted. If bit1 is set, MMC5 PCM is muted.
$200A (CART_ADC) : Read-only. An 8-bit analog to digital converter reading the microphone audio mixed with the 2A03 audio.
$200C (CART_PRG_RAM_BANK): Non-battery PRG RAM bank select.
$200D (CART_PRG_BAT_BANK): Battery PRG RAM bank select.
$200E (CART_CHR_RAM_BANK): Non-battery CHR RAM bank select.
$200F (CART_CHR_BAT_BANK): Battery CHR RAM bank select.
$4020-$4092: FDS registers. All registers (including audio) are available, although bit3 of $4025 has no effect if PPU read/writes are not acting in NROM mode (i.e. if they have been overridden by the mapper).
$4800,$F800: Namco 163 audio.
$5000-$5015: MMC5 audio. (The read mode acts on CPU memory, not NSF memory.)
$5205,$5206: MMC5 hardware multiplication register.
$9000-$9003,$A000-$A002,$B000-$B002: VRC6 audio.
$9010,$9030: VRC7 audio.
$C000,$E000: Sunsoft 5B audio.

Bank select registers are always eight high bits of whatever is available (for example if you have 64K ROM and 32K bank size, you should set only the high bit of the PRG ROM bank register).

Examples

Simple bankswitching

; Simple bankswitching mapper; write to $8000-$FFFF, low bit of address selects bank.
@INIT
IMMR F FFFF
COPR F
SWAP
IMMR F 8000
COPR F
ASLR F
RPRG @READPRG
WPRG @BANKSET
@READPRG
ANDI 0 7FFF
COPR F
IORW 0
ROPR 0 1
RETR 1
@BANKSET
7*ASLR 0
COPY 0 F

Mapper 218

; Single-chip mapper
@INIT
IMMR F FFFF
COPR F
SWAP
INVR F
COPR F
RCHR @PPU_ACCESS
WCHR @PPU_ACCESS
@PPU_ACCESS
IORI 0 2000 ; Change this line for a different CIRAM A10 connection.
CIRC

Double bus CHR RAM

; Write into low four bits of $5000-$5FFF to activate/deactivate CIRAM for PRG memory
; Write into $1000-$1FFF to copy the values written into the CHR RAM in the cartridge
@INIT
IMMR F 0000
IMMR E 5FFF
COPR E
SWAP
IMMR E 5000
COPR E
WPRG @PPU_SET
IMMR E 3FFF
COPR E
SWAP
IMMR E 0000
COPR E
RCHR @CHR_ACCESS
WCHR @CHR_ACCESS
IMMR E 1FFF
COPR E
SWAP
IMMR E 1000
COPR E
WPRG @CHR_WRITE
IMMR 8 0000
IMMR 9 0040
IMMR A 0080
IMMR B 00C0
IMMR C FFFF
@PPU_SET
COPY 8 4
COPY 8 5
COPT 8 6
COPY 8 7
COPY 1 0
IORI 0 0001
COPT C 4
IORI 0 0002
COPT C 5
IORI 0 0004
COPT C 6
IORI 0 0008
COPT C 7
WNSF 8 4
WNSF 9 5
WNSF A 6
WNSF B 7
@CHR_ACCESS
COPY 0 1
ANDI 1 3000
6*LSRR 1
;***TODO***
@CHR_WRITE
ANDI 0 0FFF
WNCH 0 1

Submapper 1

The UNIF name for this mapper is "X-Verilog".

Extra data is not used. There is expected to be a file with .nes.v extension (otherwise having the same name), which contains a Verilog code for implementing the mapper. Some emulators might require that the Verilog code is compiled first into another file (possibly a DLL or shared object file); if so, such thing should be explained in the documentation for that particular emulator.

The first sixty I/O ports of the main module of the Verilog code must correspond to the pins 01 to 60 of the 60-pin Famicom cartridge, in that order. This is followed by the pins for the PRG ROM, CHR ROM, non-battery PRG RAM, non-battery CHR RAM, battery PRG RAM, and battery CHR RAM.

The ROM/RAM pins are only for the ROM/RAM which are existing, and is as follows:

Chip enable (low to enable)
Write enable (low to enable; not exist for ROM)
Address pins (the exact number of pins needed for the ROM/RAM of the size specified in the NES 2.0 header)
Data pins (always eight)

The commands with $ at front might not be implemented, but should be safely ignored if not implemented. However, if there is a trainer ROM, there will be an additional command $trainer to access 8-bit numbers given the 9-bit address, and $battery_init which tell you if you need to initialize the battery RAM.

Analog commands may be used with the audio signals.

User:Zzo38/Mapper A

This is the "AY-3-8910 only" mapper. Registers are mapped to the PPU address space $3000-$3FFF, and only the address is used; the data isn't used for writing the mapper registers. This can be accessed by writing $2006.

Submappers

Bit0 specifies the mirroring mode. If clear, uses hardwired H or V mirroring. If set, it specifies software-controlled one-screen mirroring; the mirroring bit in the iNES header is then used to specify which bit of which register is used to control it (H=bit7 of port A, V=bit7 of port B).

The other bits are used to select the output levels and filters of each channel output; currently only zero is defined, meaning that all three channels are mixed with the 2A03 and microphone audio at equal volume.

Registers

Registers are write-only and are not accessible during rendering. To write to a register: Set the PPU address to $300x or $330x (bit10 and bit11 are ignored; the registers are mirrored), where x is the register number. Set the PPU address to $32xx, where x is the value to write. Something like this may work (untested):

  ; Write A to port Y
  ldx #$33
  stx PPUADDR
  sty PPUADDR
  dex
  stx PPUADDR
  sta PPUADDR

These are the registers of the AY-3-8910 when the BDIR pin is fixed high.

The bankswitching is done using the two I/O ports of the AY-3-8910. The mapper will not work properly unless both ports are in output mode, so after reset this should be done at first. To keep the high address lines from floating while the I/O ports are still in input mode, PRG bank lines should have pull-up resistors. An emulator should assume these resistors are present, even though some cartridges might not. Still, all 32K PRG ROM banks should contain at least some reset code because the player can press Reset at any time.

32K PRG ROM banks are selected by writing the bank number to the low bits of port A.
8K PRG RAM banks are mapped to $6000-$7FFF and are selected by writing the bank number to the high bits of port A.
8K CHR ROM or CHR RAM banks are selected by writing the bank number to the low bits of port B.
If both CHR ROM and CHR RAM is present, and four-screen mirroring is specified in the iNES header, then there is 8K RAM split at $0000-$0FFF and $2000-$2FFF, and 8K ROM split at $1000-$1FFF and $3000-$3EFF. The RAM bank is then selected by the high bits of port B.
If both CHR ROM and CHR RAM is present, and four-screen mirroring isn't specified in the iNES header, then the high bit of port B selects between ROM and RAM in $0000-$1FFF.

Note: Normally there is PRG ROM and CHR ROM, but no PRG RAM and CHR RAM. Nevertheless, use of RAM is well-defined and with some extra logic it can be added to the board (if there is no RAM, then all the decoding logic is either part of the AY-3-8910 or it is already decoded in the cartridge connector; therefore a 60-pins cartridge will have three chips and a 72-pins cartridge will have four chips).

User:Zzo38/Metadata INI

You can have a INI file, with the .nes.ini (or .unif.ini or .fds.ini or .qdi.ini) extension, to describe preferred controllers and other information about a game other than what is in the ROM image file.

Anything in the file not understood by whatever program is reading this file, should be ignored. Everything is optional (both for writing and for reading; different blocks may be meaningful for different programs that would use this information). The reason for this is to avoid complicating an implementation, while still allowing features that someone may use.

If numbers are expected in a value, they are normally decimal, and can be hexadecimal by 0x prefix.

(Note: For QDI format disk images, the INI file must correspond to the file for the bootable side.)

Contents

1 Blocks

1.1 Main

1.1.1 Title
1.1.2 Author
1.1.3 URL
1.1.4 Version
1.1.5 TV
1.1.6 License
1.1.7 CRC
1.1.8 Bootgod
1.1.9 Text
1.1.10 PPUID

1.2 Controller

1.2.1 Players
1.2.2 Player1
1.2.3 Player2
1.2.4 Player3
1.2.5 Player4
1.2.6 Expansion
1.2.7 FourScore

1.3 License

1.3.1 Name
1.3.2 FreeSoftware
1.3.3 OpenSource
1.3.4 PublicDomain

1.4 Mapper

1.4.1 Name
1.4.2 Number
1.4.3 NumberEx
1.4.4 Feature
1.4.5 Mirror
1.4.6 RAM
1.4.7 BusConflict
1.4.8 Audio
1.4.9 Verilog

1.5 Switch
1.6 Emulator
1.7 Dump
1.8 Hardware
1.9 EmuTest
1.10 Tag
1.11 File
1.12 Memory
1.13 Enhance

1.13.1 PopReduction
1.13.2 CueAudio
1.13.3 PointingDeviceRAM
1.13.4 SpriteLimit
1.13.5 HighScore
1.13.6 ScreenMode
1.13.7 Overscan

1.14 GameGenie

2 Example

Blocks

Main

Title

The title of this game. This does not have to be the same as the title in a UNIF file or the title added to the end of some iNES files.

Author

The name of the author of this game.

URL

URL to access information of this game. Any URI scheme is allowed, but file:/// and LAN addresses is not recommended for files distributed on the internet.

Version

Game version number.

TV

Specify the TV mode supported, separated by vertical bars if there is more than one.

NTSC: NTSC Famicom or NTSC NES.
RGB: RGB Famicom or Vs System.
PAL: PAL NES.
Dendy: Dendy PAL Famiclone.

Usually, a subset of this information is specified in the ROM image header.

License

Specify if the game is officially licensed.

Official means it is licensed by Nintendo.
Unofficial means that it is not licensed by Nintendo; for example, anything published by Tengen, Codemasters, or Color Dreams, or homebrew software.

CRC

Specify the CRC32 checksum. If it doesn't match, it is error (alternatives are to make it a warning, or to just ignore the rest of the INI file if the checksum doesn't match).

Bootgod

The ID number for the game in bootgod database. Emulators should not use klugy hacks to work with specific games if the INI file exists and does not have either the Bootgod entry specified or the emulator's entry in the Emulator block set.

Text

Absolute address into ROM image file of a null-terminatd text. It is not required for UNIF, although it is still allowed.

PPUID

The low five bits of the value which should be read from $2002. Normally this is read from the NES 2.0 header, but in case that is not available, it is specified here.

Controller

Players

Tells how many players. Can be 1, 2, 3, 4, or can be multiples separated by vertical bars.

Player1

Specify the device connected to the first NES controller port. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars; it can also be blank entries meaning nothing is connected.

Standard: The standard controller of NES/Famicom.
DoubleFisted: The standard NES controller, rotated 90 degrees with the Control Pad at the top and A at the bottom like a Wii Remote.
Mouse: Super NES Mouse.
LightGun: Zapper.
Arkanoid: Arkanoid controller (NES version).
SuperNintendo: Super Nintendo standard controller.
SuperPakPak: Super PakPak analog controller.
VsSystem: VS System. Player 1 VS system controller must be specified in the player 2 slot and vice versa.
VsLightGun: VS System serial light gun. Player 1 VS system controller must be specified in the player 2 slot and vice versa.
PowerPad, PowerPadB, FamilyTrainer, FamilyTrainerB: Power Pad B side.
PowerPadA, FamilyTrainerA: Power Pad A side.
PowerPadLeft, FamilyTrainerLeft: Power Pad B side, rotated by 90 degrees so that the encoder is at the left.
StandardDDR: Dance mat which is using the protocol of the standard controller and allows Left+Right and Up+Down presses. Used by some NOAC-based dance mats.

Player2

Specify the device connected to the second NES controller port. They are the same as Player1 devices, except for the following:

Standard: Does not include SELECT and START buttons.
StandardSelectStart: Does include SELECT and START buttons.
StandardMicrophone: Uses the microphone.

Player3

Used if Expansion=FourPlayers or FourScore=Yes is specified. Must be a controller that uses D0 or D1, not D3-D4.

Player4

Used if Expansion=FourPlayers or FourScore=Yes is specified. Must be a controller that uses D0 or D1, not D3-D4.

Expansion

Specify the device connected to the Famicom expansion port. (In case of some devices that work on Player2 or the expansion port, it can be specified either way.)

Keyboard: Famicom keyboard.
OekaKids: Oeka Kids tablet.
KeyboardTape: Famicom keyboard and tape recorder.
FourPlayers: Four players game (parallel multiplayer adapter). The Player3 and Player4 fields specify the controller for player 3 and 4 whose D0 is connected to the Famicom's D1.
LightGun, FamilyTrainer, FamilyTrainerB, FamilyTrainerA, FamilyTrainerLeft, StandardDDR: As above (considered as player 2 port). CaH4e3 claims that Dance 2000 12-in-1 uses StandardDDR.
Arkanoid: Arkanoid controller (Famicom version).
HoriTrack: Hori trackball.
ExciteBoxing: Exciting boxing.
Mahjong: Mahjong.
Stereovision: Famicom 3D glasses.

FourScore

Specifies if NES Four Score (serial multiplayer adapter) is used. Values can be No and Yes. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

If Expansion=FourPlayers or FourScore=Yes is specified, the Player1, Player2, Player3, and Player4 indicate device connected to the adapter (such as Standard, DoubleFisted, or StandardDDR). Devices using D2-D4 won't work on either adapter, and devices using a long report, such as the Super NES Controller and Super NES Mouse, work only with Expansion=FourPlayers, not FourScore=Yes. If a game specifies both a four-player adapter and a peripheral incompatible with the adapter, the emulator MUST provide a way to switch between the adapter and the other peripheral.

License

Name

Name of a software license.

FreeSoftware

The value can be No and Yes. Specify if it meets the Free Software definition (from FSF).

OpenSource

The value can be No and Yes. Specify if it meets the Open Source definition (from OSI).

Usually this value will be the same as the FreeSoftware value, but there are some exceptions.

PublicDomain

The value can be No and Yes. Specify if it is effectively public domain (e.g.: public domain, WTFPL, Unlicense, CC0).

Mapper

Information of mapper.

Name

Name of the mapper. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

Number

The iNES mapper number (0-255 for basic plane, 256-4095 for NES 2.0 planes), optionally followed by a dot and the submapper number (0-15 or A-F). If no submapper is specified, submapper 0 is assumed. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars. If used with NES 2.0 format ROM image files, at least one of the numbers listed here MUST be the same as in the ROM image file (and will normally be the first one), if this line is used at all. In old iNES files, it is probably going to be the same, although in some cases it might not be (these cases are fixed by the NES 2.0 format).

NumberEx

Specifies extensions to the mapper which are not necessarily relevant for emulation (or which are already disambiguated by the ROM and RAM sizes). You can have multiple numbers separated by vertical bars, but usually you won't, since you will only specify the features actually used on this mapper (some games might have been released with multiple mapper settings though, for some reason).

This is a sixteen-bit number. Its meaning depends on the first iNES mapper number specified in the Number; the low four bits have the same meaning as submapper numbers.

Feature

Specifies features used by the mapper, separated by vertical bars. These specify that a game will run correctly in a subset of a mapper, such as one that fits in a smaller CPLD or FPGA than the full mapper. An emulator is not required to care about this, but a debugging emulator MAY raise a stink if a program uses an unlisted feature. Reproduction carts using new EEPROMs with the original ASIC mapper on a donor board need not care about this either. The possible features depend on which mapper is in use:

MMC5: SquareWave, PCM_Write, PCM_Read, PCM_Zero_IRQ, PRGmode0, PRGmode1, PRGmode2, PRGmode3, CHRmode0, CHRmode1, CHRmode2, CHRmode3, RAM_Protect, ExNametable, ExAttribute, ExRAM, ExRAM_Protect, ExRAM_Write_Zero, FillMode, Vsplit, Scanline_IRQ, Multiply.
MMC3: PRGmode0, PRGmode1, CHRmode0, CHRmode1, RAM_Protect, Scanline_IRQ

Mirror

Set the mirroring. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

H: Horizontal.
V: Vertical.
1: One screen.
4: Four screen.
?: Anything other than specified here (usually this means dynamically controlled mirroring).

RAM

Specify the amount of PRG RAM used in the cartridge, in bytes. If the file is NES 2.0 format, the number specified here MUST NOT be greater than the PRG RAM amount in the NES 2.0 header (although it is allowed to be less, but usually shouldn't be).

BusConflict

Specify if bus conflict is used. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

No: Require not bus conflict.
Yes: Require bus conflict.

Audio

Use of expansion audio. Can be No and Yes.

Verilog

Version number of Verilog and/or extension of Verilog in use. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars. This is only for use with mapper 768 submapper 1.

Switch

This block specifies the name and default settings of VS Unisystem switches. The names are given by Name0 to Name7, and the default value is given by Default0 to Default7 which have the values 0 and 1.

Emulator

Specify klugy features of specific emulators. The key is the name of the emulator; the value is not described here.

Dump

Information about who dumped the ROM image from the cartridge, what hardware/software is used, etc.

Hardware

Specify what NES/Famicom hardware and hardware clone it is tested with. The values are:

Work: It works.
NotWork: It doesn't works.
Partial: It works partially; probably it is good enough.
Untested: It is not tested.

The keys are (not limited to):

Nintendo: The official hardware from Nintendo. (It ought to work!)

EmuTest

Same as the Hardware block, but for emulators. You can also specify version numbers in this block, separated by vertical bars.

Tag

Miscellaneous metadata for use with search engines. (The format is not currently specified here.)

File

This block indicates what files are included, and what purpose of the files. The keys are the filename, and the values specify what they mean. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

ROM: ROM image file; usually implied (so is not needed).
Documentation: Documentation in HTML, XHTML, DocBook, DVI, DjVu, PDF, PostScript, or PCL format.
DocumentationASCII: Documentation in plain ASCII text. (This is separate from the above since plain ASCII has no "magic number" to detect, unlike all the above formats.)
MetaFont: METAFONT file for fonts used in DVI.
SourceCode: Source codes.
Disk: A disk image (in QDI format; not needed for FDS format).
Icon: Icons for use with iPhone, Android, etc.
License: License file (normally in plain ASCII text).
ADPCM: ADPCM waveform data for expansion audio.
Label60: Label for 60-pins cartridge.
Label72: Label for 72-pins cartridge.
Boxart: Box art.
BIOS: FDS BIOS ROM. (Normally there is no need to use this type even for FDS games, since the BIOS is not normally included with the disk image. However, it might be helpful in some cases.)
Palette: Recommended RGB palette data (for RGB mode only). It is not necessarily going to be used, but it can improve the color slightly.
Enhance2xCHRROM: Double-resolution CHR ROM for enhancement.
EnhanceData: Miscellaneous files for enhancement, refer by other files such as cue files.
EnhanceAudioCue: Cue file for telling what sounds to play when values are written to RAM. (TODO: Specify format of this file.)
EnhanceTiles: File containing full-color tiles mapping to CHR ROM bank/attribute pairs. (TODO: Specify format of this file.)
InstrumentsFM: File of exactly 120 bytes containing OPLL-format FM instruments numbered 1 to 15. (There is actually only one set of instruments, but unfortunately they may be unknown; this file may be provided if the author of a homebrew VRC7 game does not know the correct settings and/or believes it sounds best with specific settings.)
SaveGame: Default initial contents of battery RAM. (PRG RAM comes first if the cartridge uses battery RAM for both PRG and CHR)
DatachEEPROM: Shared EEPROM data for mapper 157; writable (and may not be distributed with the game). (If not specified, the emulator should create its own file.)

Memory

Specify the memory mapping of the ROM and RAM for this game, for purpose of debugging, cheat codes, ROM hacks, etc. (TODO: need to specify details)

Enhance

This block lists enhancements that might be used in some emulators (the emulator should offer an option to turn them off, even if they are supported, though). Some may work on hardware too, but that does not usually affect the cartridge, so this block is probably not used when loading on hardware.

PopReduction

Values can be No or Yes. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

CueAudio

Values can be No or Yes. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

PointingDeviceRAM

This is used to write the coordinates of a pointing device into RAM. There are multiple values separated by commas, as follows:

RAM address for X coordinate.
RAM address for Y coordinate.
Leftmost coordinate.
Rightmost coordinate.
Topmost coordinate.
Bottommost coordinate.

SpriteLimit

Values can be 8, 15, or NoLimit. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

8
Normal sprite evaluation. Clear secondary OAM in 1-64, evaluate starting at 65, fetch patterns every 8 dots starting at 261.
15
Optimized sprite evaluation. Clear secondary OAM in 1-30, evaluate starting at 31, fetch patterns every 4 dots starting at 261.
NoLimit
No limit of sprites on one scanline. If evaluation or fetch overflows the allotted time, mapper side effects are disabled until it completes.

HighScore

This is a list of RAM addresses separated by vertical bars, which store high score data. The emulator might choose to somehow make them persist, or to do other things with it.

ScreenMode

Values can be Normal, 2xCHRROM, Tiles, Overlay2xPPU, Super2xSaI, Scale2x, or hq2x. You can have multiple values separated by vertical bars.

Overscan

Four numbers separated by commas. The first is the number of top lines that can be safely cut off, second is bottom lines, third is left side, fourth is right side. (It should not assume that they necessarily will be cut off; only that it can be.)

GameGenie

Contains unencoded Game Genie codes. The keys are the name of the code, and the value are one or more 32-bit numbers separated by vertical bars (normally written in hex format, with 0x prefix).

Bit14-bit0: Low 15 bits of address. High bit is always set.
Bit15: Set if this is a compare code.
Bit23-bit18: Value to read from that address.
Bit31-bit24: If it is a compare code, the value will not be changed unless it matches the value placed here.

Example

(Note: This is a old example! The stuff above is correct; not necessarily as shown in this example!)

[Main]
Title="Famicom Hangman"
TV=NTSC|RGB ; NTSC and RGB both work (emphasis bits are not used)
License=Unofficial ; Not officially license by Nintendo

[Controller]
Players=1 ; Single player game
Player1= ; Player 1 controller is explicitly not used.
Expansion=Keyboard ; Using Famicom keyboard
Player2=|StandardMicrophone ; Player 2 controller is optional, and can use the microphone if available

[License]
Name="Public domain"
Watermark=No ; Copies are not watermarked
Copy=Allow
Modify=Allow
Commercial=Allow

[Mapper]
Mirror=H|V|1|4 ; Program doesn't care about nametablem mirroring
RAM=0 ; PRG RAM is not used (this line is redundant if the ROM image is NES 2.0)
BusConflict=No|Yes ; Program doesn't care if bus conflicts are used or not

VRC6 audio

Konami's VRC6 mapper provided 3 extra channels for sound: two pulse waves, and one sawtooth. All channels operate similarly to the native channels in the NES APU.

On some boards, the A0 and A1 lines were switched, so for those boards, registers will need adjustment when emulating ($x001 will become $x002 and vice versa). Registers listed here are how they are for 悪魔城伝説 (Akumajou Densetsu, iNES mapper 024). For Madara and Esper Dream 2 (iNES mapper 026), you will need to adjust the registers.

Contents

1 Registers

1.1 Frequency Control ($9003)
1.2 Pulse Control ($9000,$A000)
1.3 Saw Accum Rate ($B000)
1.4 Freq Low ($9001,$A001,$B001)
1.5 Freq High ($9002,$A002,$B002)

2 Pulse Channels
3 Sawtooth Channel
4 Output
5 References

Registers

Overall map of VRC6 audio registers

Base | +0 | +1 | +2 | +3
$9000 | Pulse 1 duty and volume | Pulse 1 period low | Pulse 1 period high | Frequency scaling
$A000 | Pulse 2 duty and volume | Pulse 2 period low | Pulse 2 period high |
$B000 | Saw volume | Saw period low | Saw period high | (mirroring control)

Frequency Control ($9003)

Normally you should write $00 to this register on startup to initialize it, and not make any further writes to it. This is what all three original VRC6 games do.

$9003 controls the overall frequency of the VRC6 audio.

7  bit  0
---- ----
.... .ABH
      |||
      ||+- Halt
      |+-- 16x frequency (4 octaves up)
      +--- 256x frequency (8 octaves up)

H - halts all oscillators, stopping them in their current state
B - 16x frequency, all oscillators (4 octave increase)
A - 256x frequency, all oscillators (8 octave increase)

The halt flag overrides the other flags.

The 256x flag overrides the 16x flag.

The 16x/256x flags effectively control a 4-bit and 8-bit right shift of the 12-bit period registers.

Pulse Control ($9000,$A000)

$9000 controls Pulse 1
$A000 controls Pulse 2

7  bit  0
---- ----
MDDD VVVV
|||| ||||
|||| ++++- Volume
|+++------ Duty Cycle
+--------- Mode (1: ignore duty)

Saw Accum Rate ($B000)

7  bit  0
---- ----
..AA AAAA
  ++-++++- Accumulator Rate (controls volume)

Freq Low ($9001,$A001,$B001)

$9001 controls Pulse 1
$A001 controls Pulse 2
$B001 controls Saw

7  bit  0
---- ----
FFFF FFFF
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Low 8 bits of frequency

Freq High ($9002,$A002,$B002)

$9002 controls Pulse 1
$A002 controls Pulse 2
$B002 controls Saw

7  bit  0
---- ----
E... FFFF
|    ||||
|    ++++- High 4 bits of frequency
+--------- Enable (0 = channel disabled)

Pulse Channels

The VRC6 pulse channels operate similarly to the NES's own pulse channels. The CPU clock rate (1.79 MHz) drives the 12-bit divider F. Every cycle the divider counts down until it reaches zero, at which point the divider resets and the duty cycle generator is clocked.

The duty cycle generator takes 16 steps, counting down from 15 to 0. When the current step is less than or equal to the given duty cycle D, the channel volume V is output, otherwise 0 is output.

When the mode bit M is true, the channel ignores the duty cycle generator and outputs the current volume regardless of the current duty.

Therefore, D and M values provide the following duty cycles:

D value | Duty (percent)
0 | 1/16 | 6.25%
1 | 2/16 | 12.5%
2 | 3/16 | 18.75%
3 | 4/16 | 25%
4 | 5/16 | 31.25%
5 | 6/16 | 37.5%
6 | 7/16 | 43.75%
7 | 8/16 | 50%
M | 16/16 | 100%

When the channel is disabled by clearing the E bit, output is forced to 0, and the duty cycle is immediately reset and halted; it will resume from the beginning when E is once again set. Thus it is possible to reset phase by clearing and immediately setting E.

When using equivalent duty cycle settings for the VRC6 pulse channels, they will appear inverted compared to their 2A03 counterparts.

The frequency of the pulse channels is very similar to the APU pulse channels. It is a division of the CPU Clock (1.789773MHz NTSC). The output frequency (f) of the generator can be determined by the 12-bit period value (t) written to $9001-9002/$A001-A002.

f = CPU / (16 * (t + 1))
t = (CPU / (16 * f)) - 1

Sawtooth Channel

For the sawtooth, the CPU clock rate drives a 12-bit divider F. Every cycle, the divider counts down until it reaches zero, at which point it reloads and clocks the accumulator. However, it seems that the accumulator only reacts on every 2 clocks.

When clocked, the rate value A is added to an internal 8-bit accumulator. The high 5 bits of the accumulator are then output (provided the channel is enabled by having the E bit set). After A has been added 6 times, on the 7th clock, instead of A being added, the internal accumulator is reset to zero.

For an example, assume an A value of $08

Step | Accumulator | Output | Comment
0 | $00 | $00 |
1 | $00 | $00 | (odd step, do nothing)
2 | $08 | $01 | (even step, add A to accumulator)
3 | $08 | $01 |
4 | $10 | $02 |
5 | $10 | $02 |
6 | $18 | $03 |
7 | $18 | $03 |
8 | $20 | $04 |
9 | $20 | $04 |
10 | $28 | $05 |
11 | $28 | $05 |
12 | $30 | $06 |
13 | $30 | $06 |
0 | $00 | $00 | (14th step, reset accumulator)
1 | $00 | $00 |
2 | $08 | $01 |

If A is more than 42 (floor(255 / 6)), the accumulator will wrap, resulting in distorted sound.

If E is clear, the accumulator is forced to zero until E is again set. The phase of the saw generator can be mostly reset by clearing and immediately setting E. Clearing E does not reset the frequency divider, however, so the first step of the reset saw may appear shortened.

The frequency of the saw is a division of the CPU Clock (1.789773MHz NTSC). The output frequency (f) of the generator can be determined by the 12-bit period value (t) written to $B001-B002. Note that it divides the clock by 14 instead of 16, unlike the pulse channels.

f = CPU / (14 * (t + 1))
t = (CPU / (14 * f)) - 1

Output

At maximum volume, the pulse channels of the VRC6 are roughly equivalent to the pulse channels of the 2A03 (except inverted). The DAC of the VRC6, unlike the 2A03, appears to be linear.

The final mix is a 6-bit DAC summing the two 4-bit pulse outputs and the high 5 bits of the saw accumulator.

References

VRCVI Chip Info by Kevin Horton

Categories: Expansion audio

VRC7 audio

The Konami VRC7, in addition to being a mapper chip, also produces 6 channels of 2-operator FM Synthesis Audio. It is a derivative of the Yamaha YM2413 OPLL, implementing a subset of its features and containing a custom fixed patch set.

VRC7 audio was only used in one game, Lagrange Point. The chip also appears in Tiny Toon Adventures 2, but this cart does not use the audio, and its board lacks required additional audio mixing circuitry.

Contents

1 Registers

1.1 Audio Register Select ($9010)
1.2 Audio Register Write ($9030)
1.3 Register Write Delay
1.4 Internal Audio Registers

1.4.1 Custom Patch
1.4.2 Channels

2 Internal patch set
3 Differences from OPLL
4 References
5 External links

Registers

Audio Register Select ($9010)

7......0
VVVVVVVV
++++++++- The 8-bit internal register to select for use with $9030

This register is write-only.

After writing to this register, the program must not write to $9030 (or $9010 again) for at least 6 CPU clock cycles while the VRC7 internally sets up the address.

Audio Register Write ($9030)

7......0
VVVVVVVV
++++++++- The 8-bit value to write to the internal register selected with $9010

This register is write-only.

After writing to this register, the program must not write to $9010 (or $9030 again) for at least 42 CPU clock cycles while the VRC7 internally handles the write.

Register Write Delay

Lagrange Point uses the following delay routine after writes to $9010 and $9030 to ensure enough time passes between writes:

wait_9030:          ; JSR to this label immediately after writing to $9030
    STX $0082       ; stores X temporarily (address is arbitrary)
    LDX #$08
@wait_loop:
    DEX
    BNE @wait_loop
    LDX $0082       ; restores X
wait_9010:          ; JSR to this label immediately after writing to $9010
    RTS

Internal Audio Registers

The VRCVII appears to have 26 internal registers. Registers $00-$07 define a custom patch that can be played on any channel set to use instrument $0. Registers $10-$15, $20-25, and $30-35 control 6 channels for FM synthesis. Other register values appear to be ignored.

Custom Patch

Register | Bitfield | Description
$00 | TVSK MMMM | Modulator tremolo (T), vibrato (V), sustain (S), key rate scaling (K), multiplier (M)
$01 | TVSK MMMM | Carrier tremolo (T), vibrato (V), sustain (S), key rate scaling (K), multiplier (M)
$02 | KKOO OOOO | Modulator key level scaling (K), output level (O)
$03 | KK-Q WFFF | Carrier key level scaling (K), unused (-), carrier waveform (Q), modulator waveform (W), feedback (F)
$04 | AAAA DDDD | Modulator attack (A), decay (D)
$05 | AAAA DDDD | Carrier attack (A), decay (D)
$06 | SSSS RRRR | Modulator sustain (S), release (R)
$07 | SSSS RRRR | Carrier sustain (S), release (R)

The patch defines a 2-operator FM unit with a single modulator and carrier. The carrier produces the output tone, and the output of the modulator modulates its frequency. The patch has the following parameters:

$00/$01 T Tremolo applies amplitude modulation at a predefined rate.
$00/$01 V Vibrato applies pitch modulation at a predefined rate.
$00/$01 S Sustain determines whether the operator uses the sustain section of the envelope or not.
$00/$01 K Key rate scaling adjusts the ADSR envelope speed, faster for high frequencies, slower for low ones.
$00/$01 MMMM Multiplier is a multiplier on the operator's frequency according to a lookup table (see below).
$02/$03 KK Key level scaling attenuates the operator at higher frequencies $0 = none, $3 = most.
$02 OOOOOO Modulator output level, this value reduces the modulator volume in 0.75db increments.
$03 Q/W Operator waveform, 0 = sine, 1 = half-wave rectified sine (where sine values less than 0 are clipped to 0).
$03 FFF Feedback applied to modulator according to a lookup table (see below).
$04/$05 AAAA Attack is the speed of the attack fade in after key-on. $0 = halt, $1 = slowest, $F = fastest.
$04/$05 DDDD Decay is the speed of the decay fade to sustain after attack. $0 = halt, $1 = slowest, $F = fastest.
$06/$07 SSSS Sustain is the attenuation after decay, in 3db increments. $0 = highest volume, $F = lowest.
$06/$07 RRRR Release is the speed of the release fade to silent after sustain. $0 = halt, $1 = slowest, $F = fastest.

If a note is released before the attack or decay finishes, release begins from the current volume level. If the sustain bit is not set in $00/$01 S, release begins immediately after decay.

If the sustain bit is set in the channel control register $2X S (see Channels section below), the release value in the patch is ignored and replaced with $5.

The modulator's sustain bit ($00 S) also disables the release section of its envelope. If its sustain bit is set, the Attack, Decay, and Sustain portions of the envelope are used, but when the note is released the modulator will continue to sustain while the carrier releases. The carrier does not behave this way: its envelope always enters release when the note is released.

$00/$01 MMMM | $0 | $1 | $2 | $3 | $4 | $5 | $6 | $7 | $8 | $9 | $A | $B | $C | $D | $E | $F
Multiplier | 1/2 | 1 | 2 | 3 | 4 | 5 | 6 | 7 | 8 | 9 | 10 | 10 | 12 | 12 | 15 | 15

$03 FFF | $0 | $1 | $2 | $3 | $4 | $5 | $6 | $7
Modulation Index | 0 | π/16 | π/8 | π/4 | π/2 | π | 2π | 4π

Channels

Register | Bitfield | Description
$10-$15 | LLLL LLLL | Channel low 8 bits of frequency
$20-$25 | --ST OOOH | Channel sustain (S), trigger (T), octave (O), high bit of frequency (H)
$30-$35 | IIII VVVV | Channel instrument (I), volume (V)

Each channel X is controlled by three registers at $1X, $2X, and $3X.

The 8 bits of $1X with a 9th bit from bit 0 of $2X create a 9-bit frequency value (freq). This is combined with a 3-bit octave value from $2X (octave) to define the output frequency (F):

     49716 Hz * freq
F = -----------------
     2^(19 - octave)

The VRC7 is clocked by an external ceramic oscillator running at 3.58 MHz (roughly twice the NTSC NES CPU clock rate, but not synchronized with it), and it takes 72 internal clock cycles to update all of its channels, which means each channel is updated with a frequency of 49716 Hz (or roughly 36 NES CPU clocks). During these 72 cycles, the channels are output in series rather than mixed (like Namco's 163), but because the frequency is so high it is not audibly different from mixed output.

Writing to register $2X can begin a key-on or key-off event, depending on the value in the trigger bit (T). If the trigger bit changes from 0 to 1 (key-on), a new note begins. If it changes from 1 to 0 (key-off), it will begin the release portion of its envelope which will eventually silence the channel (unless release is $0). If the trigger bit does not change, no new key-on or key-off will be generated.

Using the sustain bit (S) in $2X overrides the normal release value for the patch with a value of $5.

Register $3X selects the instrument patch to use, and chooses a volume. Note that volume value is inverted: $F is the lowest volume and $0 is the highest. There is no silent volume value; its output scale is logarithmic in 3db increments.

Internal patch set

There are 16 different instrument patches available on the VRC7. With the exception of instrument $0, which can be controlled by registers $00-$07 (see above), these are hardwired into the chip and cannot be altered.

Exact values for the fixed patch set are not known, but the following table is very close:

     00 01 02 03 04 05 06 07
     -----------------------
 0 | -- -- -- -- -- -- -- --
 1 | 03 21 05 06 B8 82 42 27
 2 | 13 41 13 0D D8 D6 23 12
 3 | 31 11 08 08 FA 9A 22 02
 4 | 31 61 18 07 78 64 30 27
 5 | 22 21 1E 06 F0 76 08 28
 6 | 02 01 06 00 F0 F2 03 F5
 7 | 21 61 1D 07 82 81 16 07
 8 | 23 21 1A 17 CF 72 25 17
 9 | 15 11 25 00 4F 71 00 11
 A | 85 01 12 0F 99 A2 40 02
 B | 07 C1 69 07 F3 F5 A7 12
 C | 71 23 0D 06 66 75 23 16
 D | 01 02 D3 05 A3 92 F7 52
 E | 61 63 0C 00 94 AF 34 06
 F | 21 62 0D 00 B1 A0 54 17

Differences from OPLL

The synthesis core is related to the Yamaha YM2413 OPLL, which is itself a cost-reduced version of the YM3182 OPL2 chip made popular by AdLib and SoundBlaster sound cards.

Register layout is the same.
VRC7 has 6 channels, OPLL has 9.
VRC7 has no rhythm channels, OPLL does (the last 3 channels are either FM or Rhythm on OPLL).
VRC7 built-in instruments are not the same as OPLL instruments.
VRC7 has no readily-accessible status register, under normal circumstances it is write-only; OPLL has an undocumented, 2-bit 'internal state' register.
VRC7 has an internal state output pin (may be serial version of the 2 bit internal state register) and has one output pin for audio, multiplexed for all 6 channels; OPLL has two output pins, one for FM and one for Rhythm, and has no special status pin.

References

VRC7 chip info by Kevin Horton: http://kevtris.org/nes/vrcvii.txt
YM2413 datasheets: http://www.datasheetarchive.com/YM2413-datasheet.html
VRC7 audio test program: http://zzo38computer.org/nes_program/vrc7test.zip
VRC7 patch set revision 8/01/2012: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=6&t=9141
Discussion of modulator sustain: http://famitracker.com/forum/posts.php?id=6804

External links

Programmer's guide to the YM2413 from SMSPower
How logsin and exp tables work in OPL2
Yamaha FM internal bit depths
VRC7 discussion on NESdev BBS
OPL emulator in DOSBox

Categories: Expansion audio

VRC IRQ

Contents

1 Overview
2 Registers

2.1 IRQ Latch
2.2 IRQ Control
2.3 IRQ Acknowledge

3 Operation

Overview

Konami's VRC4, VRC6, and VRC7 share the same IRQ system.

This system is fairly unique, in that it is driven by CPU cycles, yet it can imitate a scanline counter. It does this by having a prescaler that divides the cycles by 113⅔, the number of cycles in each scanline on Famicom, NTSC NES, and Dendy-style PAL famiclones. The scanline on an authentic PAL NES is slightly shorter (106⁵⁄₁₆); if PAL games were to use a VRC, scanline counts would need to be rescaled by ¹⁵/₁₆. Since it is a CPU cycle counter and not a true scanline counter, when enabled it will run even during VBlank, or even when PPU rendering is disabled.

Registers

There are 3 control registers for VRC IRQs: IRQ Latch, IRQ Control, and IRQ Acknowledge (see desired mapper page for which addresses correspond to which register).

IRQ Latch

7  bit  0
---------
LLLL LLLL
|||| ||||
++++-++++- IRQ Latch (reload value)

Note that on VRC4, this register is split across two addresses: one for the high 4 bits, and one for the low 4 bits.

IRQ Control

7  bit  0
---------
.... .MEA
      |||
      ||+- IRQ Enable after acknowledgement (see IRQ Acknowledge)
      |+-- IRQ Enable (1 = enabled)
      +--- IRQ Mode (1 = cycle mode, 0 = scanline mode)

Any write to this register will acknowledge the pending IRQ. If this register is written to with 'E' set, the IRQ counter is reloaded with the latch value, and the IRQ prescaler is reset. If 'E' is clear, the IRQ counter and prescaler remain unchanged. The 'A' bit here has no immediate effect, and remains unused until IRQ Acknowledge is written to. It can be used to distinguish a one-shot IRQ from a repeated IRQ.

IRQ Acknowledge

7  bit  0
---------
.... ....

Any write to this register will acknowledge the pending IRQ. In addition, the 'A' control bit moves to the 'E' control bit, enabling or disabling IRQs. Writes to this register do not affect the current state of the IRQ counter or prescaler.

Operation

When in scanline mode ('M' bit clear), a prescaler divides the passing CPU cycles by 114, 114, then 113 (and repeats that order). This approximates 113+2/3 CPU cycles, which is one NTSC scanline. When the prescaler is reset (by writing to the IRQ Control register with 'E' set), the sequence is reset and it will be 114 CPU cycles before the IRQ counter will be clocked.

A simple way to emulate this behavior is to have the prescaler start at 341 and subtract 3 every CPU cycle. When it drops to or below 0, increment it by 341 and clock the IRQ counter.

When in cycle mode ('M' bit set), the prescaler is effectively bypassed, and the IRQ counter gets clocked every CPU cycle.

When the IRQ counter is clocked:

If IRQ counter is $FF, reload IRQ counter with latch value 'L', trip IRQ
otherwise, increment IRQ counter by 1

If IRQs are disabled ('E' bit clear), neither the prescaler nor IRQ counter gets clocked.

Zapper

The Zapper is a light gun, often associated with the game Duck Hunt. It reads light from a CRT SDTV and sends the brightness of the area where it is pointed on the controller port.

The Zapper can be used in either controller port, though most games will only allow you to use it in controller port #2, leaving port #1 for a standard controller used for navigating through options, moving the view, changing weapons, etc.

The Famicom Zapper is logically compatible, but can only be plugged into the Famicom expansion port and so only read from $4017. The Vs. System Zapper is not compatible[1] (see below).

Contents

1 Output ($4016/$4017 read)
2 Sequence of operations
3 External Links
4 References

Output ($4016/$4017 read)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxT WxxS
   | |  |
   | |  +- Serial data (Vs.)
   | +---- Light sense (0: detected; 1: not detected) (NES/FC)
   +------ Trigger (0: released; 1: pulled) (NES/FC)

There are three hardware variants:

NES
Light sense and trigger are output on bit 3 and 4 of $4016 or $4017, depending on the port.
Famicom
Light sense and trigger are output on bit 3 and 4 of $4017, as if the Zapper were plugged into port 2 of the NES. The pins for bits 3 and 4 in an AV Famicom's controller ports are normally not connected, but there is a published hardware modification to use an NES Zapper.
Vs. System
This Zapper communicates with the same protocol as the standard controller, returning an 8-bit report after being strobed:

0, 0, 0, 0, 1, 0, Light sense (inverted), Trigger

The "light sense" status corresponds to Left and the "trigger" to Right, and Up is always pressed.
Unlike the NES/Famicom Zapper, the Vs. Zapper's "light sense" is 1 when detecting and 0 when not detecting.

Tests in the Zap Ruder test ROM show that the photodiode stays on for about 26 scanlines with pure white, 24 scanlines with light gray, or 19 lines with dark gray. For an emulator developer, one useful model of the light sensor's behavior is that luminance is collected as voltage into a capacitor, whose voltage drains out exponentially over the course of several scanlines, and the light bit is active while the voltage is above a threshold.

The official Zapper's trigger returns "pulled" while it is halfway in, and "not pulled" once it has been pulled all the way to where it goes clunk. The large capacitor (10µF) inside the Zapper when combined with the 10kΩ pullup inside the console means that it will take approximately 100ms to change to "released" after the trigger has been fully pulled.

Sequence of operations

The proper way to implement Zapper support in a game is as follows:

Each frame, check if the player has pulled the trigger. Keep running the game loop and remain in this step until the trigger is pulled.
During vertical blanking, verify that the light gun is not detecting light, to ensure that the player is actually pointing the gun at the screen. If bit 3 is false during vblank, a standard controller is probably plugged in. Do this near the end of your vertical blank code to let the light "drain out" if the gun happens to be pointed near the bottom of the screen. If you are using sprite 0 hit, a good time to read it is right after the sprite 0 hit flag turns off.
Optional: Turn the entire screen white or display white boxes on all targets, and use timed code or a scanline IRQ handler to wait for the Zapper to start detecting light in order to see how far down the screen the Zapper is pointed. This can narrow the set of targets that must be checked in the next step.
For each target the player may hit, display a black screen with a single white ($20) or light colored ($31-$3C) box at the target's location. Wait the entire frame to check if the light sense bit goes low. The sensor may turn on and off in 10 to 25 scanlines, so continue to check throughout a whole frame. If any of the targets is hit, register a 'hit' within the game; if not, move on to the next target or, if there are no additional targets, register a 'miss'.
Restore the screen to its original state.

External Links

Forum post: Zapper test ROMs
Forum post: Zap Ruder: The Zapper test ROM project
Forum post: Zapruder calibration
Forum post: Detecting screen (X,Y) location for the NES Zapper

References

↑ Forum post: VS zapper info?

Categories: Controllers

Glossary

These terms are commonly used in technical discussions about the Nintendo Entertainment System and Nintendo Family Computer. Additional well-known computer science terms are listed at Before the basics, and terms specific to integrated circuits are at Visual circuit tutorial#Terms.

Contents

1 0
2 A
3 B
4 C
5 D
6 E
7 F
8 G
9 I
10 L
11 M
12 N
13 O
14 P
15 R
16 S
17 T
18 U
19 V
20 W
21 Z

0

10NES
The program running on the CIC.
60-pin
Referring to Famicom cassettes. The Famicom and most famiclones for the Asian market use 60-pin cassettes, which have audio passthrough and no lockout chip.
72-pin
Referring to NES Game Paks. The NES and most famiclones for the North American and European markets use 72-pin Game Paks, which have expansion port passthrough and a different lockout chip for each market.

A

Address decoding
Translation of addresses on the console's address buses into chip enables and addresses for the various ROMs and RAMs in the cartridge. In most cartridges, this involves some form of bank switching.
ASIC
Application specific integrated circuit. Used with mappers involving complicated logic that the IC chip is made specific to this purpose.
Attribute
A part of video memory that selects which part of the palette is used for a given sprite or area of the background.
Attribute table
The 64-byte table of background tile attributes at the end of each of the four nametables.
Audio Processing Unit (APU)
The hardware on the NES/Famicom that generates audio output.

B

Background
A grid of tiles (programmed using nametables).
Bank switching
The primary function of a mapper. Because the CPU and PPU don't have enough address space to see the entire ROM at once, the ROM is conceptually divided into "pages" or "banks", where the most significant bits of the ROM address are treated as a page number. The CPU writes a page number to the mapper's port, and the mapper puts this number on the most significant bits of the ROM address to make the selected page visible to the rest of the system. More advanced mappers have "fine-grained bank switching", which makes separate banks available in separate windows of the address space.
Battery RAM
RAM made nonvolatile by the addition of a battery backup circuit. This is used to let the player save progress in games with more than one chapter. Almost all battery RAM in NES games is PRG RAM; a couple games on very uncommon mappers have battery-backed CHR RAM.
BFT
"BFT" in #nesdev does not stand for Big Fake/Fat/Freaking anyThing, Blunt Force Trauma, or aBout Freaking Time. It originated from what amounted to a drinking game around the Broken Film Transition commonly used in the TV series MythBusters. Its use might be politely explained as Break For subsTance.

C

Camera
Abstraction for the part of a world that is displayed on the screen. The illusion of a moving camera is created by scrolling the background and moving all the sprites at once.
Cassette

Japanese term corresponding to the term "Game Pak" used in other markets.
Philips Compact Cassette, the magnetic tape storage medium for the Famicom Data Recorder and for homemade mix tapes of NES game background music.

CHR
Another word for pattern tables, after the traditional name character generator for a tiled background plane.
CHR RAM
An SRAM on the cartridge, usually 8192 bytes, normally mapped at $0000-$1FFF and holding pattern tables.
CHR ROM
ROM in the cartridge which is connected to the PPU, normally mapped at $0000-$1FFF and holding pattern tables.
Checking Integrated Circuit (CIC)
Nintendo's term for what the public knows better as the lockout chip.
CIC clone
A microcontroller generating the same pseudorandom stream as the authentic CIC. Examples include Tengen's Rabbit and Kevin Horton's CIClone.
CIC stun
Freezing the CIC by using a charge pump to pulse negative voltage on the data pins.
CIRAM (Console-Internal RAM)
A 2048-byte SRAM in the NES, normally mapped at $2000-$2FFF on the PPU bus (subject to mirroring controlled by the Game Pak). Holds nametables and attribute tables.
Collision
The coincidence or overlapping of two "objects" which may be made of background tiles, one or more sprites, or a combination of these. Collision detection is done by the software since the Famicom/NES hardware has no collision detection circuitry.
Color Generator RAM (CGRAM)
A 28-entry RAM inside the PPU, holding the palette.
Control Deck
The console itself, into which the Game Pak is inserted and to which the controllers and outputs are connected.

D

Dendy
Russian clone of Famicom using PAL signals but using timings to allow NTSC games to run.
Discrete logic
Mapper logic involving standard digital logic ICs such as 74xx series.
Display list
A set of data to be copied to video memory. On the NES, it is usual to prepare display lists for sprites and the background during draw time and copy them to video memory during vertical blank.
DRAM
Dynamic random access memory, or memory that needs to be periodically refreshed.
Draw time
Time outside vertical blanking, when the PPU is busy drawing the picture.
Duty cycle
The fraction of a cycle a signal stays high. For example, most input clock signals have a duty cycle of 50%. The pulse channels in the APU have a variable duty cycle.

E

Expansion audio
Extra audio in the cartridge in a few games, used in Famicom only, not in NES.

F

Famiclone
A third-party clone of the NES or Famicom hardware. A few units have swapped APU duty cycles, as 12.5, 50, 25 and 25 negated instead.
Family Computer, Famicom, FC
The Japanese version of the NTSC NES, with a few minor hardware differences.
Fixed bank
A window of address space that always points to the same bank, or the bank that appears in this window. Because a fixed bank is unaffected by bank switching. Often used to store interrupt handlers, code that accesses large amounts of data spread across several banks, or anything else that must always be available. Several mappers fix the last bank of the PRG ROM at $C000-$FFFF or $E000-$FFFF. Mappers that use outer bank switching will have a separate fixed bank for each outer bank.
Flip
Reflection of an image. For example, a "vertical flip" turns an M into a W as the pixels move vertically across a horizontal axis.
Forced blanking
Turning off the rendering circuitry by writing zero to $2001, giving the CPU the same access to VRAM through the PPU ports that the CPU normally has during vertical blanking.
Front-loader
NES-001, the original version of the 72-pin NES. It uses a pseudo-ZIF socket for Game Paks.
Four screen
A mapping of cartridge memory to the PPU bus that expands the memory available for nametables to 4K, thus allowing four distinct nametables.

G

Game Genie
A lock-on unit developed by Codemasters and distributed by Galoob that patches NES games with user-entered single-byte changes.
Game Pak
A cartridge for a Nintendo console. It contains ROMs, mappers, and possibly other circuitry.
Golf
Aggressive micro-optimization of a program for speed or size, often as a friendly competition to produce the fastest or smallest version of a particular routine. Compare the concept of "frame wars" in the tool-assisted speedrun community. In practice, golf is far less necessary on the NES than on the Atari 2600 except in a few cases. These include squeezing 17K of code into 16K for an NROM-128 release, squeezing a routine into a ROM hack of an already tightly packed game such as Super Mario Bros., getting a routine to finish in one frame or one vertical blank, or producing a code library used by other programs that have a similar reason to be space or time efficient.

I

IRQ
Interrupt request, a maskable hardware interrupt. Used most often by external hardware to do split-screen scrolling or to trigger events (like disk-loading on the Famicom Disk System or ending a game on the NES-EVENT boards).

L

Left pattern table
The pattern table at PPU $0000-$0FFF. So-called due to display conventions in debugging emulators.
Lock-on
Referring to a cartridge with two connectors: one to connect to the console and another to connect to another cartridge to use its CIC and/or to modify its program.
Lockout chip
Nintendo's scheme used in the front-loading NES to block the use of infringing copies of its games and to reassure retailers that the NES wouldn't have the flood of low-quality games seen on second-generation consoles. Nintendo was successfully sued in antitrust court over this and other practices. It consists of two 4-bit CIC microcontrollers, one in the Control Deck and one in each Game Pak, passing a stream of pseudorandom numbers back and forth.
Lockout defeat
Various ways of getting a program to run without an authentic CIC. These include CIC clone and CIC stun.

M

Mapper
Circuitry on the Game Pak to perform address decoding and counting.
Mapper hack
A patch to a ROM that uses one mapper to make it work with a different kind of mapper.
Memory Management Controller (MMC)
Name for ASIC mappers made by Nintendo.
Metatile
A block of tile numbers written to the background as a unit. These blocks, often 2x2 tiles (16x16 pixels) in size, are common building blocks for area maps in NES games.
Mirroring
Presence of one memory area at more than one place in the memory map. In the PPU memory, mirroring is used in the nametables to repeat the screen horizontally or vertically, thus the distinguishing terms "horizontal mirroring" and "vertical mirroring" are used.
Multicart
A cartridge containing several otherwise unrelated programs.

N

Nametable
Any of four areas in VRAM (PPU addresses $2000-$23FF, $2400-$27FF, $2800-$2BFF, $2C00-$2FFF) specifying which tiles to display at which places in the background. Each is 32 by 30 tiles and ends with an attribute table.
NMI
Non-maskable interrupt. Used in NES/Famicom for vertical blank.

O

Object Attribute Memory (OAM)
A 256-byte DRAM inside the PPU holding the sprite display list.
Outer bank
A large bank that encompasses a complete set of smaller banks. A mapper supporting an outer bank has one set of ports for "normal" bank switching and a second set of ports that switches higher address lines to make completely separate programs appear. It usually even switches otherwise fixed banks. Used most commonly in multicarts.

P

Palette
A color lookup table.
Pattern table
Two 4096 byte areas of video memory, mapped at PPU $0000-$0FFF and $1000-$1FFF. Each contains 256 tiles.
Picture Processing Unit (PPU)
It generates the video signal.
Piggyback
Synonym for lock-on used by Home Entertainment Suppliers (HES).
Port
An address mapped to input or output instead of ROM or RAM.
PRG
Memory in the cartridge on the CPU's bus. Short for "program".
PRG RAM
RAM in the cartridge on the CPU bus, in contrast to the internal RAM at $0000-$07FF which is usually called main RAM, system RAM, or just RAM. With few exceptions, PRG RAM is located at $6000-$7FFF and decoded with the equivalent of a circuit like this inside the mapper.
PRG ROM
ROM on the CPU's bus, containing a program to be executed and data for the program to use. In games using CHR RAM, it may also contain data to be copied to CHR RAM.
Priority
Which graphics appear in front of other graphics. In general, sprites earlier in OAM appear in front of later sprites, and a sprite may appear in front of or behind the background.
Proportional font
A font whose glyphs (character pictures) have different widths. These can fit more text onto the screen than the more common monospace (fixed-width) fonts but are rarely used on NES because of the processing overhead involved with drawing each line of text.

R

Ratchet scrolling
Scrolling that is only allowed by the game engine to occur in one direction. Super Mario Bros. is a famous example of this.
Right pattern table
The pattern table at PPU $1000-$1FFF. So-called due to display conventions in debugging emulators.

S

Scrolling
Movement of the visible portion of a background.
Sliver
An 8x1-pixel section of a tile. The PPU operates by fetching 2-byte slivers from pattern tables and passing them through shift registers.
Spin
To repeatedly read a particular address in a loop until its value changes. A program can spin on an input port or on a RAM address that is modified by an interrupt handler.
Sprite
An entry of 4 bytes in OAM, controlling a small block of 8x8 pixels that can be moved around on the screen. It has X and Y coordinates, a tile index into one of the pattern tables, vertical and horizontal flip switches, and priority.
Sprite limit
The PPU cannot render more than eight sprite slivers on one scanline. Sprites beyond the eighth will drop out.
Sprite zero hit
A non-transparent sprite (pixel) at OAM[0] overlaps a non-transparent background pixel, setting bit $40 of PPU register $2002 to true.
SRAM
Static random access memory is memory made with latches, which does not need to be refreshed but takes four to six times as much die space as DRAM. PRG RAM and CHR RAM are generally SRAM. Occasionally, it stands for "save RAM", which means the same as battery RAM.
Stack
An area of memory used to store values in last-in, first-out (LIFO) manner, especially the area at $0100-$01FF used to store return addresses when a subroutine is called.
Strobe
A signal that defines sampling points for another signal. Think of a strobe light that captures the state of whatever it's shining on when it's on to get the analogy.

T

Tile
An 8x8 pixel piece of graphics. Tile data on the NES has 2 bits per pixel, and each pixel in a tile can have one of three colors or transparency.
Top-loader
NES-101, a 72-pin console released during the end of the NES's commercial era that takes cartridges in the top, like most other consoles. It has no lockout chip.
Trainer
In video games, a trainer is a patch to add a cheat menu. In iNES, a "trainer" is an extra 512-byte segment of PRG ROM that can be used by a ROM image that has had a trainer added but is more commonly used by support routines used by mapper hacks for obsolete floppy-disk-based copiers.
Transparent
In the case of overlapping graphics, a transparent pixel means that pixels from the graphics behind this graphic show through.

U

Unlicensed
Referring to video games for the NES published outside of a contract with Nintendo. Most of these use a lockout defeat; a few use lock-on.

V

Variable-width font (VWF)
Synonym for proportional font.
Vector
One of three addresses at the end of the CPU memory map, telling the CPU where to start executing instructions after an interrupt is asserted.
Vertical blank
The interval between video frames.
VRAM
Video RAM. This is a generic term which encompasses CHR-RAM and memory for Name Table and Palettes.

W

Window
A set of contiguous CPU or PPU addresses mapped to a particular bank of memory.
Work RAM, WRAM
See PRG RAM.

Z

Zapper
The light gun for NES.